<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | RebootJeff.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-16T23:12:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Example] Refactoring to Functional JS - Combine Keyed Lists]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/12/11/example-refactoring-to-functional-js-combine-keyed-lists/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-11T09:02:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/12/11/example-refactoring-to-functional-js-combine-keyed-lists</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/20151211/pipe-174918_640.jpg" alt="pipe" /></p>

<p>Why the image of a water pipe with flowing water? It will all make sense soon, my dear reader.</p>

<h2 id="the-premise">The Premise</h2>

<p>Given a bunch of arrays kept within a JavaScript hash table (plain object), we want to extract the arrays and combine them. In other words, we’re given a collection of arrays of elements and we want a single array of elements.</p>

<p>This example was inspired by some code I found in the codebase where I work. The use case was different, but the overall idea (extracting elements from within arrays that are within an object) is the same. To make things slightly more complex, the arrays of the input object could possibly contain <code>null</code> elements because the elements were being provided by a service that could sometimes return <code>null</code>.</p>

<h3 id="example-inputoutput">Example Input/Output</h3>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Example Input/Output Data </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// example input</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> usersBySocialNetwork = {
  <span class="key">twitter</span>: [
    { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span><span class="error">@</span>RebootJeff<span class="error">’</span> },
    { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span><span class="error">@</span>doitwithalambda<span class="error">’</span> },
    <span class="predefined-constant">null</span>
  ],
  <span class="key">facebook</span>: [
    <span class="predefined-constant">null</span>,
    { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span>Kevin<span class="error">’</span> },
    { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span>Bianca<span class="error">’</span> },
  ]
};&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ expected output
<span class="keyword">var</span> users = [
  { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span><span class="error">@</span>RebootJeff<span class="error">’</span> },
  { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span><span class="error">@</span>doitwithalambda<span class="error">’</span> },
  { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span>Kevin<span class="error">’</span> },
  { <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="error">‘</span>Bianca<span class="error">’</span> }
];
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>The output has the <code>null</code>s removed. We can pretty much assume we only want to see user objects in the output array; no other kinds of elements.</p>

<h3 id="the-original-solution">The Original Solution</h3>

<p>The following code snippet is a slightly modified version of someone else’s work. I’ve changed the variable names and comments, but the core logic/algorithm is the same.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Original Solution </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> _ = require(<span class="error">‘</span>lodash<span class="error">’</span>);&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;function combineKeyedArrays(keyedArrays){
  var flattened = [];&lt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>p&gt;

<span class="tag">&lt;p&gt;</span>// produce a flat Array from an Object with values that are arrays
  _.each(keyedArrays, function(array){
    flattened = flattened.concat(array);
  });<span class="tag">&lt;/p&gt;</span>

&lt;p&gt;<span class="comment">// only return the truthy elements of flat Array</span>
  <span class="keyword">return</span> _.filter(flattened, <span class="keyword">function</span>(element) {
    <span class="keyword">return</span> Boolean(element);
  });
}
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>

<ul>
  <li>The combination of <code>_.each</code> and <code>Array.prototype.concat</code> creates one big array from all the arrays within the input object called <code>keyedArrays</code>.</li>
  <li>The combo of <code>filter</code> and <code>Boolean</code> rids the big array of falsey values to ensure no <code>null</code> elements end up in the output.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="lets-refactor">Let’s Refactor!</h2>

<h3 id="refactor-1---using-lodashs-chain">Refactor 1 - Using Lodash’s Chain</h3>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Refactored Version 1 </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> _ = require(<span class="error">‘</span>lodash<span class="error">’</span>);&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;function combineKeyedArrays(keyedArrays){
  return _.chain(keyedArrays)
    .reduce(concatArray, [])
    .filter(Boolean)
    .value();
}&lt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;<span class="keyword">function</span> <span class="function">concatArray</span>(arr, val) {
  <span class="keyword">return</span> arr.concat(val);
}
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Sadly, we need to create our own <code>concatArray</code> because Lodash doesn’t have such a utility method (I swear it used to exist in an earlier version …maybe).</p>

<p>Thankfully, we can actually use Lodash’s <code>reduce</code> on objects (not just arrays). I see the replacement of <code>each</code> with <code>reduce</code> as a win because the end result is more expressive. <code>each</code> is vague whereas <code>reduce</code> makes it more clear that we intend to go from a collection of things (in this case, a collection of arrays) to just a single thing (in this case, just a single array).</p>

<h3 id="refactor-2---using-lodashs-flow">Refactor 2 - Using Lodash’s Flow</h3>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Refactored Version 2 </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> _ = require(<span class="error">‘</span>lodash<span class="error">’</span>);&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;var combineKeyedArrays = _.flow(
  _.values,
  _.flatten,
  _.compact
);
</span></span></pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Now we use <a href="https://github.com/MostlyAdequate/mostly-adequate-guide/blob/master/ch5.md">function composition</a> via <code>flow</code>, which uses left-to-right direction. Standard function composition via <code>compose</code> would read from right-to-left, but I prefer LTR for a more familiar aesthetic. My friends who are more advanced in <a href="/blog/categories/functional-programming/">functional programming</a> assure me I’ll get used to the RTL direction if I give it a shot, but for now, I protest (i.e., I’m lazy).</p>

<p>With <code>flow</code>, we can read <code>combineKeyedArrays</code> as a series of 3 steps. First, we extract values from an object via <code>values</code>, then we flatten the resulting array via <code>flatten</code>, then we reject any falsey elements from the array via <code>compact</code>.</p>

<p>Notes:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code>values</code> obviates the need for the combo of <code>reduce</code> + <code>concat</code></li>
  <li><code>flatten</code> is <em>shallow</em> by default</li>
  <li><code>compact</code> obviates the need for the combo of <code>filter</code> + <code>Boolean</code></li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>OMG WHERE DID THE INPUT/PARAMETER GO?!</p>

  <p><strong>–You (probably)</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>We can stop referring to the input as <code>keyedArrays</code>. Our function <code>combineKeyedArrays</code> has now been written in a <strong>pointfree (aka point-free aka tacit) style</strong>. In other words, we no longer need to name - and refer back to - any parameter variable.</p>

<p>Think of it like the verbs “hit” and “type” in the English language. The word “hit” is a bit vague, so you probably should include more context or <em>references</em> for clarity. Are you hitting a person in a fight? Are you hitting some books to study? Are you hitting the bed to sleep? Are you hitting a keyboard button to type?</p>

<p>The word “type” is more specific. You already can infer you’ll be dealing with a keyboard. You don’t need to mention the keyboard at all when you use the verb “type” instead of the verb “hit”.</p>

<p>“I’m typing UNIX commands” is more concise and direct than “I’m hitting buttons on the keyboard to issue UNIX commands”. Both are valid, but the former is easier to understand even though it’s less comprehensive.</p>

<h3 id="refactor-3---using-ramda">Refactor 3 - Using Ramda</h3>

<p>Now, let’s translate from Lodash to <a href="http://ramdajs.com/">Ramda</a>, a utility library that is much more aligned with the functional programming style. I’ve covered how to get started with Ramda in <a href="/blog/2015/06/14/refactoring-towards-functional-programming-in-javascript/">an earlier blog post that one friend labeled as an “excellent summary”</a>. I must be pretty awesome <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/?q=awesome+smiley+face&amp;iax=1&amp;ia=images&amp;iai=http%3A%2F%2Fannawrites.com%2Fblog%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2012%2F03%2Fawesome-smiley.jpg">:D</a>.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Refactored Version 3 </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> R = require(<span class="error">‘</span>ramda<span class="error">’</span>);&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;var combineKeyedArrays = R.pipe(
  R.values,
  R.unnest,
  R.filter(Boolean)
);
</span></span></pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Notes:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code>pipe</code> is Ramda’s <code>_.flow</code>. I appreciate the name “pipe” over “flow” because “pipe” reminds me of Bash’s <code>|</code> operator.</li>
  <li><code>unnest</code> is Ramda’s <em>shallow</em> array-flattening method.</li>
  <li>Ramda lacks a <code>compact</code> :(</li>
  <li><code>R.filter(Boolean)</code> is leveraging <a href="https://github.com/MostlyAdequate/mostly-adequate-guide/blob/master/ch4.md">currying</a> / using partial application to yield the same effect as <code>_.compact</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="lets-review">Let’s Review</h2>

<p>We’ve gained so much:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Expressiveness!</strong> Remember that <code>each</code> is vague; the refactored versions using <code>flow</code> and <code>pipe</code> are far more direct and straightforward (assuming you’re familiar with the library methods). Also, the combo of <code>_.chain</code> and <code>_.value</code> adds unnecessary boilerplate cruft compared to the simplicity of <code>flow</code> or <code>pipe</code>.</li>
  <li><strong>Brevity!</strong> Shorter code isn’t always better code, but if expressiveness and legibility remain high as code length decreases, that’s generally what scientists refer to as a victory.</li>
  <li><strong>Robustness!</strong> We’re using well-tested library methods. There are fewer possible typos after refactoring to simpler code.</li>
  <li><strong>Fun!</strong> Wasn’t that so much fun?! Hell yeah it was!! <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qEg9wKFGtQg&amp;t=0m05s">*level-up*</a></li>
</ul>

<p>By the way, possible documentation for our refactored, pointfree <code>combineKeyedArrays</code> involves a type signature as a comment, but admittedly, I’m still learning how to do proper, FP-style type signatures. Also, keep in mind that the names of your functions should help tell others what it does, and the fact that it’s composed of 3 easy-to-read methods is quite helpful as well.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Refactored Version 3 with comment for documentation </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> R = require(<span class="error">‘</span>ramda<span class="error">’</span>);&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Object&lt;array&gt; --&amp;gt; Array (more old-fashioned)
<span class="comment">// ...or...maybe...</span>
<span class="comment">// {k: [v]} --&amp;gt; [v] (similar to Ramda docs)</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> combineKeyedArrays = R.pipe(
  R.values,
  R.unnest,
  R.filter(Boolean)
);
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></array></p>

<p>Why don’t we say something more specific such as <code>// {k: [user]} --&gt; [user]</code>? Because <code>combineKeyedArrays</code> clearly works with any type of element inside the arrays. It could even be considered as a utility function and added to an internal library of helpers. Whoooaaaaaa…</p>

<p>And because I appreciate you as a cool person, here’s a <a href="https://gist.github.com/RebootJeff/d8877fdbcff79ec140cf">Gist that has all the code in one spot</a> for your future reference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why fast code matters even when phones have octa-core CPUs]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/11/16/why-fast-code-matters-even-when-phones-have-octa-core-cpus/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-16T09:10:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/11/16/why-fast-code-matters-even-when-phones-have-octa-core-cpus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you seen the new Nexus 6P smartphone? It packs a “system on a chip” that features <em>two</em> CPUs, each with <em>four</em> cores. What a crazy, powerful world we live in! Surely modern smartphones can run your JavaScript code without breaking a sweat, right?</p>

<p><img src="/images/20151116/ss_snapdragon810.png" alt="Snapdragon 810 promo material" /></p>

<h2 id="writing-performant-code-is-hard">Writing Performant Code is Hard</h2>

<p>It’s true that really low-level performance optimizations often don’t feel like they’re worth learning or worrying about. You’ve got to deal with complicated business logic and juggling user data and state! You don’t have time to record CPU profiles for every new function you write!</p>

<p>On top of that, <strong>computers keep getting more powerful, right?</strong></p>

<h2 id="but-what-does-the-future-hold">But What Does the Future Hold?</h2>

<p>Here’s the insight*: if you’re targeting laptops/desktops, then you can probably feel safe about imperfect code in many respects. However, <strong>the trend of computers getting more powerful isn’t what it seems.</strong></p>

<h3 id="devices-speed-up-after-slow-starts">Devices speed up after slow starts</h3>

<p>Look at the trend from a bigger picture perspective: modern tech has gone from powerful desktops to less powerful laptops (and netbooks and Chromebooks!) to even less powerful smartphones/tablets to much less powerful wearables and IoT devices. Consider that smartphone apps might not be so popular if web apps were more performant earlier in the history of iOS, Android, and web views.</p>

<p><em>*Disclaimer:</em> I can’t take credit for the insight. I read it somewhere on the Internet, and I don’t remember where. Probably Quora though.</p>

<p>I’ll also add my own thought to chew on: Memory optimizations might still be important as folks browsing the web tend to leave a ton of tabs open and don’t close/reopen their browsers as often as they used to.</p>

<h2 id="whats-a-well-intentioned-developer-to-do">What’s a well-intentioned developer to do?</h2>

<p>To be fair, browsers have come a long way. And it can be tough to care about tiny performance optimizations when browsers might end up handling them for you. For example, string concatenation used to be a no-no in JavaScript. The recommended best practice was to use <code>Array.prototype.join</code> instead of string concatenation.</p>

<p>This “best practice” is now <a href="http://archive.oreilly.com/pub/a/server-administration/excerpts/even-faster-websites/writing-efficient-javascript.html">very outdated</a>.</p>

<p>Like most decisions in reality, there will be trade-offs and ROI concerns. Like most decisions, the right answer is probably somewhere in between two extremes. Like most of my commentary on this blog, I’m dispensing info with JavaScript in mind, but some takeaways are language-agnostic.</p>

<p>My decision-making process for how to spend my time on performance involves a few key points:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Always stay curious about current best practices.</li>
  <li>Don’t learn a “best practice” and expect it to remain “best” forever. If someone teaches you a performance optimization tactic, check the Internet to make sure it’s still relevant.</li>
  <li>Focus on higher-level performance optimizations (e.g., learning <a href="https://blog.codeschool.io/2015/09/11/how-to-keep-web-animations-from-slowing-you-down/">performant animation techniques</a>, shaming nested loops/traversals, plugging memory leaks, refactoring to recursion for <a href="http://www.2ality.com/2015/06/tail-call-optimization.html">Tail Call Optimization</a>) rather than lower-level concerns (e.g., <code>while</code> loop vs <code>for</code> loop, <code>i++</code> vs <code>++i</code>, etc).</li>
  <li>Learn how code is actually digested by your target platform (e.g., for browser-based apps, <a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/website-performance-optimization--ud884">learn the Critical Rendering Path</a>, learn the <a href="http://blog.carbonfive.com/2013/10/27/the-javascript-event-loop-explained/">JavaScript Event Loop</a> –and Web Workers as a bonus).</li>
  <li>Readability matters. If other devs can’t understand your code because of obscure micro-optimizations, then you’re probably hurting the team. Consider sacrificing the optimizations to prioritize collaboration.</li>
  <li>Keep dreaming for the day when platforms will optimize your code for you! Just kidding. It’s kinda sorta already happening (<a href="https://twitter.com/RebootJeff/status/603281637070123008">learn about JIT compilers</a>).</li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve noticed many of my “key points” really just boil down to “do your best, buddy!” Freaking brilliant.</p>

<h4 id="ps">P.S.</h4>

<p>Because JavaScript is single-threaded, the multi-core loveliness of modern CPUs doesn’t directly help your web app unless you use web workers.</p>

<p>That said, there will be some benefit regardless of web workers just because devices such as smartphones usually have to juggle more than just your web app (e.g., background apps, managing sensors, etc). The extra cores should help prevent the phone from stressing out from the juggling, so that tangentially helps your web app’s performance.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Refactoring Towards Functional Programming in JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/14/refactoring-towards-functional-programming-in-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-14T13:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/14/refactoring-towards-functional-programming-in-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/0b4c12a5daec02b72e6e6879861ac70f75046e65/687474703a2f2f72616d64612e6a637068696c6c697070732e636f6d2f6c6f676f2f72616d646146696c6c65645f323030783233352e706e67" alt="Ramda.js logo" /></p>

<p>This is not a “What is FP?” guide that uses JavaScript. If that’s what you’re looking for, you’ll love <a href="https://github.com/DrBoolean/mostly-adequate-guide">Brian Lonsdorf’s free GitHub-based guide</a>. For this blog post, I will assume you already know currying and composition. I won’t assume you know functors, monads, and the other funky whatchamacallits that I’m still trying to learn for myself.</p>

<p>There are a lot of blogs and presentations that answer “What is Functional Programming?” and “Why bother with Functional Programming?”. There aren’t a lot of resources answering “How do I start using Functional Programming in REAL life?”. Most intro-to-FP resources leave you feeling like you’re supposed to just drop everything and start coding from scratch in Haskell or an FP-focused language that transpiles into JavaScript (e.g., <a href="http://elm-lang.org/">Elm</a> and <a href="https://github.com/clojure/clojurescript">ClosureScript</a>).</p>

<p>My team at work has recently been exploring FP in JavaScript by using a library called <a href="http://ramdajs.com/">Ramda</a>. It’s a functional programming JavaScript library. Ramda offers some common FP utilities to help you code in the FP style or just slowly convert parts of your codebase to the FP style.</p>

<p>Most of the team is unfamiliar with FP, so rather than diving into massive re-writes to convert large chunks of code from Object-Oriented Programming to FP, we’ve been starting small. Along the way, we’ve learned some solid steps for introducing FP into an existing codebase at a comfy pace. The gist of it is: don’t dive into the world of endofunctors, monoids, and catamorphisms. Instead, focus on treating functions differently by cutting down on anonymous functions, subdividing functions into tiny functions, and using the simplest FP concepts such as currying and composition.</p>

<h2 id="code-smells">Code smells</h2>

<p>These are some signs that code is very imperative and not very FP-like:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Anonymous callbacks</strong> - It’s harder to re-use functions that don’t have names, it’s harder to write pointfree code with anonymous <em>callbacks</em> in particular, and function expressions will be more commonplace when you start using more FP (due to frequent use of <code>curry</code> and <code>composition</code>).</li>
  <li><strong>Suboptimal parameter order</strong> - Function signatures should have parameters arranged in an order that fits currying. This means putting config-like parameters first and main data parameters last (which is pretty much the exact opposite order that we’re all used to).</li>
  <li><strong>Loops</strong> - In JS, loops are usually for-loops that iterate over collections. There are specialized methods such as <code>map</code>, <code>reduce</code>, and <code>filter</code> that can perform the most common looping operations in a style that is more functional and declarative.</li>
  <li><strong>Localized mutation</strong> - This is a bit harder to explain, but local mutation (usually limited to the scope of a single function and a few nested anonymous callbacks) generally seems innocent enough until you realize it makes it more difficult to split up your functions into tiny functions, which is a major part of refactoring towards FP.</li>
  <li><strong>Side-effects from functions</strong> - One of the major principles in FP is that <a href="https://github.com/DrBoolean/mostly-adequate-guide/blob/master/ch3.md">functions should be pure</a>. When functions affect data outside their own local scope, it is usually due to IO actions or an OOP construct such as a method operating on the properties of its context object.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="refactoring-steps">Refactoring steps</h2>

<h3 id="easy-difficulty">Easy Difficulty</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Use named functions</strong> - This will make it easier to write pointfree code and to compose functions.</li>
  <li><strong>Use predicates</strong> - Functions that encapsulate conditional statements can be composed with other functions for the FP/declarative equivalent of imperative control flow.</li>
  <li><strong>Refactor loops via <code>each</code>, <code>map</code>, <code>filter</code>, <code>reduce</code>, etc</strong> - Using these FP iteration functions encourage you to also write small helper functions and predicates. They will guide you towards more FP.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="medium-difficulty">Medium Difficulty</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Focus on simple FP utilities</strong> - <code>R.curry</code>, <code>R.compose</code>, <code>R.composeP</code>, <code>R.prop</code>, <code>R.is</code>, <code>R.has</code>, <code>R.anyPass</code>/<code>R.allPass</code> are all worth checking out. Set a goal to use these as much as possible. It’s a great (and reasonable!) goal to get started with the FP style without getting too overwhelmed.
    <ul>
      <li>Using <code>curry</code> and <code>compose</code> get you to the heart of FP’s flexibility. Your code will look significantly different once you start currying and composing functions.</li>
      <li>Dot notation for accessing properties that will be used as input to a function (use <code>R.prop</code> or <code>R.has</code> as needed).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Simplify all functions</strong> - Break down larger functions into smaller functions; break down helper functions into more and more generalized helper functions.
    <ul>
      <li>Minimize the number of arguments</li>
      <li>Write pure functions as often as possible</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Segregate mutation/state</strong> - If mutation/state is absolutely necessary, then try to separate the mutation into a traditional function and the rest into something that can be more FP-like. For example, if a function called <code>foo</code> changes some parent scope variables in addition to performing some calculation, then change <code>foo</code> so it calls two helper functions: the parent scope manipulation is done by one helper function while the calculation is done by another helper function.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="getting-comfortable">Getting Comfortable</h2>

<p>What can you expect as you start writing FP code?</p>

<ul>
  <li>Function names should be very expressive and more verbose.
    <ul>
      <li>…which leads to code that looks more semantic.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Higher-level functions should be composed of smaller, lower-level functions.
    <ul>
      <li>Making functions from functions will look/feel like a tree of nested functions.</li>
      <li>Lower-level functions should be only a handful of lines (and 1-line functions become common-place). Higher-level functions might also be really short because they just rely on calling multiple functions without much additional logic.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Remember: Function compositions are normally read from right to left.</li>
  <li>Debugging may be tricky at first, but you should be able to easily test lower-level functions, which means higher-level functions should be less fragile.
    <ul>
      <li>For debugging with <code>console.log</code>, you may have to add it to compositions. E.g., <code>var processData = R.compose(calculateStuff, logFilteredData, filterData);</code> You can find a more detailed example of this logging tactic later in this blog post.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Naming functions becomes even more important; names no longer always start with verbs because they are often treated as data (nouns) rather than actions/procedures (verbs).
    <ul>
      <li>However, due to FP’s relative obscurity, naming conventions are not as widespread, which could lead to codebases with poorly named functions (significantly more helper functions means more opportunities to get function names messed up). Make sure your team is on the same page for nomenclature.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="examples">Examples</h2>

<p>Keep in mind that I’m using <a href="http://ramdajs.com/">Ramda.js</a> for these examples.</p>

<h3 id="ex-filtering-an-array">Ex: Filtering an array</h3>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Example - Filtering for odd numbers and multiples of 6 </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> originalArray = [<span class="integer">1</span>, <span class="integer">2</span>, <span class="integer">3</span>, <span class="integer">4</span>];&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Bad - using a <span class="keyword">for</span>-loop to mutate a <span class="keyword">new</span> array
<span class="keyword">var</span> filteredArray = [];
<span class="keyword">for</span>(<span class="keyword">var</span> i = <span class="integer">0</span>; i &amp;lt; originalArray.length; i++) {
  <span class="keyword">var</span> number = originalArray[i];
  <span class="keyword">if</span>(number % <span class="integer">2</span> || number % <span class="integer">6</span> === <span class="integer">0</span>) {
    filteredArray.push(number);
  }
}&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Better - using the <span class="reserved">native</span> Array filter method <span class="keyword">with</span> a typical anonymous <span class="keyword">function</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> filteredArray = originalArray.filter(<span class="keyword">function</span>(number) {
  <span class="keyword">return</span> number % <span class="integer">2</span> || number % <span class="integer">6</span> === <span class="integer">0</span>;
});&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Most Functional - using predicates <span class="keyword">with</span> a filter method
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">isOdd</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(number) {
  <span class="keyword">return</span> number % <span class="integer">2</span>;
};
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">isDivisibleBySix</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(number) {
  <span class="keyword">return</span> number % <span class="integer">6</span> === <span class="integer">0</span>;
};
<span class="keyword">var</span> isValid = R.allPass([isOdd, isDivisibleBySix]);
<span class="keyword">var</span> filteredArray = R.filter(isValid, originalArray);
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>The “most functional” technique may seem unappealling because it requires so many lines of code, but it’s vital to remember that predicates serve as re-usable, easily testable utilities. Also, <code>R.allPass([isOdd, isDivisibleBySix])</code> is more expressive than <code>number % 2 || number % 6 === 0</code>. In the latter case, readers must remember how <code>%</code> works and how the result is a number that gets coerced into a boolean value for truthiness/falsiness.</p>

<h3 id="ex-debugging-via-consolelog">Ex: Debugging via console.log</h3>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Example - Adding a logger for debugging </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// Let’s try to debug the following function</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> processData = R.compose(calculateStuff, sortByDate, filterByStatus);&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ First, we need an FP-friendly logger that works <span class="keyword">with</span> composition
<span class="keyword">function</span> <span class="function">log</span>(note, input) {
  console.log(note + <span class="error">‘</span> <span class="error">—</span> <span class="error">‘</span> + input);
  <span class="keyword">return</span> input; <span class="comment">// this return is vital</span>
}&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Second, we insert the logger into the composition to check <span class="keyword">if</span> filtering worked
<span class="keyword">var</span> processData = R.compose(calculateStuff, sortByDate, log(<span class="error">‘</span>filtered data<span class="error">’</span>), filterByStatus);&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Then we run processData <span class="keyword">with</span> some data, check the log output, and adjust
<span class="comment">// the placement of the log within the composition until we find where</span>
<span class="comment">// things go wrong.</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Once again, it may seem a tad painful. You’re being forced to create a special logger function. But much like in the previous example, keep in mind that you’re being forced to create specialized functions that will probably be useful enough to be part of your project’s internal library of utilities and helpers.</p>

<h3 id="ex-promises">Ex: Promises</h3>
<p>Let’s pretend we need to grab data about an animal.
First, we query our database of animals.
Second, we use our query results to get more info from a 3rd-party animal API.
Third, we use some part of that info to search for relevant photos from the Flickr API.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption class='code-header' style='margin-bottom:-5px;'><span>Example - Writing promise chains </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// Bad - using typical anonymous function boilerplate</span>
<span class="keyword">function</span> <span class="function">getAnimalData</span>() {
  <span class="keyword">return</span> getAnimalInfoFromDatabase().then(<span class="keyword">function</span>(response1) {
    <span class="keyword">return</span> getRelevantInfoFrom3rdPartyAPI(response1);
  }).then(<span class="keyword">function</span>(response2) {
    <span class="keyword">return</span> getRelevantPhotoFromFlickrAPI(response2);
  }).then(<span class="keyword">function</span>(response3) {
    <span class="keyword">return</span> response3;
    <span class="comment">// Note: This last part of the promise chain is actually unnecessary, but</span>
    <span class="comment">// newbies tend to include it.</span>
  });
}&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Better - using pointfree style
<span class="keyword">function</span> <span class="function">getAnimalData</span>() {
  <span class="keyword">return</span> getAnimalInfoFromDatabase()
    .then(getRelevantInfoFrom3rdPartyAPI)
    .then(getRelevantPhotoFromFlickrAPI);
}&lt;<span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>/ Most Radtastic - using Ramda<span class="error">’</span>s promise composer
<span class="keyword">var</span> getAnimalData = R.composeP(
  getRelevantPhotoFromFlickrAPI,
  getRelevantInfoFrom3rdPartyAPI,
  getAnimalInfoFromDatabase
);
<span class="comment">// Notice how the order of composition goes from right to left.</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pair Programming Impressions and Tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/12/pair-programming-tips-and-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-12T01:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/12/pair-programming-tips-and-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/20150612/pair_programming_ducks.jpg" alt="two rubber ducks pair programming" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">This is the best photo I've ever taken.</p>

<p>Some programming friends think I’m crazy, but I most definitely &lt;3 pair programming. I dig the human interaction. I appreciate enduring the horrors of debugging with a comrade. I love the anti-ego culture.</p>

<p>On top of all that, pairing reduces the risk of burnout for a couple of reasons. Firstly, the average level of focus stays high throughout the day so you don’t have to work as many hours. Secondly, any stress, tedium, and brain workouts are shared by two folks instead of one. Therefore, individuals are less likely to get overwhelmed or feel alone in handling responsibilities or overcoming blockers.</p>

<p>Admittedly, there are times when I want to get in the flow by myself without the need to constantly talk to another person, but usually, I embrace 1-on-1 talks. Why? (1) Discussion activates more of my brain. (2) <a href="http://rebootjeff.github.io/blog/categories/communication-for-engineers/">I’m a big fan of communication skills</a>. (3) Considering another individual’s perspective gives me more to think about, and I love thinking about thinking.</p>

<p>For nearly 2 years, I’ve been pair programming. During this time, I’ve picked up on a few tips and pet-peeves. Read on for some musings on software development in dynamic duos.</p>

<h2 id="communication-tips">Communication Tips</h2>
<p>These tips are good for all communication, not just pair programming. But bad communication skills become an unavoidable problem when you pair up, so consider improving how you talk and listen to become a better paired engineer.</p>

<h4 id="tone-be-inquisitive-not-accusatory">Tone: be inquisitive, not accusatory</h4>
<p>Another way to put it: be curious about your own assumptions, conclusions, and judgements. Unless you are 100% certain, give your partner the benefit of the doubt.</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>DO:</strong> What if X? Will that affect idea Y?</li>
    <li><strong>DON’T:</strong> Your idea (Y) won’t work because of X.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>DO:</strong> What are the obstacles? Let’s see if we can tackle them together.</li>
    <li><strong>DON’T:</strong> I imagine what we need to do should be easy. Why don’t you think so?</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="precision-be-specific-use-idiomatic-terms-avoid-vague-pronouns">Precision: be specific; use idiomatic terms; avoid vague pronouns</h4>
<p>The below example is more pertinent to a senior teaching a junior, but even proficient engineers get out of sync when generic words like “that one” are used instead of precise words like “the <em>[insert object name]</em> at <em>[insert context or line number]</em>.”</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>DO:</strong> The promise returned by the request at line 31 will resolve with a response body containing the JSON we need to parse and possibly flatten.</li>
    <li><strong>DON’T:</strong> That method call will give us the data we need to check out.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="keyboard--mouse-tips">Keyboard &amp; Mouse Tips</h2>
<p>Maybe it’s just me, but I find it painful to watch someone use only arrow keys to move a cursor or use slow mouse movements to scroll to the top or bottom of a file. Although, I admit that I could be a tad unfair in the typing department (<a href="http://10fastfingers.com/speedtests/generate_screenshot_result/1_102_508_0_0_96_0_97.96_3086_151253">I rock triple-digit WPM</a> so …booya).</p>

<ul>
  <li>Please learn general typing shortcuts such as moving the cursor to beginning/end of word/line/file. Use these cursor movement shortcuts in conjunction with shift/delete to select/remove code quickly.</li>
  <li>Learn IDE shortcuts such as multi-selection/cursors, vertical/block selection, switching tabs, and deleting current line.</li>
  <li>Use the mouse to point at parts of the screen, not your finger. You don’t want to block parts of the screen with your hand/arm, and you don’t want to reach over to your partner’s monitor if you’ve got a setup with dual-mirrored-monitors.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Help a Beginner Debug Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/04/11/how-to-help-a-beginner-debug/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-11T16:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/04/11/how-to-help-a-beginner-debug</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/teachingatmks.jpg" alt="Teaching" /></p>

<p>When I teach JavaScript workshops, I usually have teaching assistants who can help students complete classwork exercises. The TAs mostly focus on helping beginners debug their code rather than just giving solutions and walking through them.</p>

<p>Here’s the advice that I give TAs:</p>

<h2 id="dear-teaching-assistant">Dear Teaching Assistant</h2>

<p>Remember that you should avoid giving away direct solutions. When students ask for your help, they will often not know exactly what puzzles them. They will often just ask, “Can you help me?” rather than asking something more precise such as, “Why doesn’t this function return the value I expect?”</p>

<p>Your role is to understand the particular problem that the student is facing. Try to find out what precise questions should be asked and relay them to the student. This might require vocalizing your step-by-step thought process for solving the problem, and finding the first step that confuses the student.</p>

<p>When debugging, try to debug the student’s code one step at a time. Explain those steps so the student can learn how to debug (e.g., where to put <code>console.log</code>s, which variables need to be checked, etc).</p>

<p>Never give the hungry student a cooked fish. Teach the student how to use a fishing pole, a gutting knife, a cooking fire, and Chrome DevTools.</p>

<p>Do everything you can to show a student <em>how</em> to get the solution. Showing a student the actual solution is the last resort. At that point, you should not only show the student the solution, but walk through it and ask the student questions to test their understanding. Oftentimes, asking a student “do you understand?” is not effective. You will get nods thanks to a superficial level of a understanding. That understanding must be tested by asking the student to walk through the code verbally, asking the student values of specific variables, and so on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
