<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: technical | RebootJeff.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/technical/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-01T16:31:40-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pair Programming Impressions and Tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/12/pair-programming-tips-and-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-12T01:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/12/pair-programming-tips-and-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/20150612/pair_programming_ducks.jpg" alt="two rubber ducks pair programming" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">This is the best photo I've ever taken.</p>

<p>Some programming friends think I’m crazy, but I most definitely &lt;3 pair programming. I dig the human interaction. I appreciate enduring the horrors of debugging with a comrade. I love the anti-ego culture.</p>

<p>On top of all that, pairing reduces the risk of burnout for a couple of reasons. Firstly, the average level of focus stays high throughout the day so you don’t have to work as many hours. Secondly, any stress, tedium, and brain workouts are shared by two folks instead of one. Therefore, individuals are less likely to get overwhelmed or feel alone in handling responsibilities or overcoming blockers.</p>

<p>Admittedly, there are times when I want to get in the flow by myself without the need to constantly talk to another person, but usually, I embrace 1-on-1 talks. Why? (1) Discussion activates more of my brain. (2) <a href="http://rebootjeff.github.io/blog/categories/communication-for-engineers/">I’m a big fan of communication skills</a>. (3) Considering another individual’s perspective gives me more to think about, and I love thinking about thinking.</p>

<p>For nearly 2 years, I’ve been pair programming. During this time, I’ve picked up on a few tips and pet-peeves. Read on for some musings on software development in dynamic duos.</p>

<h2 id="communication-tips">Communication Tips</h2>
<p>These tips are good for all communication, not just pair programming. But bad communication skills become an unavoidable problem when you pair up, so consider improving how you talk and listen to become a better paired engineer.</p>

<h4 id="tone-be-inquisitive-not-accusatory">Tone: be inquisitive, not accusatory</h4>
<p>Another way to put it: be curious about your own assumptions, conclusions, and judgements. Unless you are 100% certain, give your partner the benefit of the doubt.</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>DO:</strong> What if X? Will that affect idea Y?</li>
    <li><strong>DON’T:</strong> Your idea (Y) won’t work because of X.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>DO:</strong> What are the obstacles? Let’s see if we can tackle them together.</li>
    <li><strong>DON’T:</strong> I imagine what we need to do should be easy. Why don’t you think so?</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="precision-be-specific-use-idiomatic-terms-avoid-vague-pronouns">Precision: be specific; use idiomatic terms; avoid vague pronouns</h4>
<p>The below example is more pertinent to a senior teaching a junior, but even proficient engineers get out of sync when generic words like “that one” are used instead of precise words like “the <em>[insert object name]</em> at <em>[insert context or line number]</em>.”</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>DO:</strong> The promise returned by the request at line 31 will resolve with a response body containing the JSON we need to parse and possibly flatten.</li>
    <li><strong>DON’T:</strong> That method call will give us the data we need to check out.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="keyboard--mouse-tips">Keyboard &amp; Mouse Tips</h2>
<p>Maybe it’s just me, but I find it painful to watch someone use only arrow keys to move a cursor or use slow mouse movements to scroll to the top or bottom of a file. Although, I admit that I could be a tad unfair in the typing department (<a href="http://10fastfingers.com/speedtests/generate_screenshot_result/1_102_508_0_0_96_0_97.96_3086_151253">I rock triple-digit WPM</a> so …booya).</p>

<ul>
  <li>Please learn general typing shortcuts such as moving the cursor to beginning/end of word/line/file. Use these cursor movement shortcuts in conjunction with shift/delete to select/remove code quickly.</li>
  <li>Learn IDE shortcuts such as multi-selection/cursors, vertical/block selection, switching tabs, and deleting current line.</li>
  <li>Use the mouse to point at parts of the screen, not your finger. You don’t want to block parts of the screen with your hand/arm, and you don’t want to reach over to your partner’s monitor if you’ve got a setup with dual-mirrored-monitors.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recap of LambdaConf 2015 - Where Brains Explode]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/03/recap-of-lambdaconf-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-03T20:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2015/06/03/recap-of-lambdaconf-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Can you intuit that these slides are about promise-land of virtual filesystems inspired by <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FunctionalProgramming?src=hash">#FunctionalProgramming</a> ? <a href="http://t.co/AGiupUies9">pic.twitter.com/AGiupUies9</a></p>&mdash; Jeff Lee (@RebootJeff) <a href="https://twitter.com/RebootJeff/status/602129973067952128">May 23, 2015</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>On May 21st, I traveled to Boulder for <a href="http://www.degoesconsulting.com/lambdaconf-2015/">LambdaConf 2015</a>, a functional programming (FP) conference. Overall, it wasn’t as beginner-friendly as I had hoped, but it gave me plenty of food for thought as I explore FP. Today, I’m going to summarize some key points and takeaways from the talks that really stuck with me. I didn’t understand everything I heard, but still learned a thing or two …I think.</p>

<h1 id="recaps">Recaps</h1>

<h2 id="keynote-ipecac-for-the-ouroboros-by-paul-phillips">Keynote: “Ipecac for the Ouroboros” by Paul Phillips</h2>
<p>Apparently, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ouroboros">Ouroboros</a> (serpent eating its own tail) in this talk represents all programmers (and perhaps even all computer users) who are eating their own tails by accepting the current model for filesystems (files, folders, directories, etc). Phillips suggests that he has the cure (the ipecac).</p>

<p>What if computers used virtual filesystems? Imagine if filesystems were more like databases, and retrieving files would be like using expressions that define queries and which files to retrieve. You would not need to rely on knowing filepaths and file names. You wouldn’t end up with multiple copies of the same files/folders in various directories. You would rely on useful metadata to get your latest photos. You could even ask for “all the photos with person X” (via facial recognition).</p>

<h2 id="selfish-purity-how-functional-programming-makes-every-day-jobs-easier-by-daniel-spiewak">“Selfish Purity: How Functional Programming Makes Every-Day Jobs Easier” by Daniel Spiewak</h2>
<p>Spiewak claims that FP gurus suck at articulating to non-FP programmers about why FP rocks. According to him, FP’s strengths boil down to reasonability, testability, and concurrency.</p>

<p>As a beginner in the world of FP, I partially agree. For me, it’s easy to grasp why FP rocks in theory, but sometimes it’s hard to understand in practice because it can be so difficult to start writing FP code.</p>

<p>Instead of going on about abstract algebra, Spiewak says FP evangelists should emphasize <strong>reasonability, testability, and concurrency</strong>. For intro classes, FP teachers should focus less on manipulating data and more on how to do data-centric programming instead of behavior-centric programming.</p>

<h3 id="reasonability">Reasonability</h3>
<p>FP emphasizes data over behavior, and it’s easier to reason about data than behavior (especially if the behavior can be different due to side-effects, implicit inputs, etc –in other words, impurity makes it difficult to reason about behavior).</p>

<h3 id="testability">Testability</h3>
<p>Side-effects leads to difficult testability leads to devs hating testing leads to devs writing fewer/poorer tests leads to lower software quality. This plagues the software industry.</p>

<p>Using FP algebra leads to simpler logic and better testability. By writing a “real” interpreter that performs side-effects and a “fake” interpreter that inspects, testing becomes easy. Free monads enable this pattern. Free monads make it easy to write these 2 “interpreters”.</p>

<h3 id="concurrency">Concurrency</h3>

<ul>
  <li>sequential ~ <code>flatMap</code> or <code>for-</code>comprehensions ~ monads</li>
  <li>Parallel ~ <code>zip</code> ~ applicatives</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Note:</em> In case it isn’t obvious already, I had trouble comprehending this part of the Spiewak’s talk. My understanding is that the purity of FP lends itself to easily distributing computation of expressions and composing the results.</p>

<h2 id="why-i-like-fp-by-adelbert-chang">“Why I Like FP” by Adelbert Chang</h2>
<p>Imperative programming requires you to maintain state in your head. At the very least, you have to remember values stored in all sorts of variables, maybe different state for each iteration of a loop, etc. With imperative programming, your brain uses a lot of energy on maintaining state (and types in an untyped language) when it should be focused on just solving the problem. This is really annoying if you love the expressions from physics/math where you simply derive solutions to problems.</p>

<p>Math has referential transparency (algebra is just lots of substitution), which is straightforward. FP brings referential transparency (and therefore, more algrebraic concepts) into programming.</p>

<h2 id="how-i-learned-haskell-in-5-years-by-chris-allen">“How I Learned Haskell in 5 Years” by Chris Allen</h2>
<p>Or: Thoughts on <strong>teaching</strong> Haskell (and just “teaching” in general).</p>

<p>Allen is a professional Haskeller, but he also does a lot of teaching. He spent a lot of time introducing co-workers to the language, and he eventually created a <a href="https://github.com/bitemyapp/learnhaskell">free guide on Haskell</a>. It was great to hear his perspective on education in the realm of coding.</p>

<ul>
  <li>It took Allen 5 years to learn Haskell because he went through unproductive cycles: complete a tutorial, try a practical project, get frustrated, stop …repeat.</li>
  <li>When he first started teaching, he sucked at it. He emphasizes that his first audiences were test subjects, and novice teachers should be grateful to their first audiences.</li>
  <li>His Haskell book, <em><a href="http://haskellbook.com/">Haskell Programming from first principles</a></em> is for self-learners and doesn’t assume recent Computer Science education. It doesn’t even assume programming experience because going from something like JavaScript to Haskell will feel like starting from scratch anyway (yikes!).</li>
  <li>Handwaving over explanations is problematic. Allen warns that teachers should avoid giving definitions before explanations. That tactic runs counter to how <strong>humans learn via intuition and informal observations that eventually coalesce into formal explanations</strong>.</li>
  <li>I found a few particularly interesting blog posts by Allen:
    <ul>
      <li><a href="http://bitemyapp.com/posts/2014-12-31-functional-education.html">The problem of learning functional programming</a></li>
      <li><a href="http://bitemyapp.com/posts/2014-04-29-meditations-on-learning-haskell.html">Meditations on learning Haskell</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="programming-and-math-by-harold-carr">“Programming and Math” by Harold Carr</h2>
<p>Boom: <a href="http://www4.di.uminho.pt/~jno/ps/pdbc_part.pdf">http://www4.di.uminho.pt/~jno/ps/pdbc_part.pdf</a></p>

<h1 id="further-impressions">Further Impressions</h1>

<h2 id="fp-in-the-real-world">FP in the real world</h2>
<p>Functional programming used to be considered rather academic and unpractical, but nowadays, there are a lot of languages and corresponding communities that make FP friendlier and useful. Consequently, there are plenty of people using FP for “real” software.</p>

<h2 id="fp-languages">FP languages</h2>
<p>Judging from the conference, Scala, Clojure, and Haskell are the most popular functional programming languages. Haskell seems to have the fewest programmers, but the most momentum/interest. Not only is Haskell favored by the purists, but its static type system is lauded as being the near-panacea that programmers don’t realize they need until they learn it.</p>

<p>However, I saw enough Clojure code to walk away impressed by it. It seems far less intimidating than Haskell, but perhaps that’s largely due to my background in JavaScript (JS and Clojure are both dynamically typed). The funny thing is that there seemed to be a theme where Clojure developers end up finding enlightenment in Haskell thanks to its strict ways. Perhaps learning Clojure is the perfect stepping stone for learning Haskell? If you’re intrigued, check out:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.braveclojure.com/getting-started/#1__First_things_first__What_is_Clojure_">Clojure for the Brave and True</a>, an online book</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/ClojureBridge/curriculum/tree/gh-pages">ClojureBridge</a>, organization providing workshops and a free online curriculum</li>
  <li><a href="https://sekao.net/nightmod/">Nightmod</a>, a Clojure-based game-making tool</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
