<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[RebootJeff.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-17T19:56:32-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Protractor E2E Testing: Reveal Element Blocked By Fixed Nav]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/08/17/protractor-e2e-testing-reveal-element-blocked-by-fixed-nav/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-08-17T14:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/08/17/protractor-e2e-testing-reveal-element-blocked-by-fixed-nav</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>End-to-end testing can be pretty tricky. There are a lot of “gotchas” that prove how hard it can be for you to truly think from the perspective of a computer. Ideally, E2E testing is all about writing tests from the perspective of a user, but that’s not going to always provide smooth sailing when writing E2E spec files.</p>

<p>This blog post is going to focus on a gotcha that rears its ugly head when you have a fixed nav bar. Nowadays, it’s pretty common to see fixed nav bars. Let’s use Twitter as an example. Twitter doesn’t use Angular, so you wouldn’t want to test their site using Protractor, but what I’m about to talk about can also be applied to WebDriver (which can be used for non-AngularJS sites).</p>

<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20140817/screenshot_twitter_fixed_nav.png" alt="Twitter nav bar blocking an avatar" /></p>

<h1 id="whats-the-big-deal">What’s the big deal?</h1>

<p>Here’s the problem: <strong>what if we want Protractor to click on the avatar under the fixed nav bar as seen in the screenshot above?</strong> Obviously, a human user would intuitively scroll to find an element before clicking on it. However, Protractor’s perspective is different.</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Example A - E2E spec with potential problem </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
describe(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">&quot;Who to Follow&quot; widget</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>, <span class="keyword">function</span>() {
  it(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">should include avatars that go to other Twitter profiles</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>, <span class="keyword">function</span>() {
    <span class="comment">// get first (index 0) avatar using class-based CSS selector</span>
    <span class="keyword">var</span> avatar = <span class="predefined">$$</span>(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">.who-to-follow .avatar</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>).get(<span class="integer">0</span>);

    <span class="comment">// Will this click always work?</span>
    avatar.click();

    <span class="comment">// assertion of what to expect as a result of the click</span>
    expect(blahBlahBlah).toBe(yadaYada);
  });
});
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<p>When you use <code>.click()</code>, you might expect Protractor (or WebDriver, which serves as the underlying engine for Protractor) will try to scroll the web page until the target element is displayed before clicking. However, Protractor will only scroll until the target element is in the browser <em>viewport</em>.</p>

<p>Now imagine your test suite includes several tests (ooh la la!). In test #1, the actions of the test cause Protractor to scroll to the bottom of the page. In test #2, the test tries to perform the actions of <em>Example A</em>. Therefore, during test #2, Protractor tries to scroll back up the page until the target avatar is in the viewport, but this just brings the avatar directly under the fixed nav bar.</p>

<p>Then Protractor attempts a click by finding the center of the target. So even if a tiny portion of the avatar’s butt is displayed just below the bottom of the fixed nav bar, it won’t be clicked. Instead, Protractor will throw an error saying that the target could not be clicked. The error will also mention that the nav bar would receive the click event.</p>

<h1 id="well-that-sucks-now-what">Well that sucks. Now what?</h1>

<p>There are two main solutions to consider:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Un-fix the nav bar for your E2E tests. –Bleh!</li>
  <li>Add extra scrolling to your E2E tests. –Okay</li>
</ol>

<p>The first solution might not be a great idea because it’s a major alteration for the sake of testing. What if the fixed position of the nav bar causes other issues that your tests will reveal? I believe you want E2E tests to interact with a product that is very close to the product users will interact with. Changing the nav bar’s position just for testing goes against this philosophy. The main exception to this rule is animation: I believe it’s ok to disable animations for E2E testing just because it can take up a lot of time, slowing down your test/build process. Also, animations can just be very cumbersome for automated E2E systems like Protractor to deal with.</p>

<h2 id="solution-how-to-add-pre-click-scrolling">Solution: How to add pre-click scrolling</h2>

<p>The solution I use for dealing with fixed nav bars is to define and use a helper function that invokes <code>element.scrollIntoView(false)</code>. This method is a native DOM element method <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Element.scrollIntoView">that you can read about on MDN</a>. You can’t simply invoke it on a Protractor ElementFinder object. You can’t call <code>elemFinder.scrollIntoView()</code> the same way you call <code>elemFinder.click()</code>.</p>

<p>Also, you may have noticed that <code>false</code> is passed into <code>scrollIntoView</code>. This tells the browser to scroll as far as it can in an attempt to align the bottom of the target element with the bottom of the scroll area. In other words, <strong>this solution only solves issues with fixed nav bars at the <em>top</em> of the viewport.</strong> Using <code>element.scrollIntoView(false)</code> will fail if your web app uses a fixed nav bar at the <em>bottom</em> of the viewport.</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Example B - Solution: Helper function to align element with bottom of viewport </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// Inside a separate JS file that contains helper functions...</span>

<span class="comment">// Syntax Option 1</span>
<span class="keyword">function</span> <span class="function">scrollElemToBottomOfView</span>(elem) {
  elem.scrollIntoView(<span class="predefined-constant">false</span>);
}
module.exports.<span class="function">scrollElemFinderIntoView</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(elemFinder) {
  <span class="keyword">var</span> promise = browser.executeScript(scrollElemToBottomOfView, elemFinder);
  <span class="keyword">return</span> promise;
};

<span class="comment">// Syntax Option 2</span>
module.exports.<span class="function">scrollElemFinderIntoView</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(elemFinder) {
  <span class="keyword">var</span> promise = browser.executeScript(<span class="keyword">function</span>(elem) {
    elem.scrollIntoView(<span class="predefined-constant">false</span>);
  }, elemFinder);
  <span class="keyword">return</span> promise;
};

<span class="comment">// Syntax Option 3</span>
module.exports.<span class="function">scrollElemFinderIntoView</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(elemFinder) {
  <span class="keyword">var</span> promise = browser.executeScript(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">arguments[0].scrollIntoView(false)</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>, elemFinder);
  <span class="keyword">return</span> promise;
};
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<p>There are 3 syntax options above because I just wanted to present a few different coding styles. As you can probably tell, <code>browser.executeScript()</code> accepts a couple of parameters. The first one is the script, the second one is the script’s parameter. The script can either be a function (technically speaking, it’s a function reference) or a string representation of the script’s body. Syntax Option #3 was inspired by a Stack Overflow answer for a very similar situation (it was for WebDriver, but it was easy to translate to Protractor).</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Example C - Using the Solution </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// Somewhere inside test code...</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> helpers = require(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">../path/to/helpers</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);
helpers.scrollElemFinderIntoView(avatar);
avatar.click();
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<p>You may have noticed that the solution in <em>Example B</em> mentions promises, but the code in <em>Example C</em> does not use them. My understanding is that it’s not crucial to use every single promise that Protractor and WebDriverJS provide. For example, even though the <code>.click()</code> method returns a promise, you don’t see devs writing Protractor tests with <code>exampleButton.click().then(function() { ... });</code> all the time.</p>

<p>So why did I mention promises in <em>Example B</em>? Just to reinforce the fact that <code>browser.executeScript()</code> will return a promise. By storing the result in a variable called “promise”, it tells other devs what to expect. That said, I admit it may not be terribly valuable. Let me know your opinion on this or any other part of the solution presented here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dev Job Searching Tools Roundup Part 2: Readyforce, The Muse, The Sourcery, AngelList, VC job listings]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/08/14/dev-job-searching-tools-roundup-part-2/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-08-14T18:49:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/08/14/dev-job-searching-tools-roundup-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20140814/code_and_trees.jpg" alt="JavaScript and Palm Trees" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">If you find the right job, you can feast your eyes on sweet code <strong>and palm trees</strong>.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/dev-job-search-tools-part-1">my previous post</a>, I described my experience using LinkedIn, Whitetruffle, Hired, and Dice. This time around, I’m going to cover a crop of sites that I used less extensively. Although they didn’t yield fruitful leads, they’re still pretty interesting to me, and with job searching, you <em>can’t not</em> explore more than a few avenues.</p>

<h1 id="job-sites-and-search-tools">Job Sites and Search Tools</h1>

<h2 id="readyforce">Readyforce</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Job board for entry-level opportunities (mostly for recent college grads)</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> I only browsed Readyforce for a bit</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Give it a shot, but keep expectations low if you’re not a recent college student.</li>
</ul>

<p>The <a href="http://www.readyforce.com/">Readyforce website</a> has undergone a big redesign since my job searching days. I was originally drawn to the site by its large selection of companies listing their open positions. However, the site is clearly marketed towards college grads, and the creators want job seekers to “connect” with employers through their own social(?) network.</p>

<p>When I visited the site a few days ago, it looked quite different. While it does look cooler nowadays, it also feels buggier. On top of that, there doesn’t seem to be a clear way to apply for jobs. Maybe I just don’t understand their model, or more likely: maybe I have to register an account first.</p>

<h2 id="the-muse">The Muse</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Job listing featuring “rich media”</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> Browsing The Muse was so fun that I even signed up for the email newsletter.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Must visit! The site does a fantastic job of profiling each company. Their email newsletter does a pretty bland job of standing out from other self-help resources.</li>
</ul>

<p>I love what <a href="https://www.themuse.com/">The Muse</a> is doing. Muse peeps travel to employers’ offices to take professional photos and record video interviews with current employees to highlight the benefits of working for the employers. It’s great to see photos of cool offices, and although the videos have mediocre audio/visual quality, they still provide some decent insight. The end result is that The Muse feels like a portal for quick tours of hiring companies. I felt like I was getting a fun, behind-the-scenes look at a bunch of tech jobs rather than just browsing endless, cookie-cutter job descriptions like you do with most other job sites.</p>

<p>During my first few visits to their site, I was so enamored with The Muse that I signed up for their email newsletter. That’s right, I actually <em>wanted</em> their spam. Sadly, their emails are pretty lame. Each message uses a click-bait subject line like “This Genius Formula Can Tell You Your Dream Job”. Opening one of these emails just reveals a giant button to take you to their blog where the short articles don’t live up to the hype of their titles/headlines. By the way, the “genius formula” is <code>gifts + passions + values = your calling</code>. <em>Genius</em>.</p>

<h2 id="the-sourcery">The Sourcery</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Recruiting firm that actually lists job opportunities on their site.</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> I talked to a couple of their recruiters, and I got minimal results.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> I’m not a fan.</li>
</ul>

<p>You can find a lot of <a href="http://www.thesourcery.com/job_seekers">job postings on The Sourcery</a>. The companies that use The Sourcery for recruiting will often post on other job sites, but there will be a note at the bottom of the job description that mentions the requirement to apply via The Sourcery. After filling out a job application on The Sourcery, one of their recruiters will let you know whether or not your candidacy will be pursued.</p>

<p>For me, the problems come from the recruiters. They noticed I was a Hack Reactor <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/hackr-diary-weeks-11-12-and-beyond/">grad</a>, and they immediately labeled me as just another coding bootcamp grad –in a bad way. Although they were friendly, the recruiters implied that all coding bootcamp grads are the same, that they’re all “great” <em>junior-level</em> coders, and that they all can’t handle more than the average entry-level job. What’s really weird is that I would get emails from some recruiters telling me that my job application was rejected due to a lack of work experience, but then other Sourcery recruiters would contact me and tell me that they want to interview me for the exact same job. Maybe the recruiters reach out to rejected applicants if the pool of applicants is running low for a particular job.</p>

<p>Obviously, The Sourcery is not the only company that treats bootcamp grads as low-level programmers. This is why Hack Reactor <a href="http://sympatheticvibration.com/hack-reaction-week-8-no-recognition/">doesn’t want you to talk about them during interviews</a>. It’s also why Hack Reactor avoids calling itself a bootcamp. I’m getting off-topic, but the gist is: the bootcamp market is getting bigger, and the quality is very inconsistent. Consequently, the mediocre bootcamps are hurting the reputation for all bootcamps. The Sourcery’s expectations for bootcamp grads have already been adjusted downwards.</p>

<h2 id="angellist">AngelList</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Networking in the startup bubble.</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> I hit the “I’m interested!” button several times without much luck.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Meh. It’s easy enough to use, but results will be hit-or-miss.</li>
</ul>

<p>In my last couple of weeks at <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/hackr-diary/">Hack Reactor</a>, I was instructed to make sure I had 3 online profiles ready to show off: LinkedIn, GitHub, and AngelList. The nice thing about <a href="http://angel.co">AngelList</a> is that you’re more likely to get in contact with an in-house recruiter. You don’t have to go through 3rd party recruiters. The bad thing about AngelList is that you might not get in contact with any one. When I say it’s “hit-or-miss”, what I mean is that I know some colleagues who were contacted via AngelList by several companies, and I know other colleagues who were getting zero interest. There was no apparent reason for the two distinct outcomes.</p>

<p>I was only contacted by a few companies via AngelList, and I wasn’t too interested in them. There are plenty of startups on the site, and if you’re hoping to join a tiny company, you should at least try to use AngelList.In my experience, although some companies reached out to me, none of the contacts yielded real conversations about interviewing. Also, there are a ton of companies that don’t distinguish themselves (i.e., there are a ton of startups in the advertising industry –and their profiles look too similar).</p>

<h2 id="vc-sites">VC Sites</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Easy way to discover jobs (but doesn’t make applying to jobs any easier).</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> Lots of browsing filled me with hope.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Definitely worthwhile, but it’s going to require plenty of effort.</li>
</ul>

<p>Many moons ago, a <a href="https://github.com/Ken123777/megatwillions">ridiculous</a> fellow Hack Reactor grad pointed out that Venture Capital websites tend to have giant lists of job openings for their respective startups. I eventually validated his insight for myself by checking out job lists maintained by:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.sparkcapital.com/jobs/">Spark Capital</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://careers.accel.com/careers_home.php">Accel Partners</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.kpcb.com/careers">Kleiner Perkins</a></li>
</ul>

<p>You can find a huge number of jobs. It definitely helps keep your hopes up, knowing that if you fail a job interview, there are so many other jobs to go for. But the caveat to remember is that these job postings are just like any other: it’s hard to get noticed when applying for a job without a referral/connection. For smaller companies, you have a much better chance, but overall, you will have to apply to a lot of jobs just to hear back from a couple employers. Like with all job openings, I recommend putting in some extra effort by checking LinkedIn (or maybe other social networks like Twitter?) to see if you can contact the employer’s engineers, hiring managers, and/or in-house recruiters.</p>

<h1 id="in-other-news">In other news</h1>
<p>I’m exicted to start a new series of blog posts covering various tips, tricks, hacks, best practices, puzzles, challenges, questions, and mysteries (both solves and unsolved) that I’ve encountered at work. This “Learned On The Job” series will be arriving shortly!</p>

<p>That said, I haven’t finished writing about what I learned from the job search process. More job hunt-related content is still to come (including “WTF moments” :D), but I want to mix things up a bit too. After all, talking about software engineering is more fun than talking about searching for software engineering jobs, right?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dev Job Searching Tools Roundup Part 1: LinkedIn vs Whitetruffle vs Hired vs Dice]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/dev-job-search-tools-part-1/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-06-28T11:14:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/dev-job-search-tools-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20140628/unemployed_easter_bunny.jpg" alt="Unemployed Easter Bunny" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">&#8220;Will Decorate Eggs For Food&#8221; by <a href="http://gratisography.com/">Gratisography.com</a></p>

<p>Back in December of 2013, <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/hackr-diary-weeks-11-12-and-beyond/">I graduated from Hack Reactor</a>. After graduating, I started casually looking for a job, but due to the winter holidays, I didn’t start searching in earnest until early-to-mid January. In hindsight, perhaps I should’ve spent less time searching by myself and more time using Hack Reactor’s network/connections. That said, Hack Reactor encourages grads to look for jobs using all sorts of resources, and I benefited from <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/hackr-diary-weeks-11-12-and-beyond/#overtime-support">other forms of job search support</a> from the HackR staff.</p>

<p>This blog post covers a bunch of online resources I tried out myself. I ultimately found my current job through a recruiter, but that doesn’t mean that job sites felt useless to me. Therefore, I’m happy to share some opinions and experiences with you. Maybe you’ll have better results. At the very least, job sites showed me just how many awesome jobs are available, which kept my spirits up during my battles with job interview stress.</p>

<h1 id="job-sites-and-search-tools">Job Sites and Search Tools</h1>

<h2 id="whitetruffle">Whitetruffle</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Employers and job seekers are matched using a system akin to online dating.</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> I only tried out <a href="http://www.whitetruffle.com/">Whitetruffle</a> for a few days. I revisisted sparingly.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Thumbs down. I see potential for the site, but for now, it’s lackluster.</li>
</ul>

<p>It feels a bit hollow. Much like with online dating, everyone makes a profile. Companies look at job seekers’ profiles, and job seekers like you can look at companies’ profiles. There are Like buttons to express interest. Mutual interest leads to a match. A match leads to an email notification. An email notification is <em>supposed to</em> lead to a conversation or some sort of initial phase of job candidacy…right?</p>

<p>You are also given notifications when an employer says they like your profile. The site will nag you to respond to the employer. However, in my experience, employers didn’t respond after I indicated mutual interest. Boooo! This made me wonder if employers just click the Like button on every profile (i.e., spamming) in hopes of stirring up job seeker interest.</p>

<h2 id="hired">Hired</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> “Auctions” occur regularly. During auctions, employers “bid” on you.</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> I went through a couple of auctions, which resulted in a few on-site interviews.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Thumbs up. I will explain some shortcomings, but overall, Hired is looking good.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.hired.com/">Hired</a> is quite an ambitious setup. Job seekers must pass a few coding challenges to enter their pool of candidates, but when I joined, the site hadn’t yet implemented the challenges, so I was able to join after my profile was approved. Hired must have convinced employers that their candidates are top notch because employers were “bidding” salaries between $105,000 and $130,000 on me.</p>

<h3 id="misleading-but-worth-it">Misleading, but worth it?</h3>

<p>However, the auction format is quite misleading because it implies that you must accept the highest bid. It also implies that employers must hire you and offer you whatever they bid. This is not the case. There are no strict obligations. You must still pass whatever interview process employers have. Employers can still ultimately reject you. Employers can offer you whatever salary they want to offer you if you pass their interviews. In other words, Hired simply uses an auction format as a gimmick to get people excited to participate. It’s a trick, but I’m not even mad.</p>

<p>Why not? Because the pool of employers on Hired is pretty darn good. I got serious interest from 5+ companies. I got multiple on-site interviews. I got two offers. Plus, if you get a job, Hired will give you a $2,000 bonus. Awesome, right?</p>

<p>Now it’s not all rosy. Some companies that were interested in me seemed really boring. The companies that gave me offers both offered me salaries below their respective bids. In the end, I didn’t accept any job offers because I didn’t think I was going to fit well within the companies or something irked me about the company. I should also note that Hired “provides” you with an “advocate” –in less disguised terms, Hired assigns a recruiter to you. The recruiter will call you pretty often to help plan interviews and to eventually nudge you into accepting an offer. If this sounds potentially annoying to you, don’t fret because I’ve dealt with many recruiters, and my Hired recruiter was definitely one of the nicer ones (my only beef is that the recruiter would sometimes call me in the morning when I was sleeping in late).</p>

<p><strong>Caveat:</strong> some of my friends used Hired, and they didn’t have a great experience. For me, the only real bummer was when Hired stopped including me in auctions. I think I may have disappointed my “advocate” by not accepting job offers, and I may have reacted poorly to the recruiter’s nudging because at the time, I thought it was a bit too much. Little did I know that he was far less pushy than most recruiters.</p>

<h2 id="dice">Dice</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Generic job board with a reputation for being stalked by recruiters.</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> I put my résumé on Dice and within 2 days, I was receiving tons of emails from 3rd party recruiters and head hunters.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Thumbs up. Dice is effective, but you will NOT enjoy the experience.</li>
</ul>

<p>Dice is an ugly site that is incredibly helpful in a painful way. First, I created a résumé specifically for Dice. What does this mean? Dice is for when you WANT spam from recruiters. Dice is for when you want to turbocharge your job search. <strong>Dice is for when you’re finally ready to destroy your fear of sharks, so you jump in a shark tank with craploads of bleeding tuna attached to your wetsuit.</strong> Do you get the picture, or must I throw more ridiculous warnings at your eyes? You must be mentally prepared to be inundated with contact from recruiters. They can sometimes be…unpleasant.</p>

<p>The onslaught of recruiter spam arrives from Dice because your profile is <em>public</em>. Your profile is rather pointless <em>except</em> for the résumé part of the profile. This means that your résumé has to be public, so it’s a good idea to upload a variant that excludes your contact info. Recruiters will check out your résumé and contact you via Dice messaging (which gets sent to your email). You then respond to recruiters, and work with them to get interviews and get hired. It’s a very clunky process. I could rant for several more paragraphs on the downsides of working with recruiters. However, it can be worth it. I’m very happy at my current job, which I earned through a recruiter.</p>

<h2 id="linkedin">LinkedIn</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>The gist:</strong> Networking, stalking, and head hunters.</li>
  <li><strong>My experience:</strong> Messaging through LinkedIn actually helped me. Also, I got the feeling that employers/recruiters viewed my LinkedIn more than they read my actual résumé.</li>
  <li><strong>My recommendation:</strong> Thumbs up. Linkedin is overrated, but it’s versitile and omnipresent.</li>
</ul>

<p>I didn’t get a ton of recruiters reaching out to me via LinkedIn. It can’t compete with Dice in that department, but at least with LinkedIn, you get contacted by in-house recruiters, not just 3rd party recruiters.</p>

<p>That said, after I got a job, I updated my LinkedIn profile to show my new gainful employment. Consequently, I’ve been contacted by recruiters at least a few times a week even though I’m not actively trying to get a job. In other words, the recruiter “spam” really only pours in if you’re currently employed (or experienced).</p>

<h3 id="other-uses">Other Uses</h3>

<p>Not to give false hope, but you may want to consider paying for a LinkedIn pro account. This lets you send a few messages to people you’re not connected with. I used this feature to contact executives and engineers at a few companies I was interested in. A couple of folks at one company actually replied to my messages, in which, I sincerely gushed about the company (and bragged about my 1337ness of course).</p>

<h3 id="quick-aside-unique-rsums-and-cool-profiles">Quick Aside: “Unique” résumés and cool profiles</h3>

<p>I consider my LinkedIn profile to be a way for me to show off a bit of my personal style. Some people try to be edgy or unique by formatting their résumés in a different way, but I’ve heard that’s actually a bad idea. Not to mention, a lot of people just don’t come up with good designs. Some do, but plenty don’t. Besides, <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/dev-job-search-tips-from-the-coding-interview-guru/#interviewers-process--employers-perspective">résumés need to be easily skimmed</a> by human eyes and easily scanned by software. After I got hired, I switched from being a job seeker to being an interviewer within my first week at the company. I saw over 10 resumes and sadly, the bland-looking ones were generally easier to skim. The uniquely formatted ones showed good intentions, but poor execution. You should think twice before you use bombastic fonts and lighter colors.</p>

<p>Oh! Back to my original point: I use my LinkedIn profile to demonstrate a bit of my personality through <em>writing style</em> –not through formatting (although I do add bullet points because their text organization powers are un-friggin’-paralleled). In fact, <strong>for pretty much any job site that required me to create a profile, I put in quite a bit of effort to write something actually interesting</strong>. It can be difficult to flex creative muscles for such tasks, but I believe it’s worth it to prevent your profile from being read with the same dry tone as every other candidates’ boring dossier. If you have 5+ years of perfectly relevant skills, then you can probably write a profile devoid of personality/creativity, and you’ll still stand out as a stellar candidate. Hooray for when that day arrives.</p>

<h1 id="stay-tuned">Stay Tuned</h1>

<p>Check back (somewhat) soon for more opinions and anecdotes on software developer job search sites. In part 2 of this Dev Job Searching Tools Roundup, I will ramble about Readyforce, The Muse, The Sourcery, AngelList, VC job listings, and more.</p>

<p>In future blog posts, I will cover other software engineering job hunting topics. I’m particularly excited to discuss my impressions from the other side of interview process. Also on my to-blog list: inheritance in JavaScript and lots of AngularJS best practices / app architecture patterns.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] [Dev Job Search] Tips from the Coding Interview Guru]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/dev-job-search-tips-from-the-coding-interview-guru/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-05-31T20:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/dev-job-search-tips-from-the-coding-interview-guru</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>Author of Cracking the Coding Interview, <a href="https://twitter.com/gayle">@gayle</a> , talking to <a href="https://twitter.com/HackReactor">@hackreactor</a> <a href="http://t.co/aVbcohgqSG">pic.twitter.com/aVbcohgqSG</a></p>&mdash; Jeff Lee (@RebootJeff) <a href="https://twitter.com/RebootJeff/statuses/423949825587945472">January 16, 2014</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>In a <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/hackr-diary-weeks-11-12-and-beyond/#overtime-support">previous post</a>, I mentioned that attended a talk given by <a href="http://www.technologywoman.com">Gayle Laakmann McDowell</a> when she visited Hack Reactor. She’s the author of the famous <em>Cracking the Coding Interview</em>, which is a book that helps developers perform better when interviewed for a new job. Her text mostly focuses on algorithm challenges, but there’s also a lot of content that has more to do with coaching up interview candidates.</p>

<p>I really liked McDowell’s presentation at Hack Reactor. There were plenty of intriguing anecdotes, and of course, there was plenty of good advice. Plus, she included a lot of insight into the hiring process. Many of her stories and comments provided the Hack Reactor community with a “behind the scenes” sort of perspective.</p>

<p>Keep in mind that she worked for companies like Apple, Microsoft, and Google, so <strong>her advice comes from the perspective of giant companies</strong>. I doubt her tips apply equally to smaller employers. For example, McDowell heavily emphasized the importance to study certain algorithms (e.g., various sorting and searching algos) and data structures (e.g., trees, hashes, etc). In my experience mostly interviewing with smaller companies (fewer than 500 employees; as few as 5 employees), studying textbook algorithms and data structures wouldn’t have helped me as much as studying more web-specific skills.</p>

<p>That said, I still want to share some of the more interesting takeaways from McDowell’s talk.</p>

<h1 id="interviewers-process--employers-perspective">Interviewers’ Process / Employers’ Perspective</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Your performance is evaluated relative to other candidates (so you’re not just being judged based on fixed benchmarks).</li>
  <li>Resumes are barely read. You must make yours easy to skim within 15 seconds.</li>
  <li>Unless it’s a warm-up question, you are not expected to get the solution right away.</li>
  <li>Employers judge your GitHub and public repos based on coding style (<a href="https://github.com/airbnb/javascript">do you violate any major no-nos?</a>) and use of <a href="http://addyosmani.com/resources/essentialjsdesignpatterns/book/">design patterns</a>. They don’t have much time to judge app architecture.
    <ul>
      <li><em>My 2 Cents:</em> Perhaps this falls under “design patterns”, but I would like to add that there is time to judge your use of a framework. If the employer is familiar with the frameworks you used, they will notice when you fail to follow the framework’s more important conventions. For example, for AngularJS apps, I will notice if you put too much logic in the views, if you abuse $rootScope (which is akin to relying on global scope variables as a crutch), if you create bloated controllers, if you lack services/factories/providers, etc. I will be extra happy if I see you use multiple modules, if I see tests, if I see usage of Angular best practices, etc.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Only the interviewer knows how well you did in the interview. You may think you aced it. You may think you bombed it. <a href="http://www.technologywoman.com/2011/03/31/why-your-interview-performance-is-impossible-to-judge/">But you don’t really know</a>.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote><p>When I was at Google, I referred a number of candidates, and ran a little (informal) experiment. How well could people judge their performance?<br />After each candidate completed their interview, I’d ask them how they did. Then, I’d look up their actual performance. And guess what? There was no correlation. None. Zip. Zero. Zilch.</p><footer><strong>&#8211;Gayle L. McDowell</strong></footer></blockquote>

<h1 id="interview-coaching--advice">Interview Coaching / Advice</h1>

<ul>
  <li>When answering a behavioral/experience question, you should tell a story. Your story-telling should use the following format: Premise, Situation, Action, Result. The “premise” is a quick, 1-sentence intro like “One time, I had to do X for an app.” The “situation” is the context of your story. The “action” and “result” are pretty self-explanatory. I imagine Laackmann’s motivation for this advice is that interviewees usually leave out at least one of these four parts when discussing valuable past experience.</li>
  <li>For each major experience you include on your resume, you should be prepared to discuss what you liked, what you disliked, what was challenging, and how you solved difficult problems/bugs.</li>
  <li>Always follow up with interviewers afterwards. Send them thank-you emails and ask about next steps.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-to-worry-about">What to Worry About</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Your conversational skills don’t need to be great because employers are desperate for technical skills.
    <ul>
      <li><em>My 2 Cents:</em> I think this is dangerous advice. It might apply to a giant company, but if you’re joining a smaller team, you need to be decent at chatting. Culture fit is also a bigger concern for smaller companies, and most company cultures include “must be decently articulate” as a core component.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Worry less about super advanced algorithms, but you should worry a lot about the common algorithms and data structures such as: hashes, trees (and common tree methods such as depth/breadth-first search), binary search, merge sort, and quick sort.
    <ul>
      <li><em>My 2 Cents:</em> I disagree. If you’re aiming for a back-end job, then maybe you need to be more of an algo+data structures expert. But if you’re aiming for a front-end or full-stack job, then there are more practical concerns that you will be quizzed on. I’m happy I know tree search methods, but this kind of knowledge only helped me in a few of many interviews I did during my job search. This topic of “advanced algorithms vs practical concerns” is commonly debated, but I have my reasons, which I hope to discuss in a future blog post. For the record, I’ve conducted interviews at my current job. I ask practical questions that most candidates struggle with.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>You must know Big-O, recursion, and maybe even bit-wise.
    <ul>
      <li><em>My 2 Cents:</em> I disagree about the bit-wise stuff (although, I suppose it’s impressive if you can bust it out with ease).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="whiteboarding-tips">Whiteboarding Tips</h2>

<ul>
  <li>If you are asked a trivia question, and you don’t know the answer, consider reasoning the answer by imagining how things should work. For example, if asked a question about CSS, imagine you created CSS. How would you implement a given rule?
    <ul>
      <li><em>My 2 Cents:</em> This one’s iffy because a lot of trivia questions are meant to focus on unintuitive situations. A quick aside for a quick example: <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/margin_collapsing">margin collapsing</a>. If there are two sibling <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> elements, and they both have <code>margin: 10px;</code>, then how much space is between them? You’d expect there to be 20px of space between them, but instead, there is only 10px thanks to margin collapsing.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>When solving an algorithm question, come up with some test cases (including edge cases!).</li>
  <li>Think out loud when trying to solve an algorithm question. Don’t just write code.
    <ul>
      <li><em>My 2 Cents:</em> As someone who has interviewed dev candidates, I can’t stress this enough.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>When whiteboarding, be conscious of your handwriting, alignment, etc.</li>
  <li>It’s ok to…
    <ul>
      <li>start solving a problem via pseudocode before writing real code. Just let your interviewer(s) know your plan.</li>
      <li>write <code>TODO</code> comments in your code for important-but-tangential stuff like input validation</li>
      <li>create proper variable names at first and then switch to abbreviated versions</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Use “breadth-first coding”: write your code to use helper functions that may not exist. Write the helper functions later as needed. Think of it like writing an outline before writing an essay so then other people can quickly get a grasp of your overall approach rather than waiting and awkwardly watching for several minutes while you write out everything.
    <ul>
      <li><em>My 2 Cents:</em> This sounds like a no-brainer, but you’d be surprised how many people don’t do this. To be fair, this is like writing modular code BEFORE refactoring.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Beware of common bugs you might make regardless of how awesome you are. Examples:
    <ul>
      <li>off-by-one errors</li>
      <li>bad comparison operators in if-statements, loops, and other conditionals</li>
      <li>math where you must perform a check before performing the operation to prevent edge cases from making your program explode. E.g., it might be good to perform a check before performing division so then you stop divide-by-zero errors.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Sublime Text 2 Setup and Customization]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/my-sublime-text-2-setup-and-customization/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-05-15T20:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/15/my-sublime-text-2-setup-and-customization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Updated on August 8, 2014.</em></p>

<p>I use Sublime Text 2 as my text editor for coding. I don’t use a fancy IDE like WebStorm, but I do plan on trying out WebStorm more at work. Actually, I should probably upgrade to ST3, but for now, I’m happy with ST2.</p>

<h1 id="config">Config</h1>

<p>However, ST2’s light weight comes at a cost: you probably need to configure some stuff before you’re really ready to roll. Here’s what I do when I first install ST2 on a machine.</p>

<h2 id="key-bindings">Key Bindings</h2>

<p>First, I change the keyboard shortcuts for cycling through open tabs. The default behavior is based on your usage history (most recently viewed tabs), but I prefer just cycling from left to right. There’s actually another key binding that can cycle tabs from left to right, but I prefer using <code>Ctrl+Tab</code>.Therefore, I edited my key bindings like so…</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Preferences &gt; Key Bindings – User </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
{ <span class="key"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">keys</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: [<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">ctrl+tab</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>], <span class="key"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">command</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">next_view</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> },
{ <span class="key"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">keys</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: [<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">ctrl+shift+tab</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>], <span class="key"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">command</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">prev_view</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> },
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h2 id="settings">Settings</h2>

<p>Next up, I make sure my whitespace is configured to my liking. I think most coders who lift hefty amounts of JavaScript go with indentation 2 spaces at a time, so that’s what I do. I prefer it because it takes up less space than a typical 4-space tab, which is critical when viewing code in split-screen mode. I also like having the option to manually change indentation with spaces if necessary for alignment purposes. Mixing spaces and tabs gets messy.</p>

<p>I also configure Sublime Text to automatically add a new line at the end of every file whenever I save. It won’t add a new line if one already exists at EOF. I personally never suffer from lack of new line at EOF, but <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/729692/why-should-files-end-with-a-newline">some UNIX tools won’t work without them</a>, and I know lots of hardcore coders out there like using such tools. I don’t want to screw them over. With that said, allow me to present my ST2 settings…</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Preferences &gt; Settings – User </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// The number of spaces a tab is considered equal to</span>
  <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">tab_size</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: <span class="integer">2</span>,

 <span class="comment">// Set to true to insert spaces when tab is pressed</span>
  <span class="key"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">translate_tabs_to_spaces</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: <span class="predefined-constant">true</span>,

<span class="comment">// Set to true to ensure the last line of the file ends in a newline</span>
<span class="comment">// character when saving</span>
  <span class="key"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">ensure_newline_at_eof_on_save</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: <span class="predefined-constant">true</span>,
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h1 id="theme-ui-skin">Theme (UI Skin)</h1>

<p>I use the Nexus theme, which you can find here: <a href="https://github.com/EleazarCrusader/nexus-theme">https://github.com/EleazarCrusader/nexus-theme</a>. The readme file explains a bunch of different installation options, but I recommend installing via Package Manager. The readme also tells you how to activate the theme after installation.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/EleazarCrusader/nexus-theme/master/nexus-theme.png" alt="official Nexus theme screenshot" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">The orange and blue decorations on the tabs tell you if the file has been change since last save.</p>

<h1 id="packages">Packages</h1>

<p>Sublime Text doesn’t come with many bells and whistles. Instead you add them as packages. First, you must install the package manager by following <a href="https://sublime.wbond.net/installation#st2">these instructions</a>. After that, get ready to discover a giant pool of all the bells and whistles you could possibly want. If you need to adjust the settings for any of these packages, you can usually find good documentation from the readme files of their respective GitHub repos.</p>

<p>After you install Package Manager, you can access it by hitting <code>Ctrl+Shift+P</code> (or perhaps <code>Cmd+Shift+P</code> for Macs?) and then typing “package control” into the search box. The typeahead will reveal your various options, but you mostly be using “Package Control: Install Package”. There will be some load time necessary to provide you a list of available packages, but after it’s done, you can search for packages by name. Installation will similarly require some load time. Check the bottom-left of the ST2 window to see relevant status messages.</p>

<p>Here are the packages I installed:</p>

<h3 id="alignment">Alignment</h3>
<p>Prettify your code by aligning multiple lines of variable definitions and hash objects. For example…</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Before and After using the Alignment package </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// this stuff...</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> x = <span class="integer">123</span>;
<span class="keyword">var</span> foo = <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">bar</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>;
<span class="keyword">var</span> exampleObj = {
  <span class="key">my</span>: x,
  <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="integer">99</span>,
  <span class="key">is</span>: <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">Jeff</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>
};

<span class="comment">// would turn into this stuff...</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> x          = <span class="integer">123</span>;
<span class="keyword">var</span> foo        = <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">bar</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>;
<span class="keyword">var</span> exampleObj = {
  <span class="key">my</span>  : x,
  <span class="key">name</span>: <span class="integer">99</span>,
  <span class="key">is</span>  : <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">Jeff</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>
};
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<p>This may look stupid to you, but I don’t use it all the time. The main place I like to use it is with multiple <code>var example = require('npm package name here');</code> statements at the top of a JS file. By the way, I had to edit the package settings to get alignment for object literals. I added the <code>":"</code> seen below…</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Preferences &gt; Package Settings &gt; Alignment &gt; Settings – User </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
{
  <span class="comment">// The mid-line characters to align in a multi-line selection, changing</span>
  <span class="comment">// this to an empty array will disable mid-line alignment</span>
  <span class="key"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">alignment_chars</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>: [<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">=</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>, <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">:</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>]
}
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h3 id="gitgutter">GitGutter</h3>
<p>Add indicators in your gutter so then you can see which lines of code have been changed since the last git commit. See the left edge of this screenshot:
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/ur6FY.png" alt="GitGutter in action" /></p>

<h3 id="sublimelinter">SublimeLinter</h3>
<p>I prefer live linting over build-time linting. SublimeLinter supports a ton of languages, and I have it set to simply bring up an indicator in the gutter and some underscores to point to any issues it finds. It’s not too obtrusive.</p>

<h3 id="trailingspaces">TrailingSpaces</h3>
<p>Extraneous whitespace is bad. Trailing whitespace is worse. I use this package to highlight any trailing whitespace in bright pink. I bet I could set my linter to do this, but oh well.</p>

<h3 id="markdownediting">MarkdownEditing</h3>
<p>Who doesn’t love Markdown? It makes GitHub README files and wiki pages look great. It makes dev blogs look great. It makes writing dev-related text easy. Sometimes, I write rough drafts of blog posts within Google Docs or <a href="http://dillinger.io/">Dillinger</a>, which is a sweet online Markdown editor. In the end, I always complete my blog posts by writing Markdown within Sublime Text.</p>

<p>I recently found a sweet ST package to help edit Markdown files: MarkdownEditing. It completely transforms the look and syntax highlighting of your Markdown. Sadly, I use CodeRay for codeblocks rather than standard Markdown markup. So MarkdownEditing can’t beautify my codeblocks within Sublime Text, but <code>inline code snippets like this one</code> are highlighted in a very helpful way. You can see all the ways that the package alters your Markdown <a href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/35a66d68a55666133ba7911fb0ea61277740680f/68747470733a2f2f7261772e6769746875622e636f6d2f5375626c696d65546578742d4d61726b646f776e2f4d61726b646f776e45646974696e672f6d61737465722f73637265656e73686f74732f6c696768742e706e67">here</a>. Keep in mind that there are a couple other themes available specifically for MarkdownEditing. I use the dark theme of course.</p>

<h2 id="syntax">Syntax</h2>

<p>You might also find it handy to install packages for specific languages. For example, I dabble with CSS pre-processors and templating languages. I’m currently checking out LESS for CSS and Jade for HTML, so I’ve installed syntax highlighters for them. The package names are simply “LESS” and “Jade”.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Weeks 11-12: And Beyond!]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/hackr-diary-weeks-11-12-and-beyond/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-05-11T22:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/hackr-diary-weeks-11-12-and-beyond</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20140511/flash_now_we_boogie.png" alt="Now We Boogie" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">The Flash suggests rhythmic celebration &#8211; Image by Yale Stewart of JL8 <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=252029451584354&amp;set=a.191314654322501.42323.126319720821995&amp;type=3&amp;theater">Comic</a></p>

<p>The events discussed in this blog post occurred in December 2013 and January 2014 because a <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/11/19/hackr-diary-my-apology/">blogging hiatus</a> caused a bit of a delay. Plus, I’ve just been lazy with blogging recently.</p>

<h1 id="recap-of-events">Recap of Events</h1>

<p>My “final” two weeks at Hack Reactor weren’t really final. As explained in a <a href="https://www.quora.com/Programming-Bootcamps/Has-anyone-had-a-bad-experience-at-a-programming-bootcamp/answer/Jeff-Lee-40">Quora post of mine</a>, I continued going to Hack Reactor for additional lectures and learning exercises AFTER graduation.</p>

<p>Weeks 11 and 12 were all about preparing for job hunting and prepping for hiring day by practicing presentations. These are definitely the least intense weeks of the program. Some students were motivated enough to start new projects. Some students (like me) spent some time to refactor code from our Hack Reactor projects from weeks 6-10. Throughout the final two weeks, we received a wide variety of lectures on how to find a job, on how to approach whiteboarding, and on a few different tech topics too. Most of these lectures were only an hour, and many of them didn’t have tightly associated classwork (which is unlike the first half of the program).</p>

<p>One thing I found odd was the emphasis that staff put on downplaying Hack Reactor when job hunting. I’m <a href="http://sympatheticvibration.com/hack-reaction-week-8-no-recognition/">not the only one</a> to feel funny about it. The reason is that you don’t want employers to frame their perspective of you within the confines of “recent student.” I can understand that, but I didn’t bother editing my blog to avoid “exposing” myself as a recent graduate of a training program.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the final stages of the Hack Reactor curriculum <a href="https://www.quora.com/Programming-Bootcamps/Has-anyone-had-a-bad-experience-at-a-programming-bootcamp/answer/Jeff-Lee-40">ran into issues</a>. Fortunately, Hack Reactor managed to pull together the resources to compensate. I explain later in this blog post.</p>

<h2 id="pamela-fox-discusses-engineering-culture">Pamela Fox Discusses Engineering Culture</h2>

<p>One of my favorite guest speakers during my time at Hack Reactor was Pamela Fox. Pamela <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/hackr-diary-a-visit-from-pamela-fox-re-backbone/">already gave a talk</a> at Hack Reactor, but it was a more technical talk about <a href="http://backbone.js">Backbone</a>. This time around, she gave a talk about the culture of professional software engineering. It was a great presentation that discussed what commonalities and differences you can expect to see when comparing engineering teams. A lot of what she said ended up influencing the <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/09/questions-to-ask-dev-interviewers/">questions I ask employers</a> when searching for a job.</p>

<h2 id="consultant-surveys-the-students">Consultant Surveys the Students</h2>

<p>For the first time in Hack Reactor history, a consultant was brought in specifically to give a 2-day workshop on job search prep. The consultant, David Daniels, did all the usual stuff like resume review (which would make him the 5th person to review our resumes during the job search prep portion of Hack Reactor), but he also conducted exercises on networking and personality testing. Plus, he gave a lecture about what companies like Microsoft look at when evaluating candidates.</p>

<h3 id="networking-practice">Networking Practice</h3>

<p>“Tell me about yourself” is such a common opener for job interviews (especially in the phone screen stages), but it’s funny how hard it can be to come up with a coherent answer without any practice. Therefore, David had us all practice giving quick, autobiographical pitches that would not ony sound concise (no rambling!), but also provide all the relevant info that recruiters want to hear (what you’ve been working on, what specific skills you have, what you look for in a new job, etc).</p>

<p>Students were also instructed to practice giving “pitches” on why they want to work for company XYZ in response to the frequently asked question of “Why do you want to work here?” Admittedly, this is something I did not give much attention to after graduation, and I regret that. It’s definitely important to practice answering that question for all the different companies you apply to.</p>

<h3 id="strengths-finder-personality-test">Strengths Finder Personality Test</h3>

<p>The other major activity conducted by David was post-survey analysis. What survey? The <a href="http://strengths.gallup.com/110440/about-strengthsfinder-20.aspx">Strengths Finder</a> survey. It’s a personality test that focuses on your “strengths” in a way that is supposed to help you inspect your personality in a way that is relevant to professional/work life.</p>

<h4 id="my-results">My Results</h4>

<p>Here are my top 5 (paraphrased) strengths according to the test:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Input:</strong> Craving to know more. “Input” folks like to collect and archive all kinds of info.</li>
  <li><strong>Analytical:</strong> Tendancy to search for reasons and causes. “Analytical” folks think about all the factors that might affect a situation.</li>
  <li><strong>Responsibility:</strong> Taking ownership psychological of what they say they will do. “Responsibility” folks are committed to stable values such as honesty and loyalty.</li>
  <li><strong>Restorative:</strong> Strong problem solving. “Restorative” folks figure out what is wrong and resolving it.</li>
  <li><strong>Intellection:</strong> Characterized by intellectual activity. “Intellection” folks are introspective and appreciate intellectual discussions.</li>
</ul>

<p>My results put me in the “typical” engineer group. Together, with the fellow students with similar strengths, we built a Google Spreadsheet to further analyze our results and find out who was most similar to whom. <strong>Damn. We <em>nerdy</em>.</strong></p>

<h4 id="mini-anti-personality-test-rant">Mini-Anti-Personality-Test-Rant</h4>

<p>I’m not a fan of personality tests. Any one who has taken an intro psych class knows that personality tests are often flawed by the wording of the questions, the limited options provided by multiple-choice formats, etc. On top of that, I don’t like the <em>effect</em> that personality tests have. There’s a lot of confirmation bias. Test takers tend to allow the results to define them as a self-fulfilling prophecy. When people learn of other people’s test results, they might end up pigeonholing each other. “Oh that test said you have a tendency to over-analyze situations? I should call you out on it whenever you offer criticism.” (Ok that last hypothetical example is a bit melodramatic, but it’s the type of crap that starts happening on conscious and subconscious levels)</p>

<p>Perhaps what I despise most is that personality tests can solidify self-perceptions <em>and stifle personal change</em> as a result. I believe people can change. They change all the time. This is not optimism. I believe people change for the better <em>and the worse</em> all the time. My point is that some fools take personality tests and believe the results always involve immutable properties. Such belief is more ridiculous than using programming jargon to discuss psychology concepts ;)</p>

<h2 id="graduation">Graduation</h2>

<p>There was booze, dancing, food, funny photos, and good times :D</p>

<h2 id="overtime-support">Overtime Support</h2>

<p>The day after graduation (which was in late December), my cohort returned for a follow-up. The follow-up included asking us not to reveal too many of Hack Reactor’s trade secrets, asking us for feedback about the course, and some extra heartfelt moments.</p>

<p>Then we parted ways. Some flew back home, never to return. Most of us went home for the winter holidays and returned in January for post-graduation job search help. This included mock interviews conducted by Hack Reactor staff (more specifically, <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/cameronboehmer">Cameron Boehmer</a>, an awesomely nice guy who created <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/how-to-start-reading-at-nearly-1000-words-per-minute-today-2014-3">Squirt.io</a>). It also included practicing whiteboarding with peers, lots of mentoring, and a few additional lectures about stuff like user authentication and SEO.</p>

<h3 id="presentation-by-gayle-laakmann">Presentation by Gayle Laakmann</h3>

<p>The author of the mucho famous book, <em><a href="http://www.crackingthecodinginterview.com/">Cracking the Coding Interview</a></em>, gave a talk at Hack Reactor in January. She gave a ton of great advice. I will regurgitate much of it in a future blog post. For now, I just want to share the most interesting tidbit.</p>

<p>Gayle mentioned that you will suck at surmising your own interview success. Apparently, surveys have been conducted, and they reveal zero correlation between how well a candidate thinks they did versus how the candidate’s interviewer thinks they did. You may think you aced an interview, but you actually said something that’s a deal-breaker. Or you may think you bombed, but you actually did better than all the other candidates.</p>

<h2 id="hiring-day">Hiring Day</h2>

<p>Unique to my cohort, hiring day was hosted at Hack Reactor <em>after</em> graduation. We presented group projects in front of an audience of 15 or so companies. We then went into a mini-interview marathon akin to speed dating. Each Hack Reactor student got a chance to speak with about 7 or 8 companies based on preferences submitted to Hack Reactor staff beforehand. After the crazy “speed dating”, there was an open networking session (basically a happy hour). There was a lot of stress leading up to this day, but ya know what? It really wasn’t that bad.</p>

<p>I would say about 1/3 or 1/2 of my peers who participated actually got hired by the companies that showed up. For me, hiring day was just the beginning of a nearly-3-month-long search.</p>

<p>I should (re-)mention that about a third of my cohort didn’t actually participate in hiring day because they weren’t interested in starting a new job soon or they had joined Hack Reactor’s <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/03/30/hackr-diary-weeks-8-10-group-collaboration/#hacker-in-residence-program">Hacker-in-Residence program</a>.</p>

<h2 id="job-searching">Job Searching</h2>

<p>As you can imagine, I have a lot to talk about with regards to job searching. I’m excited to blog in detail about the ups and downs of the search. To cut to the chase, let me mention that I am fully employed. I’m a professional software engineer working on a web app that uses full-stack JavaScript. I don’t mean to brag (much), but the gig is pretty friggin’ sweet. Hack Reactor was a success!</p>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<p>I learned so much about job hunting. I will go into details in a future blog post, but for now, I will outline some of what I picked up when searching for a job:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Job Sites
    <ul>
      <li>What different job sites to use</li>
      <li>How to use them <em>differently</em></li>
      <li>Which sites are more effective</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Job interviews
    <ul>
      <li>What kinds of questions to ask</li>
      <li>What kinds of questions I will be asked</li>
      <li>How to communicate for an interview</li>
      <li>The role of good/back luck</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Regrets
    <ul>
      <li>I should’ve used more Hack Reactor connections</li>
      <li>I should’ve taken more action sooner</li>
      <li>I should’ve actively shown more enthusiasm for each company I visited</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>General
    <ul>
      <li>What recruiters are really like</li>
      <li>How employers evaluate you <em>before</em> any interview</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="whats-next-for-hack-reactor">What’s Next for Hack Reactor?</h1>

<p>Yesterday, I went to my cohort’s “3-month” reunion hosted by Hack Reactor. It’s actually been closer to 5 months since graduation, but whatever. At the reuinion, the founders of Hack Reactor did a Q&amp;A panel where they provided career advice and asked us how things were going at our new jobs. After the panel, we were told that Hack Reactor HQ is expanding. It’s already expanded once since my cohort ended by using a second floor of the building. That expansion increased the size of Hack Reactor cohorts. More staff have been hired too.</p>

<p>A third floor will be opening in June. It will mostly be used as offices for the newly augmented staff, but it will also have a new lounge area for alumni to use! Niiice. Wheels have been set in motion to organize alumni events and general activity. For example, there are plans to use the alumni network as an avenue for project collaboration (e.g., Feel like starting a random side project? Get ideas and possibly form a team with alumni).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Weeks 8-10: No More Solo]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/03/30/hackr-diary-weeks-8-10-group-collaboration/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-03-30T13:52:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/03/30/hackr-diary-weeks-8-10-group-collaboration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20140330/SimoneAnne-8351-birds.jpg" alt="something something Mighty Ducks" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">Insert inspirational metaphor relating birds to teamwork</p>

<h1 id="junior-to-senior-transition">Junior-to-Senior Transition</h1>

<p>As I mentioned <a href="http://rebootjeff.github.io/blog/2014/03/21/hackr-diary-weeks-6-and-7-making-something/">last time</a>, my <a href="http://rebootjeff.github.io/blog/categories/hackr-diary/">HackR Diary</a> was on hiatus for a bit, so the events described in this blog post occurred back in mid-November thru early-December of 2013. Weeks 8, 9, and 10 of my Hack Reactor experience covered a group project period where students formed small teams to create web apps from scratch.</p>

<p>I forgot to mention a few points in my description of the personal project period:</p>

<h2 id="client-projects">Client Projects</h2>

<p>Some folks in my cohort accepted client projects rather than coming up with their own web app ideas. This meant they had to meet with clients, deal with external requirements, etc. Some had fun experiences; some had frustrating experiences. Some got paid; some volunteered. They all got to add some extra gravitas to their resumes/CVs.</p>

<h2 id="being-a-senior">Being a Senior</h2>

<p>The cohort before mine graduated from the program just before interim week. After interim week, my cohort returned to HR HQ to find a new “junior” cohort, and there was a transition to seniorhood for us. As a senior, you have fewer/shorter lectures, less guidance, and you’re given more freedom to explore on your own. You still have a schedule to follow, but it’s far less rigid, which is fantastic. It’s funny how you feel more freedom, yet you end up working harder because of the nature of project periods at Hack Reactor.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, there isn’t much time to get to know the juniors when you’re a senior. We had one code review night where seniors gave juniors feedback on their classwork, but as a senior, your mind is always worried about your project, your app, your baby born of code.</p>

<p>By the way, I noticed that the juniors had more diversity. They had more women and more minority folks. I’m not saying my own cohort felt shitty because of the percentage of white males, and I’m not saying the new junior group reached some sort of ideal diversity (eventually, I may write a rambling blog entry about my views on diversity). I’m just noting the “slope” created by two “points of data.” The junior cohort was larger by about 5 or so people, but the increase in diversity was still noticeable. That said, I also noticed Hack Reactor felt more crowded (doh!).</p>

<h1 id="recap-of-events">Recap of Events</h1>

<p>I teamed up with 3 of my fellow seniors to work on a smartphone game called Phone Tag. Gameplay is like a free-for-all laser tag. Players sneak up on one another and hit a button to tag. The game displays a map (via Google Maps) to show locations of other players, power-ups, respawn points, etc. The app consists of HTML, CSS, and full-stack JavaScript. The client app is “ported” into an iOS app and an Android app via a tool called PhoneGap. Phone Tag leverages geolocation and real-time communications.</p>

<p>The first week just consisted of setting up boilerplate code and brainstorming game ideas. It took us awhile to settle on the free-for-all game mode. We originally considered implementing a game resembling zombie tag instead. My team also had to spend lots of time researching libraries, tools, smartphone abilities, and all that sort of goodness to find out what we should use to develop our project.</p>

<h2 id="fitness-challenge-push-up-routine">Fitness Challenge: Push-Up Routine</h2>

<p>I’m sure some Hack Reactor folks (Hackers React? Hacker Reactions?) cynically roll their eyes at the staff’s efforts to promote health, but I appreciate them. For one week, there was a push-up challenge where students were encouraged to pair up and hold each other accountable for completing a set of push-ups twice a day. I paired up with a junior, and it was cool to be able to get to know someone outside of my cohort.</p>

<h2 id="hacker-in-residence-program">Hacker-in-Residence Program</h2>

<p>In the middle of the group project period, the staff told seniors about a program to extend the Hack Reactor experience. The Hacker-in-Residence program is an extra 3 months where you get paid to work part-time for the institution (develop internal tools, teach beginner-level content, interview applicants, etc) and work on more projects (i.e., extra project periods). The idea is that a select few seniors can become Hacker-in-Residence and gain valuable experience. I chose not to apply for the program because I already felt well prepared to enter the job market. Many students felt the same way, but plenty of them were attracted to the HIR program. Under half of the seniors applied, and most of them were accepted.</p>

<p>Therefore, about 1/3 of my cohort became HIRs. It’s important to note that Hack Reactor might not include these guys in their post-graduation employment stats. But even so, I know previous HIRs have had little to no trouble getting employed after their HIR phase ended.</p>

<h2 id="new-hack-reactor-admissions">New Hack Reactor Admissions</h2>

<p>At some point during weeks 8-10, Hack Reactor launched their new website. It’s quite a bit nicer than their last version, but more interestingly, they changed their admissions process too. The new process uses their website to check very basic JS skills.</p>

<p>Hack Reactor likes having students/alumni contribute to their official blog, and I anwered the call for volunteers by authoring <a href="http://www.hackreactor.com/blog/the-hack-reactor-interview-process-questions-and-tips">this blog post</a> about the admissions process. Sadly, much of my experience lost relevance when the staff produced a new admissions process. I had to go through a 2-stage interview process, but now there is only a single interview. However, I think a lot of the advice I provided still makes sense.</p>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<p>Much like the personal project period, a lot was learned via trial-by-fire work during the group project period. My group tried and scrapped various features, libraries, tools, project management strategies, etc. It was so tough and so awesome at the same time.</p>

<h2 id="tech">Tech</h2>

<p>My team knew we wanted to use geolocation, but we weren’t certain about much else. This meant that we had to research and explore many options. Eventually, we settled on a tech stack featuring quite a few different libraries/tools.</p>

<h3 id="phonegap">PhoneGap</h3>

<p>I spent a lot of time wrestling with <a href="http://phonegap.com/">PhoneGap</a>, a dev tool for creating smartphone apps using tech normally reserved for web browsers. It’s a fairly popular option for informational smartphone apps, rapid prototyping, etc. However, 101 out of 62 doctors have concluded that PhoneGap can lead to headaches and irritable demeanor. I’ve written specifically about using PhoneGap for Android in <a href="http://rebootjeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/27/setup-for-phonegap-for-android-for-reals/">a past blog post</a>.</p>

<h3 id="dont-use-jquery-animations">Don’t use jQuery animations</h3>

<p><a href="http://css-tricks.com/myth-busting-css-animations-vs-javascript/">This article</a> explains animation options quite well, but the gist of it is that you should avoid jQuery animations. You can use CSS (if you love jQuery, then use it to add animation-centric classes to target elements) or faster JavaScript animation libraries like <a href="http://www.greensock.com/gsap-js/">GSAP</a> (but it’s not very famous?). For Phone Tag, my team originally tried doing simple slide animations via jQuery-Mobile, and the performance was horrible. We switched to CSS-driven animations because there’s plenty of online help for them and we knew it would be good for us to study more CSS anyway.</p>

<h2 id="engineering-and-project-management">Engineering and Project Management</h2>

<p>Everyone expects to learn plenty of technical stuff when building projects at Hack Reactor, but there’s a slew of non-technical wisdom discovered too. My team had a lot of discussion and debates regarding feature sets, client vs server roles, project priorities, division of labor, etc. as we worked to meet MVP (minimum viable product) milestones and deadlines.</p>

<p>Unlike the personal project period, the group project period involved a ton of communication. There’s a huge amount of extra planning and talking that goes into group coding. The collaboration is great for producing cool ideas and reducing scope of work for any given individual, but the group setting necessitates expressed justification for actions. When you’re on your own, you just explore and debug however you want to, and you’re often making heavy use of your <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Working_memory">working memory</a>. When you’re in a group or even just a pair, you often have to explain before you act, which is a pretty serious exercise for your brain because it can feel like your working memory doesn’t get to operate at peak efficiency due to the extra steps of communication that fall between coming up with a small idea and implementing that idea.</p>

<p>Another way to put it: when you’re going solo, you get comfortable with the <em>just try XYZ and see if it works</em> model for programming. When you’re part of a team, you often need to <em>explain</em> XYZ, process any critical feedback you may receive, etc. Transitioning from solo work to group work needs a major change in mental processes. Luckily, everyone in my team is more patient and laidback than I am, so no wars broke out and no debates devolved into chaos. Good times.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Weeks 6 and 7: App from Scratch]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/03/21/hackr-diary-weeks-6-and-7-making-something/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-03-21T17:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/03/21/hackr-diary-weeks-6-and-7-making-something</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20140321/co-compare_presentation.jpg" alt="Personal Project presentation time" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">Presenting my project, Co-Compare, to the folks of Hack Reactor</p>

<h1 id="life-update">Life Update</h1>

<p>I got a job! I will start using my JS skills for dolla bills on Monday. I will blog all about my rather tiring job search soon. For now, I will resume blogging about Hack Reactor from <a href="http://rebootjeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/28/hackr-diary-week-5/">where I left off</a>. During the 2nd half of the program, I didn’t do any blogging, but I took plenty of notes for the sake of blogging at a later time, so prepare to be amazed …or mildly amused. Remember, the following rollercoaster ride took place during late-October through mid-November.</p>

<h1 id="recap-of-events">Recap of Events</h1>

<h2 id="interim-week-different-format">Interim Week (different format)</h2>

<p>The 2nd half of Hack Reactor starts with an “interim week” (aka “solo week”) where expectations are a bit cloudy. <strong>The Hack Reactor website didn’t do a good job of explaining that the injection of an interim week means that Hack Reactor is really a 13-week program.</strong> During this special week, Hack Reactor HQ is not guaranteed to be open to students. Also, students are not guaranteed any access to staff. The staff is either taking a break or working on reconfiguring the offices or other changes.</p>

<p>In other words, the students are on their own for starting the first week of developing their personal projects. Students self-organize if they want to meet up at a cafe or whathaveyou to enable collaboration.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
  <li>I spent most of my time working from HR HQ when it was open. I used nearby cafes when it wasn’t.</li>
  <li>Like a few others, I used interim week to do some travelling and to catch up on sleep.</li>
  <li>At one point (maybe after interim week?), I broke my laptop by being a Linux noob. I was one of few Ubuntu users in my cohort, and I had trouble dealing with permission/access issues. I eventually followed some StackOverflow suggestion and fucked up my permissions so badly that I had to reinstall Ubuntu. As you can imagine, my emotions are still failing to heal from that self-inflicted disaster.
    <ul>
      <li>FYI, my new job is giving me a Mac. Soon I will join the majority of devs in the promise land of screens that actually reproduce accurate colors, impressive battery life, and installation wonders such as homebrew.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="extras">Extras</h2>

<ul>
  <li>In my cohort, we organized a night to go to a movie theater for Ender’s Game. Good times.</li>
  <li>A rep from <a href="http://famo.us/">Famous</a> stopped by to give a presentation about a brand new web app framework. It’s so new that even now, Famous is in beta. Back during the personal project period, it was in a closed beta (or was it alpha?), but Famous was inviting Hack Reactor students to access it! The framework renders special <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> elements in a breathtaking way. I never used it, but I will talk about it a bit more in another blog post.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<p>Holy. Crap. I learned so much during the personal project weeks. Admittedly, I didn’t work extra long hours until the last week or so before the deadline. By then, I was working at least 80 hours per week. In the first couple of days, I realized there was so much I had to learn that it felt quite overwhelming, and I had a difficult time starting.</p>

<h2 id="tools">Tools</h2>

<p>Obviously I would have to learn a lot of app concepts, engineer some solid logic, etc. But I also had to do all this while learning new tools.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Balsamiq:</strong> Wireframing software. Creating wireframes really helps when trying to explain what you hope to build. To practice communication skills and project management, students had to explain their progress/goals very briefly during small stand-up meetings.</li>
  <li><strong>Yeoman:</strong> Boilerplate/scaffold generator. I used an Angular-Express generator to help me get started making a full-stack app with boilerplate code for Angular, Node, and Express. This served as a great “starter pack” of code.</li>
  <li><strong>Grunt:</strong> Task runner. To be honest, I used Grunt simpy because it came with Yeoman. However, gaining exposure to the tool opened my eyes to the possibilities provided by task runners like Grunt.</li>
  <li><strong>Stylus:</strong> CSS pre-processor. I’m not sure if CSS pre-processors are part of the tech stack or “just” another set of dev tools, but for what it’s worth, I didn’t write pure CSS for Co-Compare. Instead, I wrote Stylus CSS. I like the visual design side of front-end development, and using Stylus made that facet even more fun.</li>
  <li><strong>Heroku:</strong> Web app hosting provider. It’s easy to use because it follows a git workflow, but deployment still has challenges (re: environment configuration).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-tortured-ok-not-really-birth-of-an-idea">The Tortured (ok not really) Birth of An Idea</h2>

<p>I like to think my mind is superior –errr…I mean <em>creative</em>. However, it can be tough to come up with web app ideas based on constraints. Everyone worried about whether or not they could actually implement their ideas in just a few weeks (I think it amounted to only 2.5 weeks). In the end, I learned that “Just Do It” really applies. You can spend roughly 3 gajillion hours analyzing ideas, use cases, market needs, tech stacks, visual design, etc. But at some point, you need to just do it already. Just make something and see what happens. The price of failure is time spent. The gain of failure is lessons learned. A beauty of programming is the ability to quickly change, pivot, redo, etc.</p>

<h3 id="from-cool-to-meh">From Cool to Meh</h3>

<p>Originally, I thought my idea was too boring. I wanted to create a fantasy sports game specifically for tennis, but I couldn’t find a good way to get the data/stats from pro tennis matches, so I switched to something far less cool.</p>

<p>I switched to an idea spawned by my love for analyzing/comparing products and services. In the past, I’ve spent far too much time comparing video game consoles, cars, computer parts, <em>bootcamps</em>, etc. I enjoyed it too. A lot. But I knew most people aren’t crazy in this way, so I worried that my app idea for <a href="http://cocompare.herokuapp.com">Co-Compare</a> (a web app to build comparison tables and have others vote on them) was too unsexy.</p>

<h3 id="from-meh-to-oooh">From Meh to Oooh</h3>

<p>It’s true that Co-Compare doesn’t have a ton of wow-factor, but it provided plenty of opportunity:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Simplicity:</strong> It was the type of idea that could work with very few features (good for rapid prototyping).</li>
  <li><strong>Exploration:</strong> But I could have fun adding more and more features as I desired. There were plenty of sub-ideas to explore and keep my brain satiated with more goodies to engineer.</li>
  <li><strong>Fundamentals:</strong> My app requires CRUD actions. Create, Read, Update, and Delete are fundamental app actions that devs should know. It’s weird to “brag” that Co-Compare helped me learn <em>fundamentals</em>, but it’s important, and it’s not easy just because it’s “fundamental.” Engineering a CRUDy app is a great learning experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Full-Stack:</strong> My app covered a lot of territory so it exposed me to CSS pre-processors, front-end MVC, API design, databases, user authentication, etc. This was really scary at first, but afterwards, I was truly proud of what I covered.</li>
</ul>

<p>I really believe that the full-stack nature of Co-Compare solidified my abilities as a web app developer. By creating a nice-looking front-end, my own API, and back-end models for a SQL datastore, I learned so much that it gave my confidence a tremendous boost –which is funny because I had a ton of confidence going into the personal project weeks…then I lost a lot of confidence when nothing I created worked the first time. So at the end, I regained a lot of confidence that I already had at the beginning.</p>

<p>Note: Some of my classmates implemented ideas that had very bare front ends because all the impressive stuff was run on the server side. Other folks created apps that had little or no back-end logic. The number of things wrong with these paths is quite small. In fact, most experts would say the number rhymes with “hero.” Anyway, my point is that this particular “full-stack” facet of my experience is not the “best” way, but just something that I really value for myself.</p>

<h2 id="dev-cycleprocess">Dev Cycle/Process</h2>

<p>Hack Reactor staff helped students with their projects by giving recommendations on tech stack decisions, dev tools, deployment options, etc. And of course, they gave us debugging help, but there was no hand holding.</p>

<p>The primary form of guidance came in the form of some project management structure. We formed small groups that held its members accountable for short-term goals. The staff taught us about iterative development and the concept of creating MVPs (minimal viable products) as milestones rather than aiming for creating versions that were 100% complete.</p>

<p>In other words, I learned about some dev processes to help promote productivity as a software engineer.</p>

<h1 id="want-to-learn-from-my-app">Want to Learn from My App?</h1>

<p>You can find the code for Co-Compare on my GitHub. I took the time to write up a decent README too because for some reason, I have a good time writing English in addition to JavaScript. I suggest you <a href="https://github.com/RebootJeff/co-compare#development">check this out</a> if you’re interested in learning more about how I created an app from scratch.</p>

<p>Keep in mind that you shouldn’t follow everything I do. For example, my Angular app folder structure neglects best practice. It was a popular structure at the time, but it’s actually best to name folders based on features, rather than just lumping all controllers together, all views together, etc.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setup for PhoneGap for Android for Reals]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/27/setup-for-phonegap-for-android-for-reals/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-01-27T17:52:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/27/setup-for-phonegap-for-android-for-reals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20140127/phonegap-android.png" alt="PhoneGap and Android have wonderful conversations" /></p>

<p>PhoneGap is a crazy tool for building “hybrid” smartphone apps. You write HTML, CSS, and JavaScript code for PhoneGap to compile into an app for iOS, Android, Windows Phone, Blackberry, etc. The app will simply use a browser embedded in a native app wrapper (hence, the “hybrid” label).</p>

<p>There are many pros and cons to developing with PhoneGap, but I won’t review those because you can find debates on the usefulness of PhoneGap and others like it so long as you have (at least) mediocre Google Fu. You do have Google Fu, <a href="http://lmgtfy.com/?q=google+fu">right</a>? Don’t forget that Adobe PhoneGap is oftentimes referred to as Apache Cordova (even in modern documentation).</p>

<p>Anyway, this blog post is meant to disclose the growing pains you could encounter upon trying PhoneGap for the first time for Android development. Although if you’re developing for iOS, you’ll still face annoyances like having to disable WebView bounce (why doesn’t PhoneGap do that for you by default?!).</p>

<p>There were many unspoken hoops I had to jump through to get it working for me when I worked on an <a href="https://github.com/RebootJeff/phone-tag-phonegap">outdoor video game app</a>. I really wish someone had warned me about these hoops, but my loss is your gain.</p>

<h1 id="installfest">Installfest</h1>

<p>I’m sure you were told to just install the Android SDK plus PhoneGap and then you’d be off to the races, right? <a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/4clw90A">WRONG</a>. So wrong. Incredibly wrong. Maybe it’s because my personal dev machine is running Ubuntu, but I had to install many missing pieces to the PhoneGap puzzle. Some PhoneGap tutorials cover some of these dev components, but I don’t remember seeing one that covered all of them so here you go:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Apache Ant: Java library/tool</li>
  <li>JRE: Java Runtime Environment</li>
  <li>JDK: Java Development Kit</li>
  <li>Android SDK: platform Software Dev Kit (make sure it comes with Eclipse)</li>
</ul>

<p>After you install the Android SDK, you probably want to make sure you have the right API version. I used API 17 for supporting phones with Android v4.2. Use the SDK manager to install the desired API. Type <code>android</code> in a terminal to open the SDK manager. If that doesn’t work, it’s probably because you have a problem that will be solved by reading the next section of this blog post.</p>

<h1 id="command-line-goodness">Command Line Goodness</h1>

<p>Everyone wants to use command line tools. In fact, PhoneGap wants to use some commands for Android development, but SURPRISE! Those commands are not available until you manually edit your .bash_profile file. You may have to do some searching to find where your .bash_profile sleeps at night, but mine was in my home directory (aka ~/.bash_profile). Keep in mind that it is a hidden file, so you need to enable viewing hidden files (in case you didn’t know). I created a Development folder for my Android dev tools. Then I added the following lines to my .bash_profile (make sure you replace my filepath with your filepath):</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>.bash_profile </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
# Adds Android SDK tools to command line
export PATH=$PATH:/home/myUserName/Development/adt-bundle-linux-x86_64-20131030/sdk/tools
export PATH=$PATH:/home/myUserName/Development/adt-bundle-linux-x86_64-20131030/sdk/platform-tools
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<p>Now, you’re finally set to begin development with PhoneGap. However, if you want certain features to work, you may have to modify some XML files. Read on, my relative from a common-and-super-old ancestor.</p>

<h1 id="xml-file-modifications">XML File Modifications</h1>

<p>Want your app to access external networks? Getting origin errors? Try the sweet taste of the <code>&lt;access origin&gt;</code> tag. Want to enable geolocation? Try the soothing sounds eminating from the <code>&lt;feature&gt;</code> tag. These tags need to be edited/added to the <code>config.xml</code> file of your PhoneGap project. Put your Google Fu to practice if you need more details. Just keep in mind that if you run into various problems in the future, the <code>config.xml</code> file is yet another possible source of irritation to debug.</p>

<p>Here’s a snippet from my config file:</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>config.xml </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
# Adds Android SDK tools to command line
<span class="tag">&lt;access</span> <span class="attribute-name">origin</span>=<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">http://yourserver.com</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span><span class="tag">&gt;</span>
<span class="tag">&lt;feature</span> <span class="attribute-name">name</span>=<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">http://api.phonegap.com/1.0/geolocation</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="tag">/&gt;</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<p>By the way, it’s best practice to declare what kind of voodoo your app is utilizing. In case of GPS usage, modify your <code>/platforms/android/AndroidManifest.xml</code> file as follows:</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>/platforms/android/AndroidManifest.xml </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="tag">&lt;uses-permission</span> <span class="attribute-name">android:name</span>=<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">android.permission.ACCESS_COARSE_LOCATION</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="tag">/&gt;</span>
<span class="tag">&lt;uses-permission</span> <span class="attribute-name">android:name</span>=<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">android.permission.ACCESS_FINE_LOCATION</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="tag">/&gt;</span>
<span class="tag">&lt;uses-permission</span> <span class="attribute-name">android:name</span>=<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">android.permission.ACCESS_LOCATION_EXTRA_COMMANDS</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="tag">/&gt;</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h1 id="down-the-rabbit-hole">Down the Rabbit Hole</h1>

<p>Using PhoneGap for the first time can be incredibly frustrating. I ran into so many small issues when learning how to use it. There can be problems with connecting a device to your computer, enabling certain phone features, dealing with compatibility quirks, etc.</p>

<h2 id="connecting-an-android-device">Connecting an Android Device</h2>
<p>Type <code>adb devices</code> into a terminal after you use a USB cable to attach an Android phone to your computer. Make sure that the phone is put into <strong>USB Debugging mode</strong>. You can find that mode in the developer options. Different versions of Android have different ways to access the developer options.</p>

<p>If you don’t see any devices listed, you may need to investigate drivers for your phone. Sometimes there are other problems with adb that can be solved be restarting: try typing <code>adb kill-server &amp;&amp; adb start-server</code> in your terminal (possibly with <code>sudo</code>).</p>

<h2 id="plugins-not-included">Plugins Not Included</h2>
<p>When using GPS, I ran into some blog posts claiming that it’s necessary to install a geolocation plugin. In my experience, it’s not needed, but for other features, it may be a different story. If you’re trying to access a hardware sensor or simply want to use a feature someone has already implemented (e.g., bar code scanner), then you may need to investigate plugins. This might be helpful: <a href="http://cordova.apache.org/news/2013/10/21/cordova-registry.html">About Cordova plugin registry</a></p>

<h2 id="android-fragmentation-strikes-again">Android Fragmentation Strikes Again</h2>
<p>Be warned: PhoneGap has different bugs for different versions of Android. For example, the PhoneGap app I worked on was built with Android API 17 (aka 4.2 aka Jelly Bean). I tested the app on a phone that uses Android 4.2.2 and a second phone that uses Android 4.4 (aka KitKat). The Jelly Bean phone had no functional issues with the app, but some CSS rules weren’t being applied correctly, which created some off-center layouts. The KitKat phone had no CSS issues, so it looked nice, but it had some functional issues regarding touch gestures. However, that could’ve been a problem with <a href="http://eightmedia.github.io/hammer.js/">Hammer.js</a>.</p>

<p>FYI, my team also encountered a problem in Android 4.4 and iOS 7 where scrolling wasn’t available for a <code>&lt;section&gt;</code> that had overflowing text. We tried the usual CSS rules, but to no avail.</p>

<h1 id="links-links">Links? Links!</h1>

<p>I saved a few links that I found particularly useful. I shall deposit said links right here because I can and totally not for SEO purposes.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://yaizabailen.com/setting-up-an-android-app-build-environment-with-android-sdk-and-phonegap-in-ubuntu-13-04/">Setting Up An Android App Build Environment With Android SDK and PhoneGap in Ubuntu 13.04</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/3127539/ubuntu-android-device-debug/3129903#3129903">StackOverflow: restarting adb</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6116724/how-to-use-android-phone-instead-of-emulator">StackOverflow: USB debugging mode</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://devgirl.org/2013/09/05/phonegap-3-0-stuff-you-should-know/">PhoneGap 3.0 - Stuff You Should Know</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="to-phonegap-or-not-to-phonegap">To PhoneGap or Not to PhoneGap</h1>

<p>So is PhoneGap worth the trouble? This blog post probably makes it sound like there’s a lot of shit to scoop before uncovering any treasure. That’s…mostly true. If rapid development is a priority, then PhoneGap is still a solid choice when you lack Objective-C and Java experience. I’ve heard from colleagues that learning Objective-C is its own special kind of hell, so that’s a +1 for PhoneGap, I guess.</p>

<p>To me, tech enthusiasts need to look at the bigger picture: imagine a world where mobile web apps dominate rather than having native apps dominate the smartphone landscape. Firefox OS is actually trying to embrace JavaScript, but why does it matter? Consider the differences in distribution. Forget app marketplaces. Forget Apple acting as a gatekeeper for iOS apps. Imagine that your app is as available as any other website. Web apps are becoming more and more powerful. There are new frameworks (e.g., <a href="http://famo.us/">Famous</a> and another brand new one that I can’t remember at the moment) that make it possible to replicate the oohlala of the much-lauded Yahoo! Weather native app.</p>

<p>The problem is that web apps for mobile devices can’t yet access native notifications. This is a huge obstacle for mobile web app dominance. Companies want their apps to have notifications to enhance user engagement and fight churn. Users want their apps to have notifications because it makes smartphones more helpful (although the line between helpful and spammy seems slimmer than my chances of becoming a guitar master). That said, web apps are getting better at using phones’ GPS sensors, cameras, accelerometers, etc. Hopefully the barrier between native app and mobile web app will continue to whither and eventually die like smallpox. In the words of unoriginal coaches every where, “WE CAN DO IT!”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Questions to ask dev interviewers]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/09/questions-to-ask-dev-interviewers/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-01-09T20:06:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/09/questions-to-ask-dev-interviewers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Do you have any questions for me?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When an employer/recruiter asks you this question, you should answer, “YES OF COURSE I DO.” Then you casually bombard them with the questions listed below. Although, you should keep in mind that some questions can be answered just by doing your homework (researching the company). So don’t ask <em>all the questions</em>.</p>

<h1 id="company-vision">Company Vision</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Where will the company be in 2 years? (maybe “2 years” should be greater if company is older)
    <ul>
      <li>Will the business model remain the same? Is the business model still in flux?</li>
      <li>How many employees will there be in X years? What many of them will be engineers?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Does the company plan to scale up? How?
    <ul>
      <li>Increased marketing efforts?</li>
      <li>Increased R&amp;D?</li>
      <li>Growing talent?</li>
      <li>Creating partnerships?</li>
      <li>Business model pivot?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="employee-logisticsculture">Employee logistics/culture</h1>

<ul>
  <li>What are typical work hours?</li>
  <li>
    <p>How often do people actually take vacations?</p>
  </li>
  <li>What are some examples of your company’s culture in play?
    <ul>
      <li>e.g., It’s one thing to say the company is open and friendly, but what are examples of that happening?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>What aspects of your company help shape the cuture?</p>
  </li>
  <li>Older/bigger companies: One of the stereotypical downsides of working at a more established company is that employees don’t feel like they have a big enough impact. How do you ensure employees can make substantive contributions rather than feel like a tiny cog in a big machine?
    <ul>
      <li>How do you ensure that employees always get to try/learn new things?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="engineering-logistics">Engineering Logistics</h1>

<ul>
  <li>How many engineers does the company have?
    <ul>
      <li>How many back-end, how many front-end, how many full-stack?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>How big are the engineering teams?
    <ul>
      <li>Will team size change a lot (scaling up)?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Do employees ever change teams/roles?</li>
  <li>Exactly who would I be working with?
    <ul>
      <li>What are their roles, backgrounds, etc?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>How does user feedback ultimately end up reaching the engineers?</li>
  <li>What kind of development cycle do they use?
    <ul>
      <li>What is the structure of a typical sprint?</li>
      <li>How often do engineers deploy?</li>
      <li>Do they use Agile SCRUM, Kanban, etc?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="engineering-culture">Engineering Culture</h1>

<ul>
  <li>How does the company ensure quick, painless onboarding?
    <ul>
      <li>(does the company ensure new hires don’t get overwhelmed by huge, existing codebase?)</li>
      <li>(or is there no onboarding at all because the company is too tiny?)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Does the company have strong opinions on coding aesthetics?
    <ul>
      <li>Does the company have a style guide?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Mentorship?</li>
  <li>Are there code reviews?
    <ul>
      <li>Are they scheduled or ad hoc? (“ad hoc” may be BS for “rarely”)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Is there time set aside for post-mortems, reflections, retrospectives, etc?</li>
  <li>What kind of testing is in place?
    <ul>
      <li>(unit testing, integration testing, e2e testing, QA engineering)?</li>
      <li>which tools?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Queues & Stacks from Scratch with JS Patterns]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/04/queues-stacks-javascript-class-patterns/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2014-01-04T16:04:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/01/04/queues-stacks-javascript-class-patterns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/12/26/queues-and-stacks-in-javascript/">previous post</a>, I began my quest to help noob programmers by introducing the basic computer science topic of data structures. I provided a quick overview of queues and stacks, so please read all about ‘em before engaging your eyeballs with this blog post. This time around, we’ll check out four different patterns for creating classes in JavaScript while learning how to build stacks and queues from scratch.</p>

<p>Before we go, I should warn you that I’m going to focus on describing the class instantiation patterns rather than thoroughly explaining the implementation of the data structures. Just keep in mind that we are going to explore building stacks and queues with objects rather than arrays. More specifically, we will use a property called <code>storage</code> that is an object, not an array. Now I know what you’re pondering.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Why?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is a beautiful question. Please ask it all the time (but please don’t troll me by leaving “Why?” in the comments section of this blog post). In this case, the answer to “Why?” may be a tad disatisfying. The answer is “because we can”, but don’t worry! It’ll be fun. Now, let’s start instantiating some motherhugging classes.</p>

<h1 id="functional-instantiation">1. Functional Instantiation</h1>

<p>The simplest way to implement classes is with a “maker” function that creates a new instance of the class and returns that instance so it can be stored as a variable. The new instance is just like any other JavaScript object. It can have properties that store relevant information about the instance (e.g., with a <code>Car</code> class, instances might have a <code>price</code> property). It can also have properties that store functions. These functions serve as <strong>methods</strong> that are tightly associated with the instance.</p>

<h4 id="characteristics">Characteristics</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Creates new copies of the same functions when creating a new instance of the same class. This lack of reuse takes up more memory and can leave an unsavory taste in some programmers’ mouths.</li>
  <li>There is no quick way to modify all instances of the class after they’ve been created. This will become more clear after examining the other instantiation tactics.</li>
  <li>Private variables can be created/used by harnessing <strong>closure scope</strong> superpowers, but I won’t get into that today.</li>
  <li>If you understand JavaScript functions and objects, then you can understand classes implemented via functional instantiation (other instantiation techniques require knowledge of <code>this</code> and/or <code>new</code>).</li>
  <li>Could be used to create callable instances (i.e., the class could return a function rather than an object filled with properties).</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="example-code">Example code:</h4>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Stack from scratch (functional instantiation) </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">makeStack</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(comment){
  <span class="comment">// Provide private variables in closure scope</span>
  <span class="keyword">var</span> size = <span class="integer">0</span>;
  <span class="keyword">var</span> storage = {};
  <span class="keyword">var</span> instance = {};  <span class="comment">// Start building an instance of Stack class</span>

  <span class="comment">// Add extra properties for the hell of it</span>
  instance.annotation = comment;

  <span class="comment">// Add functions to the instance to serve as methods</span>
  <span class="comment">// (they will provide an interface to the stack's storage)</span>
  instance.<span class="function">push</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(data){
    storage[size] = data;
    size++;
  };

  instance.<span class="function">pop</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
    <span class="keyword">if</span>(size &gt; <span class="integer">0</span>){  <span class="comment">// Only perform pop actions if the stack has data</span>
      size--;
      <span class="keyword">var</span> data = storage[size];
      <span class="keyword">delete</span> storage[size];  <span class="comment">// Don't forget to delete from storage!</span>
      <span class="keyword">return</span> data;
    }
  };

  instance.<span class="function">size</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
    <span class="keyword">return</span> size;
  };

  <span class="keyword">return</span> instance;
};

<span class="comment">// Create and use an instance of the Stack class</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> myStack = makeStack(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">I'm a stack! Whoa.</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>);
myStack.push(<span class="integer">1</span>);              <span class="comment">// myStack stores 1</span>
myStack.push(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">b</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);            <span class="comment">// myStack stores 1 and 'b'</span>
myStack.push(<span class="integer">3</span>);              <span class="comment">// myStack stores 1, 'b', and 3</span>
console.log(myStack.pop());   <span class="comment">// logs 3</span>
console.log(myStack.size());  <span class="comment">// logs 2</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h1 id="functional-instantiation-wshared-methods">2. Functional Instantiation w/Shared Methods</h1>

<p>By utilizing an object filled with methods, several classes can be created that have the same methods without creating new copies of said methods. The classes will use their own function references to refer to the same set of shared methods. Therefore, using shared methods eats up less memory than functional instantiation <em>without</em> shared methods.</p>

<h4 id="characteristics-1">Characteristics</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Reuses functions (which conserves memory) by getting function references from a utility such as <a href="http://underscorejs.org/#extend">Underscore.js</a>’s <code>_.extend(instance,methods)</code>.</li>
  <li>Retains the same benefits as functional instantiation <em>without</em> shared methods.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="example-code-1">Example code:</h4>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Queue from scratch (functional instantiation with shared methods) </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">makeQueue</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(queueName, comment){

  <span class="comment">// You can use object literal notation for `instance` (instead of dot notation),</span>
  <span class="comment">// but then we have to use `this` and we lose the privacy of closure scope</span>
  <span class="comment">// (e.g., `storage` is no longer private), so this kind of sucks.</span>
  <span class="keyword">var</span> instance = {
    <span class="key">name</span>: queueName,
    <span class="key">annotation</span>: comment,
    <span class="key">head</span>: <span class="integer">0</span>,
    <span class="key">tail</span>: <span class="integer">0</span>,
    <span class="key">storage</span>: {}
  };

  <span class="comment">// The _.extend() function is provided by the Underscore.js library</span>
  _.extend(instance, sharedQueueMethods);

  <span class="keyword">return</span> instance;
};

<span class="comment">// The object below stores methods that could be shared with other classes</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> sharedQueueMethods = {
  <span class="function">enqueue</span>: <span class="keyword">function</span>(data){
    <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail] = data;
    <span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail++;
    <span class="comment">// The tail points to the next EMPTY &quot;spot&quot; for data to be stored</span>
    <span class="comment">// it does NOT point to the last OCCUPIED &quot;spot&quot; in the storage</span>
  },
  <span class="function">dequeue</span>: <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
    <span class="keyword">if</span>(<span class="local-variable">this</span>.head &lt;= <span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail){  <span class="comment">// Check the queue's size</span>
      <span class="keyword">var</span> data = <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.head];

      <span class="comment">// Deleting is even more important for queues than for stacks</span>
      <span class="comment">// (memory leaks are a bigger threat for queues)</span>
      <span class="keyword">delete</span> <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.head];
      <span class="local-variable">this</span>.head++;
      <span class="keyword">return</span> data;
    }
  },
  <span class="function">size</span>: <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
    <span class="keyword">return</span> <span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail - <span class="local-variable">this</span>.head;
  }
};

<span class="comment">// Create and use an instance of the Queue class:</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> myCoolQueue = makeQueue(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Jeff's Queue</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>,<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">Hello, world!</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);
myCoolQueue.enqueue(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">a</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);             <span class="comment">// myCoolQueue stores 'a'</span>
myCoolQueue.enqueue(<span class="integer">2</span>);               <span class="comment">// myCoolQueue stores 'a' and 2</span>
myCoolQueue.enqueue(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">c</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);             <span class="comment">// myCoolQueue stores 'a', 2, and 'c'</span>
console.log(myCoolQueue.dequeue());   <span class="comment">// output: 'a'</span>
console.log(myCoolQueue.size());      <span class="comment">// output: 2</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h1 id="prototypal-instantiation">3. Prototypal Instantiation</h1>

<p>The key to prototypal instantiation is the use of <code>Object.create()</code> to utilize shared methods. Unlike functional instantiation with shared methods, there is no need to use an <code>extend()</code> function.</p>

<p>While it’s possible to use a prototype’s functions with <code>Object.create(ExampleClass.prototype);</code>, it’s also possible to (ironically) avoid the word “prototype” altogether by using <code>Object.create(sharedMethods);</code>.</p>

<h4 id="characteristics-2">Characteristics</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Reuses shared functions via <code>Object.create(Example.prototype)</code> or <code>Object.create(objectOfFunctions)</code>.</li>
  <li>Unlike functional instantiation, function references are shared. Each instance of the class does not get its own function references that point to the shared methods. This saves even more memory (although it is a very small improvement).</li>
  <li>Unlike functional instantiation, there is no way to use closure scope to enforce privacy of variables.</li>
  <li>Variables are stored on the returned object (aka <code>instance</code>), which means the shared stack methods need to use the keyword <code>this</code> to access the necessary data. It’s not a huge bummer, but if you’re a beginner, then <code>this</code> can be a confusing concept.</li>
  <li>Can use prototype chains for dynamic method modification and inheritance (subclasses!).</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="example-code-2">Example code:</h4>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Stack from scratch (prototypal instantiation) </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">makeStack</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(comment){
  <span class="keyword">var</span> instance = Object.create(sharedStackMethods);
  instance.annotation = comment;
  instance.size = <span class="integer">0</span>;
  instance.storage = {};

  <span class="keyword">return</span> instance;
};

<span class="keyword">var</span> sharedStackMethods = {
  <span class="function">push</span>: <span class="keyword">function</span>(data){
    <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.size] = data;
    <span class="local-variable">this</span>.size++;
  },
  <span class="function">pop</span>: <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
    <span class="keyword">if</span>(<span class="local-variable">this</span>.size &gt; <span class="integer">0</span>){
      <span class="local-variable">this</span>.size--;
      <span class="keyword">var</span> data = <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.size];
      <span class="keyword">delete</span> <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.size];
      <span class="keyword">return</span> data;
    }
  },
  <span class="function">size</span>: <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
    <span class="keyword">return</span> <span class="local-variable">this</span>.size;
  }
};

<span class="comment">// Create an instance of the Stack class:</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> myStack = makeStack(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">I'm a stack! Whoa.</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>);
<span class="comment">// Using the instance doesn't change from one class pattern to another</span>
myStack.push(<span class="integer">1</span>);              <span class="comment">// myStack stores 1</span>
myStack.push(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">b</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);            <span class="comment">// myStack stores 1 and 'b'</span>
myStack.push(<span class="integer">3</span>);              <span class="comment">// myStack stores 1, 'b', and 3</span>
console.log(myStack.pop());   <span class="comment">// logs 3</span>
console.log(myStack.size());  <span class="comment">// logs 2</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h1 id="pseudoclassical-instantiation">4. Pseudoclassical Instantiation</h1>

<p>This is the most commonly used class pattern. It’s also the most complicated because, in addition to using the <code>this</code> keyword, it involves two concepts that the other class patterns don’t require: the <code>new</code> keyword and prototypes. Prototypal instantiation uses prototypes via <code>Object.create()</code>, but pseudoclassical instantiation needs you to explicitly type out <code>ClassName.prototype.methodName</code>, which is just another source of confusion for beginners.</p>

<p>Also, it’s the only class pattern that uses a true <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constructor_(object-oriented_programming)">constructor</a> for creating new instances. Other class patterns use instantiator functions that explicitly return a new instance. The pseudoclassical class pattern does not perform such a return thanks to the <code>new</code> keyword.</p>

<h4 id="characteristics-3">Characteristics</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Uses prototype chains to provide methods to instances of a class.</li>
  <li>Allows for dynamic method modification and inheritance (subclasses!) via prototype chains.</li>
  <li>Refers to the instance that’s being created with the <code>this</code> keyword.</li>
  <li>Needs the <code>new</code> keyword to make an instance of a class.</li>
  <li>Has a true constructor that is named with a noun rather than a verb. The name is capitalized.</li>
  <li>Is the most commonly used class pattern.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="example-code-3">Example code:</h4>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Queue from scratch (pseudoclassical instantiation) </span></figcaption>
 <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="comment">// Class name is now a noun (no verb), and it starts with an upper case letter</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">Queue</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(queueName, comment){
  <span class="comment">// Notice the use of 'this'</span>
  <span class="local-variable">this</span>.name = queueName,
  <span class="local-variable">this</span>.annotation = comment,
  <span class="local-variable">this</span>.head: <span class="integer">0</span>,
  <span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail: <span class="integer">0</span>,
  <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage: {}
};

<span class="comment">// Notice the use of 'prototype'</span>
Queue.prototype.<span class="function">enqueue</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(data){
  <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail] = data;
  <span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail++;
};
Queue.prototype.<span class="function">dequeue</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
  <span class="keyword">if</span>(<span class="local-variable">this</span>.head &lt;= <span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail){
    <span class="keyword">var</span> data = <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.head];
    <span class="keyword">delete</span> <span class="local-variable">this</span>.storage[<span class="local-variable">this</span>.head];
    <span class="local-variable">this</span>.head++;
    <span class="keyword">return</span> data;
  }
};
Queue.prototype.<span class="function">size</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(){
  <span class="keyword">return</span> <span class="local-variable">this</span>.tail - <span class="local-variable">this</span>.head;
};

<span class="comment">// Create an instance of the Stack class by using the 'new' keyword:</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> myCoolQueue = <span class="keyword">new</span> Queue(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Jeff's Queue</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>,<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">The grass is always greener, but just as hard to mowww!</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>);
<span class="comment">// Use the instance just like in previous examples</span>
myCoolQueue.enqueue(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">a</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);             <span class="comment">// myCoolQueue stores 'a'</span>
myCoolQueue.enqueue(<span class="integer">2</span>);               <span class="comment">// myCoolQueue stores 'a' and 2</span>
myCoolQueue.enqueue(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">c</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);             <span class="comment">// myCoolQueue stores 'a', 2, and 'c'</span>
console.log(myCoolQueue.dequeue());   <span class="comment">// output: 'a'</span>
console.log(myCoolQueue.size());      <span class="comment">// output: 2</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Queues &amp; Stacks in JavaScript (with Batman and Superman)]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/12/26/queues-and-stacks-in-javascript/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-12-26T15:54:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/12/26/queues-and-stacks-in-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The proverbial “they” say (says?) it’s good to write technical blog posts. Blog posts that get down and dirty with the nitty gritty of low-level, in-the-weeds details and nuances accompanied by jargon, acronyms, and name-dropping are all the rage in the dev community. More importantly, I really want to help beginners learn programming, so I may as well teach some basic concepts via my blog. (Later on, I hope to contribute more to <a href="http://www.theodinproject.com/">The Odin Project</a>, which is a free, open-source, online resource for beginners created by a very cool individual.)</p>

<p>So as my first foray in technical blog posts, I present to all loveable noobs: the introductory data structures known as stacks and queues.</p>

<h1 id="whats-a-stack">What’s a Stack?</h1>

<p>A stack is a collection of items (or data) that follow a particular rule: the last item to join the collection is the first one to leave.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The <strong>L</strong>ast data <strong>I</strong>n is the <strong>F</strong>irst data <strong>O</strong>ut (<strong>LIFO</strong>)</li>
  <li>Add data: <strong>push</strong></li>
  <li>Remove data: <strong>pop</strong></li>
  <li>Data enters and exits at the same end of the stack (at the <strong>top</strong>)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="simple-implementation">Simple implementation</h2>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Simple Stack (array-based example)</span><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1590247/how-do-you-implement-a-stack-and-a-queue-in-javascript">Stack Overflow </a></figcaption> <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> stack = [];
stack.push(<span class="integer">1</span>);  <span class="comment">// use the push method provided by the Array prototype</span>
stack.push(<span class="integer">2</span>);
stack.push(<span class="integer">3</span>);
console.log(stack);  <span class="comment">// output: [1,2,3]</span>

<span class="keyword">var</span> popped = stack.pop();  <span class="comment">// use the pop method provided by the Array prototype</span>
console.log(popped);  <span class="comment">// output: 3</span>
console.log(stack);  <span class="comment">// output: [1,2]</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h2 id="ridiculous-analogy">Ridiculous analogy</h2>

<p>Imagine you’ve found an old, abandoned well. You think to yourself, “Bruce Wayne fell down a well when he was a kid, and I wanna be just like the Batman, so I’m gonna fall down this sweet well!” But you hesitate because …it’s a well, and wells are scary, ya know?</p>

<p>Unbeknownst to you, <a href="http://batman.wikia.com/wiki/Harley_Quinn">your arch-nemesis</a> is out walking her <a href="http://batman.wikia.com/wiki/Bud_and_Lou">pet hyenas</a>. She spots you, and quickly runs over to shove you into the well. She giggles in delight at the sight of your plight. She then hides and waits for more people to walk near the well so she can <strong>push</strong> them too.</p>

<p>It just so happens that this well has the diameter of a single person’s width. When someone is pushed into the well, they land on top of the last person who fell in before them. This creates a <strong>stack</strong> of people and some rather pronounced discomfort. Eventually, there are 5 people in this deep-yet-thin well, and you decide it’s time to call for help to get rescued.</p>

<p>To your disappointment, the not-so-dark knight named Superman arrives to pull you well-dwellers out (one at a time). The last one pushed into the well is the first to <strong>pop</strong> out. <em>LIFO.</em></p>

<h1 id="whats-a-queue">What’s a Queue?</h1>

<p>A queue is a collection of items (or data) that follow the real-life “rules” of waiting in a line of people: the first item to join the collection is the first one to leave the collection.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The <strong>F</strong>irst data <strong>I</strong>n is the <strong>F</strong>irst data <strong>O</strong>ut (<strong>FIFO</strong>)</li>
  <li>Add data: <strong>enqueue</strong></li>
  <li>Remove data: <strong>dequeue</strong></li>
  <li>Data exits at the: <strong>head</strong> of the queue</li>
  <li>Data enters at the: <strong>tail</strong> of the queue</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="simple-implementation-1">Simple implementation</h2>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption class="code-header" style="margin-bottom:-5px;"><span>Simple Queue (array-based example)</span><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1590247/how-do-you-implement-a-stack-and-a-queue-in-javascript">Stack Overflow </a></figcaption> <div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>
<span class="keyword">var</span> queue = [];
queue.push(<span class="integer">1</span>);  <span class="comment">// &quot;enqueue&quot;</span>
queue.push(<span class="integer">2</span>);
queue.push(<span class="integer">3</span>);
console.log(queue);  <span class="comment">// output: [1,2,3]</span>

<span class="keyword">var</span> dequeued = queue.shift();  <span class="comment">// &quot;dequeue&quot;</span>
console.log(dequeued);  <span class="comment">// output: 1</span>
console.log(queue);  <span class="comment">// output: [2,3]</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
 </figure></notextile></div>

<h2 id="ridiculous-analogy-1">Ridiculous analogy</h2>

<p>Batman decides to do some in-the-field combat training. He drops into the middle of a gang meeting and yells, “I’ve sent your buddies to jail. I know you want revenge. Catch me if you can. P.S. I’m Batman!” Why does the cowled hero do this? We all know Batman is a smart dude, and sure enough, he has a clever plan. He lures the baddies who are running after him into a narrow alley.</p>

<p>The gangsters can only approach Batman one at a time to fit in the narrow alley, so they form a line (aka <strong>queue</strong>). The gangster at the front of the line is the first gangster knocked out (aka <strong>dequeued</strong>) by Batman (<strong>first in; first out</strong>). You might even say that Batman’s fists aim for the <strong>head</strong> of the queue and foolish gangsters enter at the <strong>tail</strong> of the line of doom.</p>

<h1 id="the-story-will-continue">The Story Will Continue</h1>

<p>Stay tuned for more blog posts on data structures. My next technical blog post will examine how to implement stacks and queues from scratch (without arrays) to get a deeper understanding of push, pop, enqueue, and dequeue. I know you can’t wait for the moment I deliver on this promise. I can hear your panting through my WiFi, but please stay patient. I was busy working on a <a href="https://github.com/RebootJeff/cocompare">web app</a> and then a <a href="https://github.com/RebootJeff/phone-tag-phonegap">mobile app</a>. Now, I’m busy with job searching while possibly starting mini-project.</p>

<p>On a mildly amusing, unrelated note: isn’t it funny to think about the phrase “stay tuned”? It’s getting rather archaic now that terrestrial, over-the-air TV and radio are losing popularity. Yes, these are the random things I think about as I write blog posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] My Formal Apology]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/11/19/hackr-diary-my-apology/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-11-19T21:53:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/11/19/hackr-diary-my-apology</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My previous blog post was nearly 3 weeks ago. Why? What’s stopped me from posting more stories of life at Hack Reactor? For the past several days, I have been working on an individual project. I was very confident going into it, and I should eventually blog specifically about the initial stages, but as it turned out …there is a crap-ton of stuff to juggle when developing a web app. There are so many things that can go wrong in your workflow –not just in your code.</p>

<h1 id="things-that-kept-me-busy">Things That Kept me Busy</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Defaut installation of node/npm on Ubuntu led to file permissions issues. Oh shit.</li>
  <li>Figuring out Yeoman: Before <code>npm install -g yo</code>: I wonder what will happen. After <code>yo generator-angularexpress</code>: What is all this stuff?! Oh nice.</li>
  <li>Figuring out Grunt: How can I get it to work with Stylus? Oh nice.</li>
  <li>Easy, but time-consuming (to make sure you don’t break something that used to work)
    <ul>
      <li>Organizing files/folders in a professional way (inter-file <code>require</code> statements can break)</li>
      <li>Using environment variables (typos can be devastating)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Facebook Authorization
    <ul>
      <li>Making 2 FB apps (one for dev environment; one for production environment)</li>
      <li>Figuring out the proper callback URL</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Databases
    <ul>
      <li>Juggling MySQL in development environment, then switching to PostgreSQL in production.</li>
      <li>Why is the production database getting flooded? Oh there’s a random configuration setting I missed in Sequelize.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Random Heroku hiccups (at one point, a node module provider went down, causing Heroku’s <code>npm install</code> to die).</li>
</ul>

<p>These are just a few of the little obstacles that add up. You don’t see them coming. They take quite a bit of time to hunt down.</p>

<h1 id="nerdy-chuck-norris-jokes">Nerdy Chuck Norris Jokes</h1>

<p>As an apology for not blogging much in the past 3 weeks, here are some jokes from <strong><a href="http://www.icndb.com/">the best API ever</a></strong>:</p>

<p>All arrays Chuck Norris declares are of infinite size, because Chuck Norris knows no bounds.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris doesn’t have disk latency because the hard drive knows to hurry the hell up.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris can’t test for equality because he has no equal.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris burst the dot com bubble.</p>

<p>All browsers support the hex definitions #chuck and #norris for the colors black and blue.</p>

<p>MySpace actually isn’t your space, it’s Chuck’s (he just lets you use it).</p>

<p>Chuck Norris can solve the Towers of Hanoi in one move.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris finished World of Warcraft.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris doesn’t use web standards as the web will conform to him.</p>

<p>Whiteboards are white because Chuck Norris scared them that way.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris can delete the Recycling Bin.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris’s beard can type 140 wpm.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris can unit test entire applications with a single assert.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris doesn’t need sudo, he just types “Chuck Norris” before his commands.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris doesn’t need a debugger, he just stares down the code until the bug confesses.</p>

<p>The class object inherits from Chuck Norris</p>

<p>Chuck Norris knows the last digit of PI.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris’ Internet connection is faster upstream than downstream because even data has more incentive to run from him than to him.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris’s keyboard has the Any key.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris can install iTunes without installing Quicktime.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris’s OSI network model has only one layer - Physical.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris compresses his files by doing a flying round house kick to the hard drive.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris uses canvas in IE.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris’s database has only one table, ‘Kick’, which he DROPs frequently.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris’s brain waves are suspected to be harmful to cell phones.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris sits at the stand-up.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris has never registered an account. He just logs in.</p>

<p>Code runs faster when Chuck Norris glares at it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Week 5: Final Sprints]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/28/hackr-diary-week-5/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-10-28T22:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/28/hackr-diary-week-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20131028/caltrain.jpg" alt="caltrain" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">Good morning</p>

<p>No more sprints! I’m both sad and relieved. The sprints have provided enough structure to ensure a guided education thus far. They’ve equipped me with enough skill to yield the self-belief that I can actually build a complete web app …which is good because that’s exactly what I’m going to do starting this week. Looking back on week 5 makes me think I might miss the relative safety of paired programming, but I’m pumped to be diving into my own project.</p>

<p>By the way, this blog post is really long. I think I’m going to split up future blog posts, and I’m going to post more frequently.</p>

<h1 id="recap-of-events">Recap of Events</h1>

<h3 id="alumni-panel">Alumni Panel</h3>

<p>Early in the week, there was a truly invaluable guest speaker event. Six Hack Reactor alumni held a Q&amp;A session with current students. One alumnus is a Hacker-in-Residence at Hack Reactor. His role is a paid, part-time, short-term job supporting the school. There are a handful of Hacker-in-Residences at HackR at any given time. After their stints, they are put through the same job finding process that students who didn’t want to become a Resident normally go through.</p>

<p>The other five alumni were from Adap.tv, Adobe, DocuSign, Edmodo, and Versal, respectively. They had a variety of roles including smartphone app development, front-end MVC engineering, internal QA, data visualization, and full-stack development. I have to admit that I was a bit judgemental about the QA role at first, but it actually sounded legit by the end of the Q&amp;A session. For what it’s worth, the Adap.tv guy was hired even though he doesn’t have a college degree! In my opinion, that’s awesome, and it really says a lot about the meritocracy found in the tech job market (…or the non-traditional, new-school nature of the Bay Area).</p>

<p>There was a ton of insight gleaned from the alumni panel. Examples of advice include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ask employers about their onboarding process (smaller companies might not have one, and that can be a turn-off for some newbies).</li>
  <li>Invest in social capital. Wow, that was a really buzzwordy sentence so let me translate: get to know your co-workers. “Ask them out” to coffee breaks, happy hours, lunches, etc. This may sound like basic networking at first, but I think the point is that in software development, you’re going to be asking others for help quite a lot, so it’s good to build a rapport ASAP to make asking for assistance as natural as possible. This is something I never really considered before, but after all the paired programming I’ve done at Hack Reactor, it makes a ton of sense to establish rapports that foster collaborative vibes.</li>
  <li>Ask employers to set up a meeting between you and your potential boss. It’s ok –this is totally ok. I used to work in an industry where this would never really be possible, so I had to ask if this is ok after one alumnus mentioned how one of his prioties when job hunting was to find a cool boss. I want a cool boss too!</li>
  <li>NEVER make the first move for salary negotiations. Let them make an offer before you start specifying any numbers.</li>
  <li>Specific to HackR: Don’t be too eager to accept your first job offer. You will get more. Shop around. It’s tempting to accept your first or second job offer just because employment is such a major goal when deciding to join Hack Reactor in the first place. However, joining Hack Reactor isn’t something you do just to get a job –it’s something you do to get an <em>ideal</em> job.</li>
</ul>

<p>Sorry, but I forgot to take thorough notes during the alumni panel, so the list above is rather short.</p>

<h3 id="more-guest-speakers">More Guest Speakers</h3>

<p>Now might be a good time to point out that Hack Reactor has guest speakers at least one evening per week. Attendance is optional. Oftentimes students choose to work on their assignments/projects at the workstations rather than stay in the lecture area to listen to the guest speaker.</p>

<p>What’s my point? This week was the first time I didn’t really have enough time to fully invest in the guest speakers. Rudely, I’ve forgotten that names of the speakers, but one guy spoke about databases (i.e., engineering decisions you might face when designing/creating/maintaining/scaling a database) and another guy (from Khan Academy) spoke about <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a>, the JavaScript library written and open-sourced by Facebook. Relevant link: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GW0rj4sNH2w">React presented at JSConf</a></p>

<h3 id="picking-personal-projects">Picking Personal Projects</h3>

<p>To be honest, I wasn’t thrilled with the way HackR arranged the transition from sprints to personal projects. Students were under the impression that we’d get more support/attention for coming up with project ideas, but we weren’t given much time to brainstorm. Instead of dedicating a lecture to a guided brainstorming session, students had to come up with ideas in their spare time (which is tough when busy worrying about Ruby and Angular for the sprints).</p>

<h3 id="social-night-haunted-house">Social Night: Haunted House</h3>

<p>Once again, I did not attend social night. On one hand, I feel bad that my cohort has generally had low participation in the weekly social nights. On the other hand, the consensus seems to be that the social nights just don’t feel all that appealing. The first one was awesome; the others were “meh.”</p>

<p>Instead of going to the Social Night event last Saturday, I went to a nice happy hour/dinner with a few other students. Afterwards, I went back to HackR to continue tackling client-side user authentication with my Angular sprint partner. We failed, but we got a lot of other stuff done during the day, so I felt ok about the sprint as a whole. Plus, my partner and I established a fun rapport so even failing to get “auth” working was a funny time.</p>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<p>Week 5 included assignments for building a URL shortening web app to further improve students’ full-stack skills.</p>

<h3 id="ruby-sinatra-activerecord-sqlite">Ruby, Sinatra, ActiveRecord, SQLite</h3>

<p>Server-side code used a lot of Ruby and Sinatra. HackR chose not to teach us students Ruby on Rails (RoR) because Sinatra is simpler than Rails. It’s easy to be bummed about this, but in hindsight, I’m not worried about it. Yes, Rails is a big deal right now in Silicon Valley, but I’m under the impression that RoR was embraced because of it’s great for rapid prototyping. Times are changing though. There are now more options for rapid prototyping. More importantly, I’m at the point in my HackR-guided education where I have built up enough fundamental know-how to make me confident that I can learn RoR later.</p>

<p>For now, it’s more important to learn concepts about MVC/MV* development, user authentication, databases, etc. Speaking of databases, there isn’t much for me to say about SQLite because students were harnessing ActiveRecord magic to manipulate a simple SQLite database with only two tables. We had to use <a href="https://github.com/cldwalker/tux">tux</a> to do database probing, which is slightly less convenient than using MySQL’s terminal interface (as we did in the previous week).</p>

<h3 id="angular">Angular</h3>

<p>The students were pretty hyped up to learn Angular as our final sprint. We’ve invested a lot of time into learning Backbone, but word on the street (a really nerdy street) is that Angular is the “new hotness” that will take over the world of front-end JavaScript for single-page web apps.</p>

<p>Overall, I think the students’ reception of Angular was torn. Some love the power (Angular’s data-binding is pretty addicting); some find discomfort in the need to learn some rather bizarre syntax (Angular forces you to write HTML with “directives”).</p>

<p>Here’s the low down: Backbone feels like the traditional, familiar option whereas Angular feels like the more experimental, exotic option. Yes, it took us awhile to appreciate Backbone, but once we got comfortable with it, we realized how easy it is to comprehend after you get your mind around it.</p>

<p>For Angular, the learning curve is a lot less steep, but it also seems like it will be harder to master. There is more “magic” …and now I’m realizing I should explain that word.</p>

<h4 id="aside-what-is-magic">Aside: What is “magic”?</h4>

<p>When I say “magic,” I’m using it colloquially to refer to abstraction that feels harder to comprehend and feels less intuitive. For analogy*, a door knob abstracts mechanical bits. You may not be a locksmith, but it’s probably easy for a child to imagine how it works. Even as a child, you probably had some intuition that door knobs just have some simple mechanism for converting rotational movement of the knob into longitudinal movement of the latch On the other hand, it’s a bit hard for a child to imagine how a digital camera works. Even an old-school film-based camera feels magical at that tender age when you’re first capable of comprehending door knobs. Ahhh…those were the days, am I right?</p>

<p><strong>*By the way, can we make “for analogy” a thing in the same way that “for example” is a thing?</strong></p>

<p>Also, if you google “parts of a door knob,” you will see some complex diagrams, but I will defend my analogy! For the sake of argument, let’s just say door knobs use simple cams.</p>

<h4 id="back-to-my-thoughts-on-angular">Back to my thoughts on Angular</h4>

<p>So why does Angular seem so magical? By using Angular’s library of directives, you can have the browser display a list of items without writing DOM-manipulating code (i.e., jQuery). You can sort those items without writing a sorting function. You can filter those items without writing a sorting function. In Angular, you’re not supposed to use jQuery to change/update the HTML on the page. Angular takes care of that for you. How does it do that? Magic (directives). I haven’t even touched Angular’s feature that allows you to just create your own semantic HTML tags (e.g., <code>&lt;tab&gt;&lt;pane&gt;Content for Pane 1&lt;/pane&gt;&lt;pane&gt;Content for Pane 2&lt;/pane&gt;&lt;/tab&gt;</code>).</p>

<h3 id="routers-templates-user-authentication">Routers, Templates, User Authentication</h3>

<p>With MVC frameworks comes routers and templates. With web apps comes user authentication (sometimes).</p>

<p>On the server-side, routing involves RESTful APIs, which are fairly tidy interfaces that allow clients to talk to servers. On the client-side, routing involves flow control and updating the URL in the browser address bar so that it looks pretty/semantic. For example, you may want to switch to an editing panel when the user clicks a button. The router changes the URL to end in <code>/edit</code> without causing the page to refresh. The router also calls a function that might do edit-related things such as rendering an editing panel.</p>

<p>Templates are used to create sections of HTML that will contain dynamic content. Let’s say you want to render an unordered list (<code>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</code>), and the app will determine how many items (<code>&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</code>) will be in the list. Templates take care of that.</p>

<p>On the server-side, routing and templating is pretty easy with Sinatra. On the client-side, routing with Angular feels easier than routing with Backbone. Templates are way easier in Angular for me.</p>

<p>In any case, I find user authentication isn’t very straightforward, but I haven’t tried many gems for Ruby nor <a href="http://passportjs.org/">Passport</a> for Node.js. You need to check for authentication, redirect visitors as necessary, encrypt passwords (AND usernames –don’t forget that), save login info into a database, manage sessions/cookies, etc. A surprising amount of mistakes can be made.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Week 4: Now Entering Callback Hell]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/21/hackr-diary-week-4/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-10-21T21:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/21/hackr-diary-week-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20131021/joebowers_at_hackreactor.jpg" alt="photo of Joe Bowers presentation" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">Joe Bowers from Mixpanel discussing tech decisions based on company culture</p>

<p>Another week down, another blog post arriving a Monday rather than the planned Sunday. Woops. Week 4 ended on a more stressful note for me (more on that in the <em>What I Learned</em> section <a href="#what-i-learned">below</a>), so I really felt the need to relax and decompress yesterday rather than write up this blog post. That said, once I complete roughly 25% of a blog post, I really start enjoying the writing process.</p>

<p>Because the school educates us students at such a tough pace, it’s tempting to say every week is a game changer, the most challenging week ever, the most interesting, etc. Well I’m going to induldge and say week #4 was the craziest week thus far.</p>

<p>I discovered that the Hack Reactor directory contains a partially complete list of all alumni’s employers. I started looking up some of the companies during a break from work. I didn’t have much time, but what I saw really inspired me. Now I’m even more excited about my own future prospects. <em>Hooray!</em></p>

<p>There were two guest speakers this week. They both were quite technical, and I took time to smell the roses by taking a moment to think to myself, “Wow I’ve learned a lot because I understand all this very technical, very specific stuff discussed by these speakers.” <em>Hooray!</em></p>

<p>There were a couple of <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/06/hackr-diary-week-2/#toy-problems">toy problems</a> that gave me some trouble this week. Maybe I’m putting too much pressure on myself, but solving a toy problem gives me a lot of self-confidence …and failing a toy problem puts a figurative frown on the figurative face of my mood for the rest of the morning (or longer). <em>Dammit!</em></p>

<p>Students are told not to worry about comparing themselves to peers, but the seniors are killing it. I feel happy for them, but sometimes their impressive projects make me second-guess myself. Can I come up with a cool idea for an app? Self-doubt is creeping in. I only have one more week to think of something. <em>Dammit!</em></p>

<p>As you can tell from the previous four paragraphs, the previous week was a bit of a battle between fear and pride. The worst part was falling behind on the databases sprint. The best part was watching seniors’ presentations.</p>

<h1 id="recap-of-events">Recap of Events</h1>

<h3 id="guest-speaker-pamela-fox">Guest Speaker: Pamela Fox</h3>

<p>On Monday, Pamela Fox (formerly Coursera, currently Khan Academy) gave a great Backbone presentation at Hack Reactor. I wrote about it <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/hackr-diary-a-visit-from-pamela-fox-re-backbone/">right here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="guest-speaker-joe-bowers">Guest Speaker: Joe Bowers</h3>

<p>On Thursday, Joe Bowers (pictured at the top) gave an intriguing talk about intra-company coding culture. There are a lot of decisions to make with regards to software architecture/design, and Joe explained that many decisions are made based on coding culture/philosophy. In other words, many decisions come down to subjective thinking and preferences for certain aesthetics. His primary example was about Mixpanel’s tendency to embrace code cleanliness to the point of sacrificing <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don't_repeat_yourself">DRYness</a> and abstraction. Their code is very explicit, so you always know what it’s doing without having to spend hours studying various layers of abstraction or other quirks that might improve elegance at the cost of human-readability.</p>

<h3 id="social-night-lit-crawl-skipped">Social Night: Lit Crawl (skipped)</h3>

<p>I’m not sure what <a href="http://litcrawl.org/sf/">SF Lit Crawl</a> is, but that was the designated event for social night. I decided not to join because I felt like I needed to spend more time studying ORMs (more on that below). Spending Saturday evening at Hack Reactor is actually quite nice. There were probably 10-20 students/staff still hanging out at HackR. Sadly, I wasn’t very productive. I think my brain was just too tired from battling asychronous database queries.</p>

<p>On a related note, I’ve told HackR staff that the Social Nights are not well-organized. It’s clear that they are not given a high priority (attendance is optional for students), and I think they’re missed opportunities for cohort bonding. With a class size of nearly 30 students, it’s hard to get to know everyone when you spend most of your time with one person every two days (during 2-day paired programming sprints).</p>

<h3 id="seniors-group-project-presentations-practice">Seniors’ Group Project Presentations (practice)</h3>

<p>So. Friggin’. Stellar.</p>

<p>Just. Absolutely. Outstanding.</p>

<p>I was truly blown away by the seniors’ final projects. HackR students work on two major projects during their time here. The first is an individual project, the second is a group project. Students present their projects to some Hack Reactor staff and fellow students as practice for when they have to present to employers on hiring day.</p>

<p>The group projects I saw last Saturday were incredible. They only had 2-3 weeks to create something worth bragging about, and they certainly surpassed my expectations. I’m half-inspired and half-worried. What they’ve done makes me prouder to be associated with Hack Reactor, but now I definitely feel more pressure to reach a similar level of awesomeness. Here are a few highlights:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Personal website powered by <a href="http://famo.us/">Famo.us</a>: Making a personal website might not sound impressive, but don’t get the wrong idea. I’m not talking about an About.me page. The site has very sexy Twitter/Facebook feed integration. The product looks like something Feedly or Flipboard would create (pro quality). <strong>More importantly</strong>, the team behind the product is one of the first to use brand new tech called Famous. Famous is a JavaScript framework for continuously rendering webpages with the power of client GPUs rather than CPUs. It replaces typical HTML with a bunch of <code>div</code> elements that are constantly being updated (at ~60 frames per second) with new values for their properties. The Hack Reactor students not only used the new tech (which is still in <em>private</em> beta), they also <em>contributed</em> to the Famous codebase. In fact, Famous will be using the students’ product at future HTML5 conferences to demo the power of the framework!</li>
  <li>Virtual Furniture Placement: A group of 4 (or was it 5?) made an app that takes user-uploaded photos of empty rooms and allows the user to place virtual, 3D furniture into the photos. The 3D rendering looks so good! It’s amazing what you can do with JavaScript (I believe they used <a href="http://threejs.org/">three.js</a>). This is definitely an app that every home seller and furniture seller should use.</li>
  <li>Reddit Submission Scheduler: It’s basically <a href="http://bufferapp.com/">Buffer</a>, but it’s for Reddit instead of Twitter. The students have built a product that I imagine every marketer wants: an app that allows you to submit a post to Reddit at a future date/time. I actually wonder if Reddit will ban the app because it could potentially be abused to proliferate spam. That said, if Buffer can work for Twitter, than surely something similar can work for Reddit. The idea is simple and unglamorous, but it certainly meets a big demand. It’s easy to imagine a company willing to buy the students’ app.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<h2 id="nodejs-without-express">Node.js (without Express)</h2>

<p>Finally! Server-side code! Up to this point, the students have been just working with client-side assignments. With the <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a> sprint, we started sending HTTP requests back and forth between client and server. We have yet to use <a href="http://expressjs.com/">Express</a> or any other Node.js framework to make life easier. We used modules like http, fs, url, and so on. The asynchronous nature of Node.js was weird at first, but to be honest, a lot of us got around that complexity by using synchronous variants of methods (e.g., <code>fs.readFileSync()</code>in place of <code>fs.readFile()</code>).</p>

<h2 id="databases">Databases</h2>

<p>At first, I was excited by the idea of learning database goodness. But then the asynchronous nature of Node.js started raining on my parade. We worked with MySQL and a SQL-for-Node.js ORM called <a href="http://http://sequelizejs.com/">Sequelize</a>. ORMs are libraries that provide a way to interact with databases without having to write SQL code. In the case of Sequelize, you just write JavaScript code with the Sequelize class/methods to query the database.</p>

<p>It’s not all sunshine and rainbows though. I found Sequelize to be troublesome. You can get stuck in callback hell because unlike the http module for Node.js, the Sequalize module lacks synchronous variants of methods. We have yet to explore the benefits of asynchronous/non-blocking server-side code, so it’s hard to embrace the “pyramid of doom” (aka callback hell). When I asked for help, I was told to investigate another library for adding “promises” to my code. Promises help make asynchronous code much more manageable, but I didn’t have enough time to truly learn and implement them.</p>

<p>So what I’m basically saying is that last week ended on a crappy note: an unfinished assignment. I’ve been told not to worry because there will be more opportunities to learn databases when working on projects (during the 2nd half of the Hack Reactor course).</p>

<h1 id="in-other-news">In other news…</h1>

<h2 id="the-next-phase">The Next Phase</h2>

<p>There isn’t much time! In just a couple of weeks, the individual project phase begins. I have no good ideas for what to create! In my limited spare time, I’m playing Hawken, browsing Imgur, and freaking out about the personal project phase.</p>

<h2 id="nuances-of-javascript">Nuances of JavaScript</h2>

<p>On a more positive note, Hack Reactor shared this YouTube video <a href="https://twitter.com/HackReactor/status/390905108105818112">via Twitter</a>:</p>

<iframe width="300" height="225" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iSxNCYcPAFk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>As I watched it, I realized that it covered material I learned in the first week or so at Hack Reactor. It felt pretty awesome. You may wonder why it took a week to learn content covered by a simple presentation on YouTube. My opinion is that the video is not meant for beginners; it’s meant for seasoned coders trying to learn JavaScript.</p>

<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>

<p>After a few weeks of this HackR Diary blogging, I’ve noticed that I’ve missed a few things. Despite my best efforts, these posts are not as comprehensive as I originally imagined. For example, last week, I forgot to talk about learning eventing systems. Overall, I’ve been forgetting to talk about specific aspects of student life like food options, daily mini-presentations, fitness challenges, the “halp system”, volunteering for tech blogging, and so on and so forth…</p>

<p>So much to write about; so little time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Event: Pamela Fox on Backbone]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/hackr-diary-a-visit-from-pamela-fox-re-backbone/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-10-16T07:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/hackr-diary-a-visit-from-pamela-fox-re-backbone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="last-updated">Last updated on Oct 16, 2013 (see strikethrough text).</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/pamelafox">@pamelafox</a> schooling <a href="https://twitter.com/HackReactor">@HackReactor</a> students on <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23backbonejs&amp;src=hash">#backbonejs</a> <a href="http://t.co/1xRuxIEvKl">pic.twitter.com/1xRuxIEvKl</a></p>&mdash; andre (@AndrEvangelestA) <a href="https://twitter.com/AndrEvangelestA/statuses/389949525588062209">October 15, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>Last Monday, the Hack Reactor students were treated to <a href="http://backbone-3ways.appspot.com/">a Backbone presentation</a> by <a href="http://blog.pamelafox.org/">Pamela Fox</a>. It was packed with a ton of insight. I frantically took notes on my smartphone (like a fool), so now I present to you a collection of cool cucumbers.</p>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<h2 id="backbone-nuggets">Backbone Nuggets</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Region management (which you can “outsource” to the likes of <a href="http://chaplinjs.org/">Chaplin</a> or <a href="http://marionettejs.com/s">Marionette</a>) is worth checking out. Apparently, it helps limit the amount of rendering you need to do by allowing you to target specific regions of the web page.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Not all Backbone libraries are created equal! Some provide sweet functionality at the cost of depressing performance losses. The Backbone ecosystem is cool, but not entirely safe. Pamela once removed a library from Coursera’s codebase that was responsible for a <em>full second</em> of page load time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Backbone is so flexible that you might feel like an Backbone expert one day and then feel like a noob the next day when you see someone else’s radically different and compelling usage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Break up your views into more views. Make sibling views and nested views. No single view should be a bajillion lines of code. If you find yourself making long js files in Backbone, it’s time to split things up, my fellow noob.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="general-code-related-nuggets">General Code-Related Nuggets</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Don’t optimize prematurely. Performant code is harder to read. Making code harder to read early on can be annoying. I wonder if Pamela is pro-<a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/hackr-diary-first-impressions/#guard-operator">guard operator</a> or anti-guard operator.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://requirejs.org/">RequireJS</a> kills your foolish usage of global vars. Perhaps I should use it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Single-page web apps can be harder to debug (than multi-page web apps?) because state gets saved across various renders. Errors can be hard to reproduce during the debugging process because there might be many user interactions that need to occur in a particular sequence to cause the error.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ask potential employers about their companies’ testing practices.</strong> How much regression testing do they do? How many tests have they created? More tests means less fear when contributing to the codebase as a fresh employee.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Making <strong>forms</strong> with Backbone (or any MV framework?) is great because forms lend themselves to the model-view-collection paradigm with ease. Forms are collections of questions, which are models, which have their own views. Each question view can draw from a set of views meant to provide a particular format (a view for a question answered by checkboxes, a view for question answered by text fields, a view for question answered by generic menu, etc). This also means Backbone is good for creating <strong>control panels</strong> for admin users (e.g., admin control panel for teacher conducting a Coursera class).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="re-coursera">Re: Coursera</h2>

<p>Pamela used to work for Coursera. She drew from her experiences with that company to provide a lot of context and real-world examples for the arguments she put forth in her presentation.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>To address SEO concerns associated with single-page web apps, Coursera used <strong>Just-in-Time rendering</strong>. Coursera would detect whether or not a visitor was a search/social engine bot crawling the sit. Upon identifying the bot, Coursera servers would respond by firing up a rendered instance of the web app using Selenium. The bot would then be directed to the code produced by the rendering. This prevents the bot from crawling an HTML file that has nothing but <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags pulling in Backbone code. Side note: Google is not cool with the just-in-time technique. Coursera had to use a different technique for Google, but that was not disclosed during Pamela’s talk :(</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><del>It’s not the most organized</del> (nevermind –it’s split into easy-to-understand folders), but you can find a lot of Coursera <a href="https://github.com/coursera/forum-js-snapshot">code on Github</a> (open source, baby!)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When viewing their source code with your browser, you’ll see mostly <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags. There is very little <code>&lt;body&gt;</code> HTML. That’s due to extensive use of Backbone.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="what-i-thought">What I Thought</h1>

<p>Pamela is a fantastic speaker. What I liked most about her talk was the use of real-world examples. As a student, it’s always so informative to hear about life in the wild (so to speak). Seeing as how this was a Hack Reactor event exclusively for students, it’s hard to judge it impartially, but I’m going to go ahead and claim it was awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Week 3: Order in the Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/14/hackr-diary-week-3-backbone/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-10-14T00:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/14/hackr-diary-week-3-backbone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RebootJeff.github.io/images/20131014/logos.png" alt="logos" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">Tech from the previous week: Bower, Backbone, and CoffeeScript</p>

<p>It’s funny how time perception is so easily manipulated. After 3 weeks of immersive education, I forget what day of the week it is. My fellow students also think time is passing by really quickly despite how many hours per day we spend in one (big) room.</p>

<p>Weekends are limited to Sundays due to the 6-days-per-week schedule, so Fridays don’t feel like Fridays (so to speak). However, I should note that Saturdays at Hack Reactor are less intense than other days because the weekly social nights replace the final few hours of the daily classwork with entertainment. Social nights are optional, and plenty of students decide to spend that time working.</p>

<h2 id="more-varied-thoughts-from-week-3">More varied thoughts from week 3</h2>

<ul>
  <li>I’ve stopped using pen + paper. I probably didn’t need to buy notebook for this course, and I’m just not a fan of paper. Hopefully my lack of note-taking won’t bite me later. Hack Reactor provides some good online notes, diagrams, etc, but I’m not sure they’ll be enough when it comes time to study for job interviews. That said, I’m not too worried.</li>
  <li>Gym time is limited. Students get 2-hour lunch breaks every other day, but it takes at least 10 minutes to walk to the gym, a few minutes to change clothes, a few minutes to shower, 5-10 minutes to buy lunch afterwards, etc. Actual workout time is roughly 45-60 minutes max. A lot of us have ended up eating during the post-lunch lecture, so I guess it’s all good.</li>
  <li>Hack Reactor hosts <a href="http://www.meetup.com/hackreactor/">various meetups</a> throughout the week (Coursera study group, general JS meetups, etc). I think that’s a pretty cool way for them to help out the greater dev community.</li>
  <li><strong>Burnout watch:</strong> I still feel pretty excited to go to Hack Reactor 6 days per week, but I definitely look forward to relaxing on Sundays. In <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/06/hackr-diary-week-2/">my previous blog post</a>, I lamented about spending free my limited free time to write substantive blog posts, but now I think they really help me exercise my memory to prevent that “it was all a blur” feeling.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="recap-of-events">Recap of Events</h1>

<h3 id="industry-event-firebase">Industry Event: Firebase</h3>

<p>Sadly, I didn’t attend the <a href="https://www.firebase.com/">Firebase</a> meetup hosted at Hack Reactor HQ. I heard from fellow students that the Firebase tech is pretty sweet. Firebase devs gave a demo that impressed many with promises of data syncing hotness.</p>

<p>Why didn’t I attend the event? My pair programming partner and I decided we couldn’t spare any time for the event because we were more concerned with Backbone. Firebase just happened to come around at a bad time for me.</p>

<h3 id="social-night-movie-theater">Social Night: Movie Theater</h3>

<p>Yesterday, many students went to see <em>Gravity</em> (in 3D IMAX format). It was pretty friggin’ fantastic. Afterwards, some of us went our separate ways, some went back to studying/working, and some went out to partake in beverage consumption.</p>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<p><strong>Quick tip:</strong> I learned a tactic for dealing with low brain energy. When I’m tired of analyzing software architecture decisions or concocting algorithms, I can give myself a productive break by switching to CSS work. Changing gears from program development to applying styles and designing layouts works wonders to give certain parts of my brain a rest while exercising others.</p>

<p>Most Hack Reactor assignments come with some pre-written code, but they often come devoid of any interesting visuals so that you can practice CSS skills.</p>

<h3 id="bower">Bower</h3>

<p>Not much to say here. Students got a very brief lecture about <a href="http://bower.io/">Bower</a>, but it didn’t take much time to convince me to use it. Easily manage libraries/dependencies with a few terminal commands? Nice. <code>bower install</code> = woot!</p>

<h3 id="inner-workings-of-the-web-httpajax-full-stack-overview">Inner workings of the web (HTTP/AJAX, full stack overview)</h3>

<p>Students have yet to write any server-side code, but we’ve dealt with programming small client-side apps that interact with servers. We were taught some AJAX skills and some general HTTP knowledge. One lecture covered the overall system architecture that describes client-server interaction. <strong>There were so. Many. Terms:</strong> local storage, sockets, page requests, asset requests, client vs server MVC, content delivery networks (CDNs), object-relational mapping (ORM) –good times.</p>

<h3 id="backbone">Backbone</h3>

<p>Most of the week 3 assignments involved <a href="http://backbonejs.org/">Backbone</a>, which forced us students to really change the way we think about <em>designing</em> software. Developing with Backbone means organizing code to follow paradigms involving models, views, and collections (not quite MVC –which is “model view <em>controller</em>”).</p>

<p>Before Backbone (a JavaScript framework for providing web apps with structure) our code was a like a stream of consciousness. With Backbone, our code was given order, structure, and rules to follow. It was a tough, but rewarding adjustment. Students were struggling with the process when initially exposed to Backbone. <strong>It’s funny because we were all questioning the effectiveness of Hack Reactor’s curriculum at first, but by the end of the week, most of us feel much more comfy with the framework.</strong></p>

<p>Imagine you could only teach via stream-of-consciousness statements. Content would be expressed, but it would be messy as hell. Now imagine you were forced to teach by writing a well-structured, well-organized textbook. The difference is staggering. Suddenly you need to think about organizing concepts into topics, sequencing topics, connecting topics, etc. Making the leap from using no framework to using Backbone isn’t quite as drastic, but it’s still a tough contrast to get comfortable with in just a few days –even if those days involve ~12 hours of learning.</p>

<h3 id="coffeescript">CoffeeScript</h3>

<p>Before my time at Hack Reactor began, I was open to the idea of learning <a href="http://coffeescript.org/">CoffeeScript</a> (a more expressive, human-readable programming language that compiles into JavaScript, allowing you to write JavaScript with a very different syntax) because it looked friendly in the same way Ruby looks friendly. After a couple of weeks of writing lots of JavaScript code, I was far less open-minded about spending time learning a drastically different syntax. Imagine being told you were going to take a break from learning intermediate Spanish so you could learn beginner Portugese. You’d say, “No thank you, crazy person.” </p>

<p>After finishing the CoffeeScript sprint, I remain somewhat ambivalent. I don’t love it, but I don’t hate it. <strong>The whole experience taught me that learning new syntax isn’t so bad.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Week 2: Now Exiting My Comfort Zone]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/06/hackr-diary-week-2/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-10-06T22:17:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/06/hackr-diary-week-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="last-updated">Last updated on Oct 13, 2013 to fix a typo and embedded a tweet.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Awesome of the <a href="https://twitter.com/Airbnb">@Airbnb</a> team to visit <a href="https://twitter.com/HackReactor">@HackReactor</a>. Picture of them talking about their tech stack. <a href="http://t.co/AYVDYA3JaT">pic.twitter.com/AYVDYA3JaT</a></p>&mdash; Ben Martin (@HealthfulHacker) <a href="https://twitter.com/HealthfulHacker/statuses/385258134677106689">October 2, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>I don’t know if <a href="blog/2013/09/29/hackr-diary-thoughts-about-week-number-1/">my summary of week #1</a> made it clear or not, but although my first six days at Hack Reactor were tough, I didn’t exactly struggle with any of the material. This is probably because the pre-course work was <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/22/hackr-diary-pre-course-anticipation/">incredibly difficult</a>, thereby infusing me with helpful knowledge while also shaping my expectations.</p>

<p>Well guess what? Week 1 was an anomaly. It was a week filled with more lectures and less hands-on programming. I knew this ahead of time, but week 2 still caught me off guard. There was quite a bit more learning with minimal guidance. Also, the joys/stresses of pair programming are turned up a few notches as a result of the additional programming time created by reducing the amount of lecture time.</p>

<p>Consequently, I’ve been feeling more tired in general. Forgive me, but spending my free time to write this blog is beginning to look less and less appealing.</p>

<p>I joined a nearby gym (aside: I just remembered that I need to notify Hack Reactor to get my $50 reimbursement from them!) so my energy levels should increase in a week or two. Every other lunch break is two hours long instead of just one hour long. The extra time is meant to encourage students to go exercise.</p>

<p>I want to write more about student life at Hack Reactor, but I think I’ll just spread out the details in my <a href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/hackr-diary/">HackR Diary</a> series rather than providing every bit of info in a single, giant blog post. So for now, I cover gym time, toy problems, and tapouts. In the future, I’ll discuss the workstations, help system, student-staff interaction, food, and more.</p>

<h1 id="week-in-review">Week in Review</h1>

<h4 id="toy-problems">Toy Problems</h4>

<p>This week, my cohort, the junior students, started solving (almost) daily toy problems, which are small coding challenges designed to get us used to the type of timed problems that will be thrown our way at tech interviews. We have to complete these problems individually. We have 30-60 minutes to think of a solution, code the solution, and submit pull requests to have an automated tester give us feedback that we can use to help fix our solutions as necessary.</p>

<h4 id="tapouts">Tapouts</h4>

<p>This week, us juniors also started attending weekly(?) tapouts. Tapouts are like small group therapy sessions where five students voice their opinions of Hack Reactor to an alumnus. She will send anonimized feedback up the chain while also providing us with advice for any struggles we care to talk about. </p>

<h4 id="special-event-airbnb-presentation">Special Event: AirBnB Presentation</h4>

<p>Lead devs from <a href="https://twitter.com/Airbnb">AirBnB</a> presented a ton of info about their tech stack, their work environment, <a href="http://nerds.airbnb.com/weve-open-sourced-rendr-run-your-backbonejs-a/">their open source project</a>, dev career advice, startup advice, etc. There was a post-presentation panel for answering several questions. Then there was a post-panel meet-and-greet session. It was a truly fantastic event.</p>

<h4 id="saturday-social-night">Saturday Social Night</h4>

<p>I skipped last Saturday’s social night to go to a close friend’s birthday celebration(s). Week 2’s theme for social night was board/card games.</p>

<h1 id="what-i-learned--what-i-thought">What I Learned + What I Thought</h1>

<h4 id="inheritancesubclassing-in-javascript">Inheritance/Subclassing in JavaScript</h4>

<p>The subclassing sprint was a bit frustrating at first. It took me awhile to grasp the keyword <code>this</code> because of JavaScript’s tendency to pass functions around as parameters to other functions.</p>

<p>Upon wrapping one’s brain around <code>this</code> (and the <code>.call()</code>/<code>.apply()</code> methods), there was a lot of fun to be had with the assignment that Hack Reactor gave the students. This was the first assignment involving a visual facet, and the student body reacted accordingly (with creativity galore).</p>

<h4 id="algorithms">Algorithms</h4>

<p>The algorithms sprint was a fantastic challenge, but there was no specific set of knowledge to learn. It felt like the main goal of the sprint was to get students’ minds thinking in more computer-oriented ways. We were taught some basics about time complexity, but we didn’t go into much depth about Big-O notation. We briefly described actions (e.g., deleting data from an array) and algorithms (e.g., solutions to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eight_queens_puzzle#Related_problems">n-queens puzzle</a>) as constant, linear, quadratic, polynomial, and exponential (as opposed to discussing the nuances of O(c), O(n), O(n^2), O(n^c), O(c^n), etc).</p>

<p>The main takeaway was that we should worry more about macro optimizations (storing data in variables in a way that allows for constant-time lookup) rather than micro optimizations (improving a <code>for</code> loop so then it loops fewer times). <strong>Micro optimizations are good, but they aren’t very valuable when you’re just creating prototypes, minimum viable products, etc.</strong></p>

<p>I’m somewhat disappointed that we weren’t taught specific algorithms such as quicksort, binary search, etc. I’m under the assumption that all software developers need to know the “greatest hits” of algorithms. Although, I’m also under the assumption that such knowledge is more useful in tech interviews than in day-to-day coding.</p>

<h4 id="layoutpositioning-htmlcss">Layout/Positioning (HTML/CSS)</h4>

<p>I taught myself a decent amount of HTML/CSS before my cohort’s start date, so I was very comfortable with the layout assignment, but it wasn’t easy. There are still plenty of times when proper CSS positioning eludes me. That said, this topic doesn’t provide an intellectual challenge.</p>

<p>The difficulty lies in getting the syntax just right and understanding hierarchy. Some students didn’t learn much HTML/CSS before joining Hack Reactor, and so they had a lot to learn (box model, DOM hierarchy, CSS selectors, etc.) in a very short amount of time.</p>

<p><strong>If you’re thinking of joining Hack Reactor as a student, I highly recommend you teach yourself HTML/CSS</strong> ahead of time. HTML/CSS isn’t tough to learn on your own, but it can be time-consuming even if you’ve got pros helping you. You may as well prepare yourself so then you can spend less time at Hack Reactor worrying about HTML/CSS and more time worrying about other technologies and concepts.</p>

<h4 id="d3-library">D3 (library)</h4>

<p><a href="http://d3js.org/">D3.js</a> is a JavaScript library for creating data-driven visuals inside HTML documents. I thought jQuery was cool, but now I think D3 takes the cake. It’s much harder to learn D3, but there is tremendous power to be had from familiarizing yourself with it.</p>

<p>That said, the D3 assignment left me mentally tired as hell. Like jQuery, you can easily select DOM elements, but the rest of the D3 syntax isn’t so straightforward, and the general concepts for using D3 properly will feel rather foreign at first. I hope to spend more time on my own to master D3 …when I’m not so damn tired. The key is to understand the <a href="http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/3808218">general update pattern</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Thoughts about Week #1]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/29/hackr-diary-thoughts-about-week-number-1/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-09-29T14:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/29/hackr-diary-thoughts-about-week-number-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="last-updated">Last updated on Oct 1, 2013 (minor edits).</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Good way to start week 2 at <a href="https://twitter.com/HackReactor">@HackReactor</a> <a href="http://t.co/6pB80gQKCO">pic.twitter.com/6pB80gQKCO</a></p>&mdash; Jeff Lee (@RebootJeff) <a href="https://twitter.com/RebootJeff/statuses/384728991359176704">September 30, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>This post is a bit late, but it can be hard to find time to write up a thorough blog post when I’m studying at Hack Reactor for 70-80 hours/week. During my free time, it’s tempting to just play <a href="http://www.playhawken.com">Hawken</a> or catch up on YouTube (yes, I subscribe to some damn good channels).</p>

<p>Quick correction: In <a href="">my previous HackR Diary entry</a>, I said that the staff gets a 1-week vacation every 7 weeks (6 weeks of work followed by a 1-week break). This isn’t entirely true. The interim week can be used as vacation, but staff also use it to make changes to Hack Reactor. For example, the most recent interim week was used by staff to rearrange the lecture room, which involved installing a new projector screen.</p>

<h1 id="week-in-review">Week in Review</h1>

<p>I wake up everyday Mon-Sat at 7:30am. I should really wake up earlier so then I can arrive before 8:50am. I rely on the BART (subway) to get to/from Hack Reactor. I make my subway rides more enjoyable by saving YouTube videos as .mp4 files to my phone. I generally watch documentaries on cosmology and nature featuring British narrators. The accent is key. If you’re interested in such documentaries, <strong>check out <a href="http://science-documentaries.com/">this link</a> and <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ag0U65NkxrI&amp;feature=share&amp;list=PL300BF5A42D3C21C4">this link</a></strong>.</p>

<p>Ok enough of that. You came here to read about the intersection of start-up life and student life, not BBC on YouTube. Here’s a quick recap of what I was up to last week:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Learning:</strong> 2 “standard” sprints + 1 longer sprint</li>
  <li><strong>Reflection:</strong> Provided feedback on what students did and didn’t like about week 1.</li>
  <li><strong>Week 0 self-assessment:</strong> An ungraded quiz to force you to ask yourself how confident you are about what was taught in the pre-course work.</li>
  <li><strong>Code Review by seniors:</strong> The “upperclassmen” took a look at our data structures solutions.</li>
  <li><strong>Social Night:</strong> Visited <em>House of Air</em>, a sweet trampoline gym.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Sprint #1:</strong> Recursion</li>
  <li><strong>Sprint #2:</strong> Mini-clone of Underscore.js</li>
  <li><strong>Extra #1:</strong> Advice for Success
    <ul>
      <li>Hack Reactor’s role in students’ success</li>
      <li>Students’ role in our own success</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Extra #2:</strong> Debugging
    <ul>
      <li><code>debugger;</code> statement</li>
      <li>Sources tab in Google Chrome dev tools</li>
      <li>Call Stack in Sources tab</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Sprint #3:</strong> Instantiating Data Structures with various Class Patterns
    <ul>
      <li>Class Patterns
        <ul>
          <li>Functional (with and without shared methods)</li>
          <li>Prototypal</li>
          <li>Pseudoclassical</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Data Structures
        <ul>
          <li>Stacks</li>
          <li>Queues</li>
          <li>Linked Lists</li>
          <li>Trees</li>
          <li>Sets</li>
          <li>Hash Tables</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="what-i-thought">What I Thought</h1>

<h2 id="lectures">Lectures</h2>

<p><strong>Week 1 is very different from most weeks</strong> due to the amount of lengthy lectures we have to sit through, but ya know what? I really liked the lectures. The main instructor for week 1 is Marcus, and he’s pretty great at teaching. Students constantly ask questions during lecture so it feels much more interactive and much less like being force-fed information.</p>

<p>I like that lectures involve plenty of analogies, live coding examples, industry best practices, and “every interviewer will ask you about this” moments. You’d think students would get pretty tired of all the lectures, but they’re too good to be off-putting. Also, 5+ hours of lectures per day isn’t a lot when you consider we’re spending 12+ hours per day at the school.</p>

<h2 id="paired-programming">Paired Programming</h2>

<p>I generally like the idea of paired programming so long as you have a good dynamic with your partner. That said, it can be <em>really</em> tiring because you’re constantly talking as you and your partner are coding. Not only are you exhausting your brain’s cognitive abilities by working on programming challenges, but you’re also exercising verbal comm skills and listening skills. It can be tough to listen to your partner explain his/her solution when you feel like you’re on the brink of working out your own awesome solution in your head.</p>

<h2 id="the-school">The School</h2>

<p>Hack Reactor is a fantastic environment, and I know every student of every bootcamp says this, but it’s just so amazing to be in a school where the students and teachers are all so pumped to be there. On top of that, the students are open-minded without being naive. Basically, <strong>Hack Reactor is filled with the positive vibes that should make every college wildly jealous.</strong></p>

<p>It’s also worth noting that Hack Reactor is transparent. They’re a small company, and their small size allows them to build a tighter community of teachers, students, and alumni. I love that Hack Reactor staff is very honest and genuine. When cynics look at the relatively expensive tuition, it’s tempting for them to say HackR is “in it for the money,” but check out a lecture or listen to them explain their intentions and you won’t hear a sales pitch. You’ll hear earnest intentions to educate the next generation of developers using next-generation methods.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/hackr-diary-first-impressions/"/>
    <author>
      <name><![CDATA[@RebootJeff]]></name>
      
    </author>
    <updated>2013-09-25T21:23:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/hackr-diary-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="last-updated">Last updated on Sep 28, 2013 to edit section on guard operator.</p>

<p>It’s the end of day #3. I don’t have much time to write, so this blog post is a smattering of thoughts from a fresh Hack Reactor student.</p>

<h1 id="initial-observations">Initial Observations</h1>

<h2 id="recap">Recap</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Day 1 and 2 are just review days covering topics and challenges covered by the pre-course work. Day 1 covered ettiquette, expectations, and recursion. Day 2 covered passing functions, a lot of JS fundamentals, and awesome advice for being successful (e.g., we talked about impostor syndrome, Hack Reactor’s motivations, some job-hunting advice, etc).</li>
  <li>Day 3 covered paired programming, object-oriented programming (OOP), and classes (e.g., functional instantiation vs. prototypal instantiation vs. psuedoclassical instantiation).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="logistics">Logistics</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Week 1 is full of lectures. Each day is about 50% lectures, 50% coding.</li>
  <li>The first 6 weeks will have plenty of lectures and structured challenges. Then there is an interim week where you work on a project from home, which gives you the flexibility to travel, but the Hack Reactor staff will be offline (they basically get a 1-week vacation every 7 weeks). After the interim week is more time for your individual project, time for a group project, and time for job prep.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="nuances">Nuances</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Lunch breaks and dinner breaks are often cut short due to lectures running long.</li>
  <li>Lectures run long due to people asking questions.</li>
  <li>All teachers advocate for students to ask questions. At Hack Reactor, the students ask a TON of questions because the class atmosphere is very comfortable.</li>
  <li>The students are really nice. Everyone’s excited to meet new people (even the quiet ones are clearly motivated to be social).</li>
  <li>I’ve heard stories of students of other bootcamps going out at night to hang out and have fun. I could be wrong, but so far it seems like there’s no time/energy left for going out at night.</li>
  <li>That said, students don’t stay here that late (so far). A lot of us leave by 9pm. I thought it’d be common to leave no earlier than 10pm, but there aren’t even that many students from the senior cohort by the time the clock strikes 9:20pm (which is the latest I’ve stayed). I have a feeling this will change in a few weeks (beause that will be crunch time for the senior cohort).</li>
  <li>Nothing’s perfect. Some equipment is broken, some chairs are shitty, some online resources are buggy, etc. None of these issues have been big issues.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="nuggets-of-knowledge">Nuggets of Knowledge</h1>

<p>I’ve picked up a lot of cool (and oftentimes valuable) advice/facts in just 3 days.</p>

<h2 id="life-nuggets">Life Nuggets</h2>

<h3 id="re-education">Re: <strong>Education</strong></h3>

<p>Passive learning is deceptively similar to true understanding. When you just observe a correct solution, it can give you the illusion that you learned more than you really did. For example, you might watch someone code up a good solution. When you walk away, you’ll think you understand everything necessary to solve the problem, but all you learned was some code without its meaning.</p>

<h3 id="re-starting-a-new-tech-career">Re: <strong>Starting a new tech career</strong></h3>

<p>Everyone thinks starting a new tech career with a tiny startup is really exciting. That might be true, but people tend to forget an important caveat: less structure could lead to a less efficient roadmap to individual success.</p>

<p>In less formal terms, you might work for a tiny startup on something you truly care about, but the startup could easily be too small or too young to provide an environment with superiors/peers that can help you develop your programming skills (or any job-related skills).</p>

<h2 id="javascript-nuggets">JavaScript Nuggets</h2>

<h3 id="guard-operator">Guard operator</h3>

<p>Marcus, the primary instructor, warned us that some devs dislike the guard operator, but it’s really concise (which is cool to him). The guard operator is a logical-AND or logical-OR that “guards” a small bit of code the same way an <code>if</code> statement would guard it. For example:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">if</span>(goodStudent === <span class="predefined-constant">true</span>){
    candy++;
}

<span class="comment">// The above code could be refactored into the following:</span>
goodStudent &amp;&amp; candy++;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>The following is a more practical example:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="comment">// Let's say you want to only call a function with an array if the array is NOT undefined (i.e., you want to guard against a scenario where you pass an undefined argument to a function).</span>
arg &amp;&amp; myFunction(arg);
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>You can also use a logical-OR in a guard-like fashion. This is sometimes called the <strong>default operator</strong> rather than a guard operator.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="comment">// if no name was passed into the function, just give the name variable a default value of 'friend'</span>

<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">sayHello</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(name){
  <span class="keyword">if</span>(name === <span class="predefined-constant">undefined</span>){
    name = <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">friend</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>;
  }
  console.log(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">Hello, </span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span> + name + <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">!</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);
}

<span class="comment">// the function above could be refactored to use the OR-guard as follows:</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">sayHello</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(name){
  name = name || <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">friend</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>;
  console.log(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">Hello, </span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span> + name + <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">!</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);
}
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
