<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JavaScript | RebootJeff.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-25T21:21:17-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/hackr-diary-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T21:23:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/hackr-diary-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s the end of day #3. I don’t have much time to write, so this blog post is a smattering of thoughts from a fresh Hack Reactor student.</p>

<h1 id="initial-observations">Initial Observations</h1>

<h2 id="recap">Recap</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Day 1 and 2 are just review days covering topics and challenges covered by the pre-course work. Day 1 covered ettiquette, expectations, and recursion. Day 2 covered passing functions, a lot of JS fundamentals, and awesome advice for being successful (e.g., we talked about impostor syndrome, Hack Reactor’s motivations, some job-hunting advice, etc).</li>
  <li>Day 3 covered paired programming, object-oriented programming (OOP), and classes (e.g., functional instantiation vs. prototypal instantiation vs. psuedoclassical instantiation).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="logistics">Logistics</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Week 1 is full of lectures. Each day is about 50% lectures, 50% coding.</li>
  <li>The first 6 weeks will have plenty of lectures and structured challenges. Then there is an interim week where you work on a project from home, which gives you the flexibility to travel, but the Hack Reactor staff will be offline (they basically get a 1-week vacation every 7 weeks). After the interim week is more time for your individual project, time for a group project, and time for job prep.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="nuances">Nuances</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Lunch breaks and dinner breaks are often cut short due to lectures running long.</li>
  <li>Lectures run long due to people asking questions.</li>
  <li>All teachers advocate for students to ask questions. At Hack Reactor, the students ask a TON of questions because the class atmosphere is very comfortable.</li>
  <li>The students are really nice. Everyone’s excited to meet new people (even the quiet ones are clearly motivated to be social).</li>
  <li>I’ve heard stories of students of other bootcamps going out at night to hang out and have fun. I could be wrong, but so far it seems like there’s no time/energy left for going out at night.</li>
  <li>That said, students don’t stay here that late (so far). A lot of us leave by 9pm. I thought it’d be common to leave no earlier than 10pm, but there aren’t even that many students from the senior cohort by the time the clock strikes 9:20pm (which is the latest I’ve stayed). I have a feeling this will change in a few weeks (beause that will be crunch time for the senior cohort).</li>
  <li>Nothing’s perfect. Some equipment is broken, some chairs are shitty, some online resources are buggy, etc. None of these issues have been big issues.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="nuggets-of-knowledge">Nuggets of Knowledge</h1>

<p>I’ve picked up a lot of cool (and oftentimes valuable) advice/facts in just 3 days.</p>

<h2 id="life-nuggets">Life Nuggets</h2>

<h3 id="re-education">Re: <strong>Education</strong></h3>

<p>Passive learning is deceptively similar to true understanding. When you just observe a correct solution, it can give you the illusion that you learned more than you really did. For example, you might watch someone code up a good solution. When you walk away, you’ll think you understand everything necessary to solve the problem, but all you learned was some code without its meaning.</p>

<h3 id="re-starting-a-new-tech-career">Re: <strong>Starting a new tech career</strong></h3>

<p>Everyone thinks starting a new tech career with a tiny startup is really exciting. That might be true, but people tend to forget an important caveat: less structure could lead to a less efficient roadmap to individual success.</p>

<p>In less formal terms, you might work for a tiny startup on something you truly care about, but the startup could easily be too small or too young to provide an environment with superiors/peers that can help you develop your programming skills (or any job-related skills).</p>

<h2 id="javascript-nuggets">JavaScript Nuggets</h2>

<h3 id="guard-operator">Guard operator</h3>

<p>Marcus, the primary instructor, warned us that some devs dislike the guard operator, but it’s really concise (which is cool to him). The guard operator is a logical-AND that “guards” a small bit of code the same way an <code>if</code> statement would guard it. For example:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">if</span>(goodStudent === <span class="predefined-constant">true</span>){
    candy++;
}

<span class="comment">// The above code could be refactored into the following:</span>
goodStudent &amp;&amp; candy++;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>The following is a more practical example:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="comment">// Let's say you want to only call a function with an array if the array is NOT undefined (i.e., you want to guard against a scenario where you pass an undefined argument to a function).</span>
arg &amp;&amp; myFunction(arg);
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
