<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JavaScript | RebootJeff.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-15T21:18:07-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] Event: Pamela Fox on Backbone]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/hackr-diary-a-visit-from-pamela-fox-re-backbone/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-16T20:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/hackr-diary-a-visit-from-pamela-fox-re-backbone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/pamelafox">@pamelafox</a> schooling <a href="https://twitter.com/HackReactor">@HackReactor</a> students on <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23backbonejs&amp;src=hash">#backbonejs</a> <a href="http://t.co/1xRuxIEvKl">pic.twitter.com/1xRuxIEvKl</a></p>&mdash; andre (@AndrEvangelestA) <a href="https://twitter.com/AndrEvangelestA/statuses/389949525588062209">October 15, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>Last Monday, the Hack Reactor students were treated to <a href="http://backbone-3ways.appspot.com/">a Backbone presentation</a> by <a href="http://blog.pamelafox.org/">Pamela Fox</a>. It was packed with a ton of insight. I frantically took notes on my smartphone (like a fool), so now I present to you a collection of cool cucumbers.</p>

<h1 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h1>

<h2 id="backbone-nuggets">Backbone Nuggets</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Region management (which you can “outsource” to the likes of <a href="http://chaplinjs.org/">Chaplin</a> or <a href="http://marionettejs.com/s">Marionette</a>) is worth checking out. Apparently, they help you limit the amount of rendering you need to do by allowing you to target specific regions of the web page.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Not all Backbone libraries are created equal! Some provide sweet functionality at the cost of depressing performance losses. The Backbone ecosystem is cool, but not entirely safe. Pamela once removed a library from Coursera’s codebase that was responsible for a <em>full second</em> of page load time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Backbone is so flexible that you might feel like an Backbone expert one day and then feel like a noob the next day when you see someone else’s radically different and compelling usage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Break up your views into more views. Make sibling views and nested views. No single view should be a bajillion lines of code. If you find yourself making long js files in Backbone, it’s time to split things up, my fellow noob.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="general-code-related-nuggets">General Code-Related Nuggets</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Don’t optimize prematurely. Performant code is harder to read. Making code harder to read early on can be annoying.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://requirejs.org/">RequireJS</a> kills your foolish usage of global vars. Perhaps I should use it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Single-page web apps can be harder to debug (than multi-page web apps?) because state gets saved across various renders. Errors can be hard to reproduce during the debugging process because there might be many user interactions that need to occur in a particular sequence to cause the error.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ask potential employers about their companies’ testing practices.</strong> How much regression testing do they do? How many tests have they created? More tests means less fear when contributing to the codebase as a fresh employee.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Making <strong>forms</strong> with Backbone (or any MV framework?) is great because forms lend themselves to the model-view-collection paradigm with ease. Forms are collections of questions, which are models, which have their own views. Each question view can draw from a set of views meant to provide a particular format (a view for a question answered by checkboxes, a view for question answered by text fields, a view for question answered by generic menu, etc). This also means Backbone is good for creating <strong>control panels</strong> for admin users (e.g., admin control panel for teacher conducting a Coursera class).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="re-coursera">Re: Coursera</h2>

<p>Pamela used to work for Coursera. She drew from her experiences with that company to provide a lot of context and real-world examples for the arguments she put forth in her presentation.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>To address SEO concerns associated with single-page web apps, Coursera used Just-in-Time rendering. Coursera would detect whether or not a visitor was a search/social engine bot crawling the sit. Upon identifying the bot, Coursera servers would respond by firing up a rendered instance of the web app using Selenium. The bot would then be directed to the code produced by the rendering. This prevents the bot from crawling an HTML file that has nothing but <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags pulling in Backbone code. Side note: Google is not cool with the just-in-time technique. Coursera had to use a different technique for Google, but that was not disclosed during Pamela’s talk :(</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It’s not the most organized (in my opinion), but you can find a lot of Coursera code on Github here: https://github.com/coursera/forum-js-snapshot (open source, baby!)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When viewing their source code with your browser, you’ll see mostly <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags. There is very little <code>&lt;body&gt;</code> HTML. That’s due to extensive use of Backbone.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="what-i-thought">What I Thought</h1>

<p>Pamela is a fantastic speaker. What I liked most about her talk was the use of real-world examples. As a student, it’s always so informative to hear about life in the wild (so to speak). Seeing as how this was a Hack Reactor event exclusively for students, it’s hard to judge it impartially, but I’m going to go ahead and claim it was awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[HackR Diary] First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/hackr-diary-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T21:23:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/hackr-diary-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="last-updated">Last updated on Sep 28, 2013 to edit section on guard operator.</p>

<p>It’s the end of day #3. I don’t have much time to write, so this blog post is a smattering of thoughts from a fresh Hack Reactor student.</p>

<h1 id="initial-observations">Initial Observations</h1>

<h2 id="recap">Recap</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Day 1 and 2 are just review days covering topics and challenges covered by the pre-course work. Day 1 covered ettiquette, expectations, and recursion. Day 2 covered passing functions, a lot of JS fundamentals, and awesome advice for being successful (e.g., we talked about impostor syndrome, Hack Reactor’s motivations, some job-hunting advice, etc).</li>
  <li>Day 3 covered paired programming, object-oriented programming (OOP), and classes (e.g., functional instantiation vs. prototypal instantiation vs. psuedoclassical instantiation).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="logistics">Logistics</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Week 1 is full of lectures. Each day is about 50% lectures, 50% coding.</li>
  <li>The first 6 weeks will have plenty of lectures and structured challenges. Then there is an interim week where you work on a project from home, which gives you the flexibility to travel, but the Hack Reactor staff will be offline (they basically get a 1-week vacation every 7 weeks). After the interim week is more time for your individual project, time for a group project, and time for job prep.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="nuances">Nuances</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Lunch breaks and dinner breaks are often cut short due to lectures running long.</li>
  <li>Lectures run long due to people asking questions.</li>
  <li>All teachers advocate for students to ask questions. At Hack Reactor, the students ask a TON of questions because the class atmosphere is very comfortable.</li>
  <li>The students are really nice. Everyone’s excited to meet new people (even the quiet ones are clearly motivated to be social).</li>
  <li>I’ve heard stories of students of other bootcamps going out at night to hang out and have fun. I could be wrong, but so far it seems like there’s no time/energy left for going out at night.</li>
  <li>That said, students don’t stay here that late (so far). A lot of us leave by 9pm. I thought it’d be common to leave no earlier than 10pm, but there aren’t even that many students from the senior cohort by the time the clock strikes 9:20pm (which is the latest I’ve stayed). I have a feeling this will change in a few weeks (beause that will be crunch time for the senior cohort).</li>
  <li>Nothing’s perfect. Some equipment is broken, some chairs are shitty, some online resources are buggy, etc. None of these issues have been big issues.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="nuggets-of-knowledge">Nuggets of Knowledge</h1>

<p>I’ve picked up a lot of cool (and oftentimes valuable) advice/facts in just 3 days.</p>

<h2 id="life-nuggets">Life Nuggets</h2>

<h3 id="re-education">Re: <strong>Education</strong></h3>

<p>Passive learning is deceptively similar to true understanding. When you just observe a correct solution, it can give you the illusion that you learned more than you really did. For example, you might watch someone code up a good solution. When you walk away, you’ll think you understand everything necessary to solve the problem, but all you learned was some code without its meaning.</p>

<h3 id="re-starting-a-new-tech-career">Re: <strong>Starting a new tech career</strong></h3>

<p>Everyone thinks starting a new tech career with a tiny startup is really exciting. That might be true, but people tend to forget an important caveat: less structure could lead to a less efficient roadmap to individual success.</p>

<p>In less formal terms, you might work for a tiny startup on something you truly care about, but the startup could easily be too small or too young to provide an environment with superiors/peers that can help you develop your programming skills (or any job-related skills).</p>

<h2 id="javascript-nuggets">JavaScript Nuggets</h2>

<h3 id="guard-operator">Guard operator</h3>

<p>Marcus, the primary instructor, warned us that some devs dislike the guard operator, but it’s really concise (which is cool to him). The guard operator is a logical-AND or logical-OR that “guards” a small bit of code the same way an <code>if</code> statement would guard it. For example:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">if</span>(goodStudent === <span class="predefined-constant">true</span>){
    candy++;
}

<span class="comment">// The above code could be refactored into the following:</span>
goodStudent &amp;&amp; candy++;
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>The following is a more practical example:</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="comment">// Let's say you want to only call a function with an array if the array is NOT undefined (i.e., you want to guard against a scenario where you pass an undefined argument to a function).</span>
arg &amp;&amp; myFunction(arg);
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>You can also use a logical-OR in a guard-like fashion. This is sometimes called the <strong>default operator</strong> rather than a guard operator.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="comment">// if no name was passed into the function, just give the name variable a default value of 'friend'</span>

<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">sayHello</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(name){
  <span class="keyword">if</span>(name === <span class="predefined-constant">undefined</span>){
    name = <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">friend</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>;
  }
  console.log(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">Hello, </span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span> + name + <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">!</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);
}

<span class="comment">// the function above could be refactored to use the OR-guard as follows:</span>
<span class="keyword">var</span> <span class="function">sayHello</span> = <span class="keyword">function</span>(name){
  name = name || <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">friend</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>;
  console.log(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">Hello, </span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span> + name + <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">!</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>);
}
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
