<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learn to code | RebootJeff.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/learn-to-code/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-16T23:12:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Start AND Continue Learning JavaScript and Web Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/11/23/how-to-learn-javascript-and-web-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-23T21:37:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2014/11/23/how-to-learn-javascript-and-web-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/20141123/IMG_20141116_135049sp.jpg" alt="Teaching my JS Fundamentals workshop" /></p>

<p class="my-caption">Me teaching a JavaScript workshop for beginners</p>

<p class="last-updated">Last update on Nov 30, 2014 to add a great link to the "Compilations" section.</p>

<ol>
  <li>A couple of weeks ago, a friend asked me for advice on giving advice to beginners.</li>
  <li>One week ago, I taught a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/hackreactor/events/217841372/">class on JavaScript</a> for beginners (or <em>advanced</em> beginners –as I like to say).</li>
  <li>A few days ago, I recently found a <a href="https://www.quora.com/Should-I-purchase-a-Code-School-subscription-to-prepare-for-the-Hack-Reactor-interview">Quora question about getting better at JS</a>.</li>
</ol>

<p>These three moments have had my brain wondering about how to point coding newbies in the right direction. After some Googling and recalling my own past, I’ve gathered some links that will hopefully help beginners and maybe even intermediate folks. However, I should warn you that I haven’t tried out all the various services for myself.</p>

<h2 id="the-basics">The Basics</h2>

<p><a href="http://imgur.com/gallery/BL6Vs">This Imgur post</a> lists 6 sites that provide tutorials for getting started in coding. I’ve personally used Code School and Codecademy. They’re great, but after awhile, you’ll want to explore other options. They are not sufficient by themselves.</p>

<h2 id="compilations">Compilations</h2>

<p>These sites gather tutorials and various resources into one place. Most of these also give some guidance or roadmap to help beginners prioritize what to learn:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://programming-motherfucker.com/become.html">Programming, Motherf…</a>: Categorized links for various languages.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bento.io/">Bento</a>: Links organized into manageable sections.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.whatsnext.info/#/javascript">What’s Next</a>: Links grouped by topic and difficulty.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.theodinproject.com/courses">The Odin Project</a>: Open-source web dev curriculum.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.jstherightway.org/">JavaScript The Right Way</a>: Links covering the entire JS ecosystem (basics, patterns, testing, frameworks, news/podcasts/feeds).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-fundamentals-of-js">The Fundamentals of JS</h2>

<p>If you’re specifically trying to learn the quirks of JavaScript, then <a href="http://www.meetup.com/hackreactor/events/217841372/">classes like the one I teach</a> are perfect for you. If you’re not near San Francisco, you can try <a href="https://frontendmasters.com/workshops/js-fundamentals-to-functional/">online classes</a> taught by the one who helped me become a teacher (<a href="https://twitter.com/biancagando">@BiancaGando</a>).</p>

<p>But these aren’t free. Ya know what is free? This great gathering of words describing vital JS concepts: <a href="http://javascriptissexy.com/16-javascript-concepts-you-must-know-well/">16 JavaScript Concepts JavaScript Professionals Must Know Well</a></p>

<h2 id="the-community">The Community</h2>

<p>San Francisco is my neck of the woods. If you’re lucky enough to be around here, then you should take advantage of the stellar community. There are lots of free meetups/events that can help you learn. If you’re not in the area, check Meetup.com for groups that provide similar events.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/tinderbox/events/212435202/">Tinderbox</a>: They often host “hack nights”, which might sound intimidating, but they’re very open-ended so you could show up and just ask for help learning a particular subject.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/SFRails/events/199733902/">SF Rails</a>: Much like Tinderbox, the SF Rails group hosts open-ended “protonight” events. The group might focus on Ruby on Rails, but you’re likely to find people who can help with any beginner or intermediate level coding topic.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’re female, you might want to search for organizations that provide free support for women. Some examples:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.womenwhocode.com/">Women Who Code</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.girldevelopit.com/">Girl Develop It</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://railsbridge.org/">Railsbridge</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/tevgende">Aysegul Office Hours</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Back in the day, I used <a href="http://curriculum.railsbridge.org/frontend/frontend">a free, online curriculum</a> created by Railsbridge to learn some web dev skills.</p>

<p>A Hack Reactor alum recently launched a free service called Hackvard. It helps people quickly find nearby programmers who want to meet up. After a few weeks (or days?), it was renamed to <a href="http://www.codaround.com/">Codaround</a>. One of the co-founders contacted me and mentioned that Codaround might be changed to focus on helping match mentors/teachers with students/beginners. I don’t know any details, but it’s worth keeping an eye on this.</p>

<h2 id="games">Games</h2>

<p>Want to play while you program? Here are some sites that turn learning to code into a game:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.checkio.org/">CheckIO</a>: When I <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2013/09/02/mini-review-of-checkio/">tried them out</a>, I wasn’t impressed by their attempt to cover coding challenges in a layer of gamification. A CheckIO employee reached out to me and told me things have changed a lot. I haven’t verified his claims, but their user base was pretty large last time I checked, and their blog is very active, so they’re alive and kicking.</li>
  <li><a href="http://codecombat.com/">Code Combat</a>: I played with this a couple months ago. It was fun, but a tad buggy. I like the idea of writing code to control your character.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.screeps.com/">Screeps</a>: This looks quite promising. You write code to control small armies.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-else">What else?</h2>

<p>Let me know in the comments (or via Twitter) if you know of any other solid resources that help people learn JavaScript and other programming skills.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mini-Review of CheckiO]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/02/mini-review-of-checkio/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-02T13:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/02/mini-review-of-checkio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="overview">Overview</h1>

<p><a href="http://www.checkio.org/">CheckiO</a> is a website that aims to teach programming by providing an online gaming world with some social features heavily emphasized. CheckiO is meant for beginners and experts alike, but all coding challenges must be completed in Python.</p>

<p>The creators have quite a bit of hype behind them. They have received hundreds of thousands of dollars in funding. They have cultivated a thriving community of users. So yeah, my interest was piqued.</p>

<iframe width="300" height="169" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/kWoW6RgH04g" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Side note: The site doesn’t seem to use secure HTTPS. It lets you log in with your other social media and developer community accounts (Facebook, Twitter, WordPress, GitHub, Stack Exchange, etc) so does that mean it’s safer to log in with a Twitter account rather than with a native CheckiO account?</p>

<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>

<p>I did not play with CheckiO for more than a few hours, so that’s why I call this blog post a mini-review.</p>

<p>I think giving it a couple of hours is enough to pass judgement considering that most users will probably give up or continue based on their initial 10 minutes on the site. But my point is that it’s possible that CheckiO is a much deeper, richer website if you’re patient enough to explore it.</p>

<h1 id="what-i-thought">What I Thought</h1>

<p>It looks like the CheckiO community is quite strong, but the site is designed to attract users with a visual wow factor that is misleading. The visuals don’t really tie into the actual coding experience very well. It reminds me of when I first tried Neopets. I was disappointed to find that interaction with the pets was limited to static interaction rather than real-time, animated interactions.</p>

<p>Although the visuals of the CheckiO world seem to be geared towards attracting a younger crowd, that potential user base will be deterred by the detachment of said world. Try as they might, the creators of CheckiO fail to make the world, the backstory, the characters, etc. feel relevant when facing a coding challenge. It’s kind of like how some action movies and video games have plots that barely exist because the creators focused more on the action than the story. I get the sense that the creators of CheckiO are actually trying hard to make their story feel relevant, but it’s just not working for me.</p>

<p>In other words, CheckiO wants to prevent users from thinking it’s just another site full of coding challenges by showering the experience with cool graphics and a backstory. They want you to think it’s an edutainment experience rather than a purely academic one. They want you to think CheckiO is a game rather than a series of assignment akin to homework, but it just doesn’t feel like a video game.</p>

<p>The bulk of the experience is not something that could be described as “gameplay.” The in-browser IDE screams “boring” when compared to the home screen presented after logging in. This is a big bummer because everything you see leading up to a coding challenge makes you think you’re about to see something really cool and interactive. It actually makes me think I’m about to see a mini-game. Instead, you end up setting your eyes on a very unappealing IDE.</p>

<p>Despite its attempts to the contrary, CheckiO is just another site full of coding challenges. The challenges are fun for people who already enjoy programming, but the site just doesn’t live up to its potential to reach out to a new, bigger, untapped audience. The user experience really needs to be remade to properly engage users quickly. Instead, it leaves you a bit confused because it looks like a site full of features and gamification, but you can’t quite figure out how to enjoy the benefits.</p>

<p>Given the current success earned by CheckiO, I have a feeling more patient yields more rewards when using the site, but I still have a hard time imagining that “coding on CheckiO” could ever be described as “playing CheckiO.” I feel bad to give CheckiO a thumbs down because they’re the type of underdog with the type of good intentions that I want to support.</p>

<h2 id="woo">Woo!</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Thriving international community</li>
  <li>Fun coding challenges</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="boo">Boo!</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Long load times</li>
  <li>Tangled navigation</li>
  <li>Omg bubbly/glassy UI is so 2009 duh</li>
  <li>Solutions not displayed for first few challenges (even after you pass them)</li>
  <li>The weird capitalization in the brand name “CheckiO” bothers me :p</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
