<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | Jeff: Rebooted]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-25T17:17:26-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ready. Set. Octopress.]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/08/02/ready-set-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T17:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/08/02/ready-set-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="last-updated">Last updated: Aug 10th, 2013</p>

<h1 id="here-we-go">Here We Go</h1>
<p>Dammit. I’ve made so many tweaks and adjustments, but I still haven’t gotten this blog looking quite right. I’m about to get nerdy, so <a href="#whats-next">jump down</a> if you have no sympathy for programmer growing pains.</p>

<p>FYI, I’m using <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> to create this blog, <a href="https://github.com/RebootJeff">github</a> to host, and I write posts/pages in a little language called <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/Markdown/">Markdown</a>. Maybe I should’ve just created a WordPress blog, but I admit I fell victim to Octopress’s tagline: “A blogging framework for hackers.”</p>

<p>Some of you non-tech geeks may raise an eyebrow at the term “hacker,” but it’s really <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/gba.html">not as evil as you think</a>. The word embodies a more jargon-y connotation as well as the archetype portrayed in the media. In this case, Octopress is appealing to the techy DIY folks who like to have a lot of control over their creations (even at the expense of convenience…as is definitely the case for me).</p>

<h2 id="the-tweaks-never-end">The Tweaks Never End</h2>
<p>I began customizing this blog by adding a lovely Octopress theme. I then tweaked the hell out of it. You can compare and contrast by checking out the theme’s <a href="http://www.adrianartiles.com/">original implementation</a>. My changes customized the color scheme, the background image, the size of the hero (i.e., cover photo area on the home page), the Twitter widget, the footer, navigation links, etc.</p>

<p>The customization process was tough because I had never seen a <a href="https://github.com/Shopify/liquid/wiki/Liquid-for-Designers">Liquid</a> setup before. Also, I’m fairly new to git, Ruby, and the other bits involved in an Octopress-powered blog. I had to delete, re-install, and re-clone more times than I care to disclose.</p>

<p><del>But I’m still not done. I still need to tweak the colors and the background image. I want a green theme because I think green is under-used. Unfortunately, it clashes with certain Markdown parts. I switched my blog’s Markdown engine to <a href="https://github.com/vmg/redcarpet">Redcarpet</a>, but I still get gross code blocks and lists. I tried using <a href="https://github.com/nono/Jekyll-plugins/blob/master/redcarpet2_markdown.rb">a Redcarpet plugin</a>, but that threw errors during the <code>rake generate</code> process. I tried <a href="http://blog.alestanis.com/2013/02/04/octopress-and-the-twilight-color-scheme/">kramdown</a> with a sweet <a href="https://github.com/danielpietzsch/CodeRay-GitHub-Theme">CodeRay theme</a>, but that setup completely ignored code blocks, block quotes, etc. I need help!</del></p>

<h3 id="update-aug-10-2013">Update! (Aug 10, 2013)</h3>
<p>I used <a href="http://html5devgal.com/blog/2013/06/08/octopress-toc-and-coderay-codeblocks/">HTML5 Dev Gal</a>’s helpful instructions and links to finally implement the alliterative combo of Kramdown and CodeRay. I also realized how to add custom CSS to specifically address lists created via the Markdown engine.</p>

<p>So hooray! Lists and Code blocks are no longer given a ridiculous dark blue background! And why were lists given a background anyway?</p>

<p>Sadly, <a href="http://kramdown.rubyforge.org/converter/html.html#toc">automatic TOCs</a> don’t seem to work. I also still need to figure out how to add autolinking, which works in stock Octopress, but once modified to use kramdown, shit’s broken?</p>

<h1 id="tldr">TL;DR</h1>
<p>I’m whining about how difficult it can be to use a DIY path, but it’s really helped me learn a lot. So it’s all good.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>
<p>So what can you expect on this blog other than sentences that probably shouldn’t start with the word “so”?</p>

<h3 id="past">Past</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Difficulties of my cross-country move</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="present">Present</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Chronicles of my career change</li>
  <li>Short reviews</li>
  <li>Compilations of cool links I’ve found</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="future">Future</h3>
<ul>
  <li>My goals, targets, milestones</li>
  <li>My thoughts on the future of tech, cars, gaming, music, tennis, and more</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
