<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bootcamp research | Jeff: Rebooted]]></title>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/categories/bootcamp-research/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-04T01:11:16-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Lee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Coding Bootcamp Research] How to Compare Bootcamps]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/04/coding-bootcamp-research-how-to-compare-bootcamps/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-04T01:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/09/04/coding-bootcamp-research-how-to-compare-bootcamps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-do-you-research-bootcamps">How do you research bootcamps?</h1>
<p>When you’re about to buy a car, you gather relevant data by going to KBB, Edmunds, and other sites. You read editorial reviews and watch video reviews. You can investigate possible issues by searching forums and recall databases.</p>

<p>When comparing cars, you consider fuel economy, reliability, style, and niceties. When comparing any big expenditure, you consider price and value. As for determining which aspects of a car really matter to you the most, it’s pretty intuitive to just think about your daily life.</p>

<p>So what do you do when “shopping” for a coding bootcamp? It’s a lot like shopping for cars, choosing a university, or making any other big decision: it’s time-consuming, it can be overwhelming, and there’s a ton of info for your consideration. However, it’s pretty easy to learn how to research cars and colleges thanks to the abundance of resources out there –but bootcamps are new, so it’s no surprise that learning how to research them seems mysterious. I’m going to help you.</p>

<p>When I started looking at coding bootcamps, I wasn’t sure what to do other than basic Googling and looking at compay websites. This blog post serves as an examination of how to examine bootcamps.</p>

<h1 id="what-factors-should-you-consider">What factors should you consider?</h1>
<p>I’m not claiming you need to thoroughly analyze every item in the list below. Just like any other big decision, you need to prioritize various factors based on your own preferences and needs.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Curriculum:</strong> What will you learn? How will you learn it?
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Technical Skills:</strong>
  Which programming languages will be taught? What tools of the trade will you learn? What about Test Driven Development (TDD)? How many frameworks will you be exposed to?</li>
      <li><strong>Non-Tech Skills:</strong> Does the bootcamp cover job interview prep? Paired programming? Presentation experience? Resume workshops? Listening skills?</li>
      <li><strong>Intensity:</strong> How much time is devoted to various topics? How difficult is the bootcamp relative to other bootcamps?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Faculty:</strong> How many teachers are employed by the bootcamp? What qualifies them to teach you and earn your money?</li>
  <li><strong>Job Placement:</strong> Other than teaching you relevant skills, how can a bootcamp help you get a job?
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Alumni Success:</strong> What kinds of careers have previous students earned after attending the bootcamp (employment rate)?</li>
      <li><strong>Network:</strong> How well-connected is the bootcamp? How many employers are in touch with the program?</li>
      <li><strong>Image:</strong> What kind of reputation does course have? Are employers familiar with the brand?</li>
      <li><strong>Initiatives:</strong> Does the bootcamp conduct a hiring day? How many employers show up to the hiring day? Does the bootcamp offer job interview training? Does the bootcamp have a staff member dedicated to helping you find a job?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Schedule:</strong> Is there any flexibility in when you work? Are there any days off? Holidays?
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Typical Day:</strong> Students often dedicate more than 8 hours per day, but what about faculty? Will the long hours make it difficult to commute?</li>
      <li><strong>Start &amp; End Dates:</strong> Do you want to get started right away? If so, the start date surely matters. The end date might affect your ability to find a job ASAP. What if the end date is right around the end of employers’ fiscal years?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Cost:</strong> How does a bootcamp’s price compare to its competitors? Why did they choose a particular price?
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Payment Plans:</strong> What’s the initial deposit? Do you pay in chunks, or all at once upfront? Can you defer payment until after a certain date?</li>
      <li><strong>Discounts:</strong> Are there any scholarships for minorities/females? Are there any refunds or partial refunds upon getting hired by their employer network?</li>
      <li><strong>Value:</strong> How much faculty time do you get for your money? Does the bootcamp provide computers? Does the bootcamp provide extra nice office space?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Facilities:</strong> Speaking of office space, are the facilities boring, or do they add to the learning experience? Where are they located? Will the location involve high commute costs? How feasible is it to live in a hostel near the bootcamp?</li>
  <li><strong>Character:</strong> Does the bootcamp feel like a startup, a corporate player, or an amateur hour?
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Personalities:</strong> What’s the culture like? Do they welcome total noobs, or do they demand demonstrable coding experience?</li>
      <li><strong>Long-Term Vision:</strong> How does the bootcamp treat its alumni? Does the bootcamp plan on expanding its territory or re-investing in a single location?</li>
      <li><strong>Extras &amp; Perks:</strong> Free wifi? Duh. Free lunch? Oh nice. Organized outings? Sports? Happy hours? Guest lectures from industry experts?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="how-do-you-prioritize-factors">How do you prioritize factors?</h1>
<p>Not only do you want to know what factors to consider, but you also want to know how much you should care.</p>

<p>For factors like cost and location of facilities, it’s obvious how to think about their impacts relative to your life. For factors such as curriculum and long-term vision, it can be hard to figure out what matters to you. Should you look for a bootcamp that focuses on Ruby on Rails or Python with Django? Should you believe it when people say picking a programming language doesn’t matter?</p>

<p>Other factors might actually surprise you once you dig into them. For example, it might bother you to find out that some of your tuition/time is being spent on <a href="http://devbootcamp.com/2013/01/30/yoga-panic-pandas-3-things-you-might-not-expect-from-a-programming-bootcamp/">mandatory yoga</a> classes.</p>

<p>(For the record, I like the idea of mandatory yoga, but I’ve seen <a href="http://qr.ae/IL5Mc">negative reactions</a> to the fact.)</p>

<p>I will try to explore the question of “how do you prioritize factors?” in much greater details in upcoming blog posts that focus on a few factors at a time.</p>

<h1 id="how-do-you-gather-info">How do you gather info?</h1>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Bootcamp website:</strong> Most bootcamp websites provide an overview of curriculum, tuition, etc. They don’t always do a good job of telling you the quality of their faculty or the typical day schedule.</li>
  <li><strong>Comparison sites:</strong> A pair of new websites have been created to help you compare bootcamps by providing spec sheets. They don’t do a good job of providing info on bootcamp culture. What’s nice is that they have reviews, but the reviews basically feel like Quora comments.
    <ul>
      <li><a href="http://bootcamps.in">bootcamps.in</a>: Has a few helpful articles and a big list of self-education resources.</li>
      <li><a href="http://bootcamper.io">bootcamper.io</a>: No articles, but cleaner aesthetics and better layout.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Quora:</strong> This is a fantastic resource if you want to hear from both students and co-founders. I’ve seen a lot of posts by founders of Dev Bootcamp, RocketU, Hack Reactor, and a few non-San Francisco bootcamps. Some posts feel like advertisements, but some feel like authentic, honest nuggets of insight.</li>
  <li><strong>Student blogs:</strong> There are a lot of blogs out there by current and former students. They often cover curriculum details. They sometimes talk about bootcamp culture. It’s nice to read success stories, but you might also find tales of unfulfilled expectations.</li>
  <li><strong>YouTube and Vimeo:</strong> Searching for videos can help you find out more about a bootcamp’s facilities, student personalities, etc.</li>
  <li><strong>Admissions interviews:</strong> These are going to be your best chance to get your questions answered about typical day schedule, payment options, job placement, etc. Just keep in mind that the answers are biased.</li>
</ul>

<p>You can also find press coverage of bootcamps, but I’ve found that they generally fail to give you much insight. Most articles are just explaining what a coding bootcamp is. Some press coverage involves video interviews and whatnot. Those are worth watching because even though they’re edited fluff pieces, they still give a glimpse into personalities and facilities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hack Reactor is my future]]></title>
    <link href="http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/08/25/hack-reactor-is-my-future/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T15:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RebootJeff.github.io/blog/2013/08/25/hack-reactor-is-my-future</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have enrolled in the September 23, 2013 cohort of <a href="http://hackreactor.com">Hack Reactor</a> (aka HackR), which is a 12-week coding bootcamp (or “academy” as they say) located in downtown San Francisco. I will pay them thousands of dollars so I can spend about 72-80 hours/week training, learning, and exploring –all in an attempt to gain the skills of a software developer (with a focus on web tech).</p>

<h1 id="hold-up-whats-a-coding-bootcamp">Hold up. What’s a coding bootcamp?</h1>
<p>Coding bootcamps are training courses that teach students the fundamentals needed to become immediately employable in some field of programming (generally web development, but some bootcamps focus on smartphone apps). Most bootcamps require full-time commitment (you must quit your job) and are pretty intense. Students generally “work” for more than 40 hours per week.</p>

<p>I put “work” in quotes because it in this case, I’m using the word to cover many different things that happen in a typical day at a bootcamp. Students listen to lectures by faculty and guest speakers. Students program in pairs. Students study and complete assignments. Most importantly, students get a ton of hands-on learning experience. Bootcamp curriculae typically involve projects that help students establish a portfolio of apps.</p>

<p>Bootcamps are a great option for people who want to switch from a non-computer science career to a programming-heavy career. That said, there will be some CS grads in some bootcamps because college often neglects to teach relevant hard skills like how to use git.</p>

<p>Coding bootcamps are also called programming bootcamps, developer/dev bootcamps, etc. The term “bootcamp” is sometimes replaced with “immersive course” or just “immersive.”</p>

<p>Check out this video to get a sense of the Hack Reactor vibe:</p>

<iframe width="300" height="169" src="http://RebootJeff.github.io//www.youtube.com/embed/ko9bXImNirE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h1 id="why-pick-hack-reactor">Why pick Hack Reactor?</h1>
<p>In the coming days and weeks, I am going to extensively blog about my experience researching different bootcamps in a series unsurprisingly entitled <a href="/blog/categories/bootcamp-research/">Coding Bootcamp Research</a>. The series will cover all the ins and outs of how I examined my options, the admissions processes, and my decision to choose HackR over its competitors.</p>

<p>To give you the gist of it, I chose HackR because it seems to produce the smartest bootcamp “grads” through a combination of high quality faculty/curriculum and lots of time. What I mean by “lots of time” is that faculty are on the clock from 9am-8pm x 6 days/week instead of the typical 9am-6pm x 5 days/week found at other bootcamps.</p>

<p>The claim that HackR has the best grads is backed up by…more claims. They claim that 100% of their grads find a developer job within 3 months after graduation. They claim that the average starting salary of their alumni is somewhere around $100,000 (I don’t remember the exact dollar amount because the raw amount matters less than how high it ranks). No other bootcamps claim to have such high levels of success.</p>

<p>Why should I believe Hack Reactor? Because I trust them. And I would normally litter such claims in my blog with relevant links, but the previous few paragraphs lack links because I will simply discuss these things in much greater detail in future blog posts.</p>

<p>I have a lot to say regarding HackR’s pros and cons. I have a lot to say about the pros and cons of App Academy, Coding Dojo, General Assembly, Dev Bootcamp, and the brand new RocketU as well. So stay tuned.</p>

<h1 id="so-what-now">So… what now?</h1>
<p>I have about a month of funemployment left before HackR dominates my life. During that time, I have to deal with financial concerns, HackR introductory homework, and my own personal goals.</p>

<h2 id="money-money-money-moneyey">Money, money, money (moneyey!)</h2>
<p>This is about to get a bit personal, so prepare thyself.</p>

<p>I need to deal with tuition. $2,000 down. $15,780 to go. In the word of the great philosopher, Bart Simpson: “Eep.” Luckily, my mom has offered to cover my tuition. At first, I was reluctant to accept. After all, I have the money…sort of (most of my money is in stocks). I wouldn’t have much left over if I paid tuition myself, but the real reason I hesitated to accept my mom’s generosity was based on principle.</p>

<p>I like being independent in many ways. Financial independence is one of those ways.</p>

<p>I often question what my mom thinks rather than just accepting her ideas at face value. I changed my mind about her offer by using a thought process I use whenever I encounter this questioning that routinely visits my mind. The process is simple. I ask myself, <strong>“How would I feel if I were the parent?”</strong> Obviously, I easily consider what happens when I’m the child. So when I consider the parent perspective, I can be imagine being a parent considering the child perspective too.</p>

<p>But let’s not get too cyclical/meta because I was telling a story that actually has an ending.</p>

<p>As I thought about things from the view of my hypothetical, futuristic, child-rearing mind, I realized that if I were in my mom’s shoes, I would very much want my son to accept my money. The reason? Principle.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>OMG @RebootJeff just paradoxed himself #WTF #ICallBS #hypocrisy</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Shut up and listen. You can posit that I’m merely rationlizing a money-grubbing stance, and I know that’s what it looks like, but I hold myself obligated to meet the same standards and expectations when I’m finally a parent. In this case, the expectation I’m talking about is the responsibility (and deep desire) to help my child <del>become a Neil deGrasse Tyson badass</del> get really awesome education.</p>

<p>Not to mention, my family has that traditional Asian risk-aversion baked into its collective mind. However, as my mom pointed out, pursuing fantastic educational opportunities shouldn’t be considered a (financial) risk to avoid if the parent can help out.</p>

<h2 id="the-curriculum-begins-now">The curriculum begins now</h2>
<p>There are a few tasks to accomplish prior to the first day of class other than making HackR rich(er). The bootcamp’s pre-course work requires about 90 hours of dedication (about 50 hours mandatory + about 40 hours optional). I’ve been instructed to…</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Complete a lot of <a href="http://codeschool.com">Code School</a> tutorials (which is a bit of a bummer because I’m tired of online tutorials).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Learn more JavaScript through some TDD challenges using Jasmine and Mocha (I don’t know what these are if they’re not hot beverages).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Learn about git via various videos and tutorials (which should be easy because I already know some git).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Build a basic Twitter clone (which sounds so difficult that I can’t wait to do it –what an odd feeling).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Check out a list of optional online resources.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="my-own-pre-course-to-do-list">My own pre-course to-do list</h2>
<p>I plan on completing most of the optional pre-course work (in addition to the mandatory parts), but I also hope to make time for some other pre-course goals of mine. Maybe some are covered by the pre-course work, but here’s a comprehensive list:</p>

<h3 id="relevant">Relevant</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Watch videos re: <a href="https://tutsplus.com/course/improve-workflow-in-sublime-text-2/">Sublime Text wizadry</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Consider PAYING for Sublime Text to get rid of the money-begging feature</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Figure out regex</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Get intimate with that scary thingamabob known as <a href="http://linuxcommand.org/lc3_learning_the_shell.php">Linux shell</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Buy a notebook that is made of something called “paper”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Conform to a proper sleep schedule (makes me cry just thinking about it)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Watch more lectures from Berkeley’s <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fr-B4xHZRzY">CS169: Software as a Service</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Buy tons of snacks/drinks because I won’t have much time for grocery shopping during bootcamp weeks</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Attend lots of dev meetups, especially <a href="http://www.theodinproject.com/">Odin Project</a> meetups</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Think of how I want to make my own HackR vlog</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="not-so-relevant">Not-so-relevant</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Take one last hit of that <a href="http://www.sfr-solo.org/solo2/cgi-bin/schedaction.cgi?autox&amp;where=all&amp;Next_three_months">autocross</a> high</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Finish reading some rather <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Batman-Robin-Vol-Must-Die/dp/1401235085">disturbing-but-amazing Batman</a> comic books</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Deactivate my online dating profiles because I won’t have time for that crap (although it’s not like I was a total playa to begin with)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Help a roommate build a new PC (he’s never built one before)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make at least 1 more faux vlog episode</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make at least 1 music recording</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Most of all, I want to write up a LOT of blog posts documenting all the research I did when investigating coding bootcamps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
